<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discourse concerning the worship of the Blessed Virgin and the saints with an account of the beginnings and rise of it amongst Christians, in answer to M. de Meaux's appeal to the fourth age, in his Exposition and pastoral letter.</title>
            <author>Clagett, William, 1646-1688.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1686</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 252 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 62 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A33211</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C4384</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R171370</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12379537</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12379537</idno>
            <idno type="VID">60697</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A33211)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 60697)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 655:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discourse concerning the worship of the Blessed Virgin and the saints with an account of the beginnings and rise of it amongst Christians, in answer to M. de Meaux's appeal to the fourth age, in his Exposition and pastoral letter.</title>
                  <author>Clagett, William, 1646-1688.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 114, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Tho. Bassett ... and Tho. Newborough ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1686.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: p. 114.</note>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. [1]-[2] at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Mary, --  Blessed Virgin, Saint --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Bossuet, Jacques Bénigne, 1627-1704. --  Exposition de la doctrine de l'Eglise catholique sur les matières de controverse.</term>
               <term>Saints --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:60697:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>IMPRIMAT<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>R.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Car. Alſton,</signed> 
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Maii</hi> 10. 1686.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:60697:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DISCOURSE Concerning the Worſhip OF THE <hi>Bleſſed Uirgin</hi> AND THE SAINTS; WITH An Account of the Beginnings and Riſe of it amongſt CHRISTIANS, in Anſwer to M. de <hi>Meaux</hi>'s Appeal to the <hi>Fourth Age,</hi> in his <hi>Expoſition</hi> and <hi>Paſtoral Letter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho. Baſſett</hi> at the <hi>George</hi> in <hi>Fleetſtreet,</hi> and <hi>Tho. Newborough</hi> at the <hi>Star</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard, 1686.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:60697:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:60697:2"/>
            <head>OF The Worſhip of the B. Virgin AND The SAINTS.</head>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>§. 1.</head>
               <p>THE Gentlemen of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> have been pleaſed lately to ſend Books amongſt us of a very different ſtrain: On the one ſide <hi>Popery Miſrepreſented and Repreſented,</hi> but eſpecially Monſieur <hi>de Ms.</hi> Expoſition of the <hi>Roman</hi> Doctrine: On the other ſide our Ladies <hi>Roſary,</hi> and the <hi>Contemplation of her Life and Glory,</hi> &amp;c. which go up and down, though not ſo openly as the other. And we believe they have Books in readineſs, to explain over again their Meaning in the other Articles (treated of in the <hi>Expoſition</hi>) at the ſame rate, that their Books of particular Devotion to our Lady, do explain the Articles of <hi>Religious</hi> Worſhip, and <hi>Invocation of Saints.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the mean time they ſeem to believe, that there are no Articles will bear a Repreſentation in their true Colours, ſooner or better than theſe. And the truth is, as Mankind has in all Ages been very prone to Superſtition, ſo to no kind of it more than to that of Worſhipping <hi>Dead Men and Women;</hi> which being the Practice they would reconcile us
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:60697:3"/>to, in the firſt place, we are concerned the more throughly to examine, what they now think fit to ſay for it.</p>
               <p>But let no man think, that in this Cauſe, we are engaged againſt the Saints departed, becauſe we contend with their Worſhippers. Let no Man take our Refuſal to honor them, as their Worſhippers honor them, for an argument that we do not honor them at all. We are content to be tryed by that known Rule of St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> that <hi>they are to be honor'd for Imitation, not to be adored for Religion.</hi> We believe, that the higheſt honor we can do them, is to follow their Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples. We love their Memories, we celebrate Anniverſary Commemorations of their Piety and Virtues, eſpecially of their Sufferings for Righteousneſs ſake; we congratulate their Victories over the World; we rejoyce in their Glory and Happineſs; we propound their Examples to the Imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the Faithful, exciting them to live as the Saints once lived, that they at length may inherit thoſe <hi>Promiſes,</hi> which <hi>by their Faith and Patience</hi> in this World, the Saints now <hi>inherit</hi> in the other; we praiſe God for them, as often as we meet together at the Holy Table of our Lord: And when we meet to interr our Chriſtian Brethren, we pray to God <hi>to haſten his Kingdom, that we with all thoſe that are departed in the true Faith of his Holy Name, may have our perfect Conſummation and Bliſs, both in Body and Soul, in his everlaſting Glory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus we honor the departed Saints, remembring all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long, that though they are highly exalted above us, who are here below impriſon'd in earthly Bodies, and ſtrugling in a ſinful World with Infirmities and Temptations; we yet belong to the ſame Body, of which they are Members, and that they are ſtill our Fellow-Servants. We are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, they have not leſs but rather more Charity for us, than they had for the Church, when they lived upon the Earth; but whether they know us in particular or not, or
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:60697:3"/>in what inſtances they expreſs their Charity towards us, God having made no Revelations of theſe things; we can define nothing about them; and therefore we dare not give them thoſe Honors, which ſuppoſe ſuch an Aſſurance of theſe things, as God hath thought fit to deny us.</p>
               <p>As to the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> in particular, we do with Men and Angels acknowledge, that ſhe was <hi>Bleſſed amongst Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> ſince ſhe brought forth the Saviour of Mankind, and the Lord of Heaven and Earth; ſince ſhe was not the <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> only, but the <hi>Virgin Mother</hi> alſo of our Lord, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived him by the Power of the Holy Ghoſt. Which Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion ſo honourable to her being inſeparable from a right Belief concerning our Lord <hi>Jeſus,</hi> we do not only ſet it forth upon the Anniverſary of the <hi>Annuntiation,</hi> but fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently alſo in our <hi>Sermons,</hi> and daily in the <hi>Creed</hi> More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, we take theſe ſingular Graces of God towards her, in Conjunction with other things of a more common quality: We doubt not, but ſhe was an excellently Pious and Virtuous Perſon.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 1.</note> We ſee by her Behaviour, when the Angel <hi>Gabriel</hi> came to her, that ſhe was not apt to be impoſed upon by counterfeit Viſions and Revelations; nor forward to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve great things of her ſelf; nor lifted up with Pride, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſhe was ſo highly Favoured; but that upon this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary occaſion, ſhe wholly reſigned her Self to the diſpoſal of God, with a Wiſdom and Humility, that could not but be habitual. But if nothing at all had been ſaid of her perſonal Qualities in the Scriptures (as indeed there is but very little;) we might have preſumed without Raſhneſs, that becauſe God (who has no leſs regard to a holy Mind then to a pure Body) would have the Mother of our Lord to retain the Purity of a Virgin, he would alſo chuſe a moſt holy Virgin to be his Mother; and ſince he was pleaſed to ſend us ſo Heavenly a Treaſure in an Earthen Veſſel, he would chuſe one of the greateſt Honor. For
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:60697:4"/>which reaſon likewiſe, we might have concluded without other Teſtimony, that ſhe became afterwards a faithful Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of her Son. For when one in admiration of him cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out, <hi>Bleſsed is the Womb that bare thee, and the Paps that gave thee Suck. Yea rather,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>Bleſſed are they that hear the word of God, and keep it:</hi> without which Bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs ſhe that bore him in her Womb, and nouriſhed him at her Breaſts, would have been juſtly eſteemed by all <hi>ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerations,</hi> the moſt unhappy and miſerable Creature in the World. Finally, from all this we cannot but conclude, that ſhe is very happy and glorious in the Kingdom of Heaven. For though we have no particular Revelations concerning this, to warrant any Compariſons of her ſtate, with that of <hi>Angels</hi> and <hi>Archangels;</hi> yet upon general Reaſons we may ſay, with ſufficient aſſurance, That her Rewards and Glories in Heaven are exceeding great, and ſuch as hold propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, not only with her Faith and Patience (for as ſome think ſhe ſuffered Martyrdom;) but likewiſe with that Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, which God was pleaſed to confer upon her in this World.</p>
               <p>Now if any thing remains, whereby to expreſs the Tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs we have for the honor of the <hi>B. Virgin,</hi> it is this, That we ſhould do what we can to redeem her Name, from that diſhonorable Imputation of affecting Glories, that cannot belong to the moſt Excellent Creature, that is but a Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. For they who by moſt ſolemn Rites of Religious Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice addreſs to her, as to the <hi>Queen of Heaven and Earth,</hi> would make us believe, and pretend to believe themſelves, that ſhe is pleaſed with that Worſhip, which they offer to her. But if, as we ſay, they yield to her thoſe Services, which no Creature is to receive; they do by conſequence repreſent her as a <hi>Lady,</hi> that aſpires to the Glory of the Moſt High; which is by no means for the Glory of the <hi>B. Virgin.</hi> And if their Saint-Worſhip be liable to the ſame charge, thus alſo
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:60697:4"/>they repreſent the other Saints. Now thô in oppoſing their Doctrine and Practice, we are principally moved, by that Concern we ought to have for the Glory of our Creator and Saviour; yet it is ſome inducement to us ſo to do, that we ſhall thereby vindicate the <hi>B. Virgin</hi> alſo, and all the glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied Saints. For if ſhe knows what paſſes amongſt Mortals, ſhe cannot but be diſpleaſed at thoſe Services, that have been and ſtill are paid to her, by ſome of her Son's Diſciples; and if ſhe ſaid any thing at all to 'em, ſhe would ſay to her Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries, but with greater indignation, what the Angel ſaid to St. <hi>John</hi> falling at his feet to worſhip him,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.10.</note> 
                  <hi>See thou do it not: I am thy Fellow-Servant: Worſhip God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſame I ſay of the Angels, the Apoſtles, the Martyrs and all the Saints, whom they honor with the ſame kind of Worſhip, that they give to the <hi>B. Virgin.</hi> Only the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of her Worſhip, and the Frequency of their Addreſſes to her, and the ſtrength of their Confidence in her is ſo much greater, that they have thought fit to invent a word of Art to expreſs it by. <hi>Hyperdulia</hi> they call it; a word which our people cannot underſtand better, then by knowing the Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice which it is a name for.</p>
               <p>It is ſo vaſt a proportion of Religious Service which they render to her, it conſiſts of ſo many Parts and Diverſities, that it were a Labour to recount them, as particularly as the Caſe would bear. It ſhall ſuffice to mention ſome of the principal Heads. They worſhip her with Religious Prayers and Vows. They erect Churches and Oratories for her Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice; where they worſhip her very Images and Pictures, and pretended Reliques. They make Roſaries, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe Hours, Pſalters, and other Forms of Devotion to her. They ask things of her, that are proper to be asked of God only. They burn Incenſe to her Images, and offer their very Sacrifice of the Maſs in her Honor.</p>
               <p>Now as to this, and all the reſt, we cannot but ſtand
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:60697:5"/>amazed, that this Service of the B. Virgin ſhould grow to be one of the principal parts of their Religion; when the H. Scriptures have not given us the leaſt intimation of Rule or Example for it, or of any Doctrine or Practice that leads to it. That it ſhould be a main deſign of their Catechiſmes, to inſtruct Youth in the Worſhip of the B. Virgin; of their Sermons to excite the People to put Confidence in her, and to call upon her for the preſent occaſion; of their Books of Devotion to direct them how to pray to her, and magnify her in Formal Invocations; of their Confeſſors to injoyn Penitents to ſay ſo many <hi>Ave Maries,</hi> in ſatisfaction for their ſins and to make at leaſt as frequent Applications to <hi>Mary</hi> as to <hi>Jeſus</hi> himſelf, for deliverance from Sins and Dangers: When not one word, not one Intimation of any thing, like to any thing of all this, is left upon record in the Writings of the <hi>Evangeliſts</hi> and <hi>Apoſtles;</hi> from whom thoſe men pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to derive their Religion; whoſe Books are large enough for this ſo famous a Service, to have been at leaſt mentioned ſomewhere or other; and who, without all doubt, would have more then mentioned it, if it had been the Religion of thoſe Times. This is that we muſt always wonder at, and ſo much the more, becauſe the conſtant Tenor of the Holy Scriptures, bears againſt ſuch Practices as theſe, agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably to that Precept of both Teſtaments, <hi>Thou ſhalt worſhip the Lord thy God, and him only ſhalt thou ſerve.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And indeed our Reaſons, to keep at a diſtance from this worſhip of the B. Virgin and the Saints, are ſo obvious and commonly known, that I ſhall not make it a Buſineſs by it ſelf to repreſent them. But theſe two things I ſhall conſider, as well as I can;</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>The plauſible Expoſitions and Colours, by which they have tryed of late to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uſtify themſelves in theſe things.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>What were the B ginnings of this kind of Worſhip amongſt</hi> Chriſtians, <hi>and by what ſteps it is grown to that height, in
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:60697:5"/>which we now ſee it.</hi> I ſhall conſider the former in a narrow compaſs, becauſe much has been ſaid to it already. The latter is what I chiefly deſign.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>§. 2.</head>
               <p>IN purſuance of the firſt thing propounded, I ſhall parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly obſerve how <hi>Monſieur de Meaux</hi> hath expound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed theſe Matters, under the heads of <hi>Religious Worſhip,</hi> of <hi>Invocation of Saints,</hi> and <hi>giving honor to Images and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques.</hi> But I ſhall begin with the two latter, becauſe he expounds theſe particularly; and then I ſhall conſider the general Defence he makes, for all the Religious Worſhip they give to the B. Virgin, and to the Saints.</p>
               <p>The Worſhip of Invocation, is the Foundation of a great many other things done in her Service. For inſtance, It is this that hath brought forth the <hi>Roſary,</hi> the <hi>Pſalters,</hi> the <hi>Hours,</hi> and all other <hi>Offices</hi> of Devotion to her. It is this that hath raiſed her <hi>Shrines,</hi> and built <hi>Oratories</hi> and <hi>Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pels</hi> for her eſpecial Service. And indeed, if ſhe as well as God is to be worſhipped with Prayers and Hymns, it is but reaſonable, that ſhe ſhould have her <hi>holy Places</hi> for ſuch Services, as well as God. And yet St.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cont. Maxim. Arian. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 11.</note> 
                  <hi>Auſtin</hi> thought the <hi>erecting of Temples to be ſo proper an act of Divine Worſhip that if we ſhould do it to the moſt excellent Angel, we ſhould be anathematized from the Church of</hi> God. Whereas there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our Churches are known from one another in <hi>Cities</hi> and populous <hi>Towns,</hi> by the names of ſeveral Saints; yet we profeſs that, however for diſtinction ſake they are ſo called, they are <hi>God</hi>'s Houſes and Oratories, and not theirs; and it is moſt manifeſt, that they are uſed by us for his Worſhip, and not for theirs, in whole or in part.</p>
               <p>The Invocation of the B. <hi>Virgin</hi> and the <hi>Saints,</hi> has run out into ſome Exceſſes, from which they might have
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:60697:6"/>ſeparated it; and therefore to theſe Exceſſes I ſhall ſay but little, eſpecially becauſe they defend them very faintly, and with great appearances of ſelf-Condemnation.</p>
               <p>It was too much in all reaſon, that the Council of <hi>Trent</hi>
                  <note n="(a)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Seſſ.</hi> 25. <hi>de Invoc. S. Bellar. de ſanct. Beatit. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 20.</note> allowed of <hi>Mental,</hi> as well as <hi>Vocal,</hi> Prayers to be made to the Saints; for this aſcribes to them the Knowledge of the Secrets of Hearts. And 'tis a very faint Plea for this which Monſieur de <hi>Meaux</hi>
                  <note n="(b)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Exp. p.</hi> 8.</note> makes in ſaying, that <hi>God did not diſdain to diſcover future things to the Prophets, tho they appear much more particularly reſerved to his own know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</hi> For this does not clear Mental Praying to the Saints, from the conſequence we charge it with, unleſs they were ſure, that as God diſcovered ſome future things to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, ſo he does alſo perpetually reveal the Prayers of our mind to the Saints. The Inſtance ſhews what is needleſs, that God can do it if he pleaſe; it does not ſhew that he does it, and that only would have been to the purpoſe.</p>
               <p>Beſides, whatever Opinion they have of the Lawfulneſs and Profitableneſs of praying to Saints, they ſhould have been very much afraid, to affirm them to be <hi>Mediators of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſion;</hi> when without any diſtinction, the Scripture does not only give to <hi>Chriſt</hi> the <hi>Quality of a Mediator,</hi> as <hi>M. de Meaux</hi>
                  <note n="(c)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Exp. p.</hi> 6.</note> grants; but likewiſe the Quality of our <hi>Only</hi> Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator, as he ſhould have granted. For as <hi>there is one God,</hi> ſo
<note n="(d)" place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.5.</note> 
                  <hi>there is one Mediator between God and Men, the Man Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> Much leſs ſhould Men have been encouraged to make immediate Applications to the <hi>Saints,</hi> more fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently than to <hi>God,</hi> or to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as if the Saints were more eaſily prevailed with by our Prayers, than our God and Saviour. Theſe Exceſſes were too notorious to be denied, but withall they were too Scandalous to be confeſſed; but in all reaſon they ought to have been ſeverely reproved. <hi>M. de Meaux</hi> would have us to obſerve, that the Council teaches, <hi>It is good and profitable</hi> to pray to the Saints.
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:60697:6"/>And we do obſerve, that tho the Fathers were not inſenſible of the extravagant Practices and Doctrines in this matter, that were currant amongſt them, yet they would not vouchſafe to note them with the leaſt Cenſure; but were content to let them go on, as they had done before.</p>
               <p>Moreover, they pray to the B. Virgin, to <hi>protect them from the Enemy,</hi> to <hi>receive them at the hour of Death,</hi> to be <hi>propitious to them,</hi> to <hi>ſpare them,</hi> to <hi>give them ſtrength,</hi> to <hi>give them grace,</hi> to <hi>open the gate of Everlaſting life to them;</hi> and for all that a good Chriſtian can ask of God. Such like Prayers do they alſo offer to the other Saints. But nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall I ſtay upon this; becauſe they do not go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to juſtifie it amongſt us, otherwiſe then by pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that they ſay what they do not mean: and that <hi>the Intention of the Church and of her Faithful,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exp.</hi> p. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>reduces theſe Prayers always to this Form,</hi> that the Saints would pray for us. Now when they confeſs,
<note place="margin">p. 9.</note> that <hi>the outward Venerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is eſtabliſhed to teſtifie the inward ſentiments of the Mind,</hi> we deſire no greater evidence of ſelf-Condemnation in this Caſe, then to hear them ſay quite backward, that the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention of the Church and her Faithful, is eſtabliſht to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain the meaning of ſo conſiderable a part of their out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Worſhip. But in the mean time God help the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon People, if they are to be judged after their own Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Underſtandings, and not the Intentions and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions of ſome few Guides of their Church.</p>
               <p>To name no more of theſe Enormities; their dividing to the Saints their ſeveral Offices in their Prayers to them, is a moſt unaccountable Superſtition, <hi>i. e.</hi> That one Saint is applied to for the cure of one Diſeaſe, and another for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, and ſome peculiar things deſired of almoſt every one. For how can they perſwade us, that they deſire no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of the Saints, but the help of their Prayers, when they attribute to each Saint his particular Vertue and Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er;
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:60697:7"/>unleſs they think that St. <hi>Apollonia</hi>'s Interceſſion is not as effectual againſt the Gout, as the Tooth-ach?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>§. 3.</head>
               <p>But ſetting aſide theſe Exceſſes, which ſeveral mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Men of their own Church have complain'd of, but all to no purpoſe; let us hear what they ſay in behalf of Praying to the B. Virgin, and to the Saints at all, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing it be for nothing, but to pray for them, as one Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture may do for another, and that they ſpeak to her and them, in Hymns and Strains, which as to the matter there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in contained, do not exalt them above the condition of Creatures: In one word, why they addreſs to her, and the reſt of the Saints, with any ſort of formal Invocation.</p>
               <p>We dare not do this, becauſe we believe Prayer to be an Eſſential Part of Gods Worſhip, inaſmuch as 'tis ſometimes put for the whole. <hi>How ſhall they call upon him, in whom they have not believed?</hi> i. e. How ſhall they ſerve and Worſhip him? 'Tis ſo incommunicable a Worſhip, that God himſelf deſcribed his own Houſe by it. <hi>My houſe ſhall be called an houſe of Prayer.</hi> And ſurely when God named his houſe, by ſome part, of that Service that was performed there, he would chuſe ſuch a part as was peculiar to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. This and much more we ſay for our ſelves.</p>
               <p>But to all that we can ſay, they give this plauſible An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer,
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                     <hi>What have they to ſay to this Prayer?</hi> Pray for us. <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> it not word for word St.</hi> Pauls? <hi>Is it more injurious to the Creator, becauſe in the ſame Spirit we addreſs to the Saints that live with him.</hi> Paſt. Let. <hi>p.</hi> 16.</note> That it makes no more againſt their practice, in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring the Prayers of their Brethren in Heaven, then againſt theirs and ours, in deſiring the Prayers of our Brethren up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Earth; and, as <hi>Monſieur de M.</hi> ſayes, that it <hi>is profitable to pray to the Saints, in the ſame Spirit of Charity, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the ſame order of Fraternal Society, which moves us to demand aſſiſtance of our Brethren living upon Earth.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exp.</hi> p. 6.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Now this is a very popular way to ſave themſelves from
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:60697:7"/>blame, but by no means ſufficient. For there is a Concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of other Reaſons to make it profitable to deſire the Prayers of our Brethren upon Earth, beſides theſe two, that <hi>they are our Brethren,</hi> and that <hi>we love one another.</hi> God has manifeſtly approved it in the Holy Scriptures; that is one Reaſon: Beſides, we are alſo ſure, that when we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire our Brethren upon Earth to pray for us, that they hear us; that is another reaſon. But neither of theſe Reaſons can be juſtly produced, to ſhew the Profitableneſs of Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Saints departed.</p>
               <p>But becauſe this is the moſt common and colourable Defence they make; I ſhall further ſhew, what may and ought to be replied to it, by the People of our Communion. They ſay, we may as lawfully deſire thoſe in Heaven to Pray for us, as thoſe on Earth. But let us then tell them, that when we ask of one another things proper to be ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, theſe Requeſts are by no means that which we under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand by <hi>Prayer,</hi> or <hi>Religious Invocation:</hi> and that them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves do not ſo account them. <hi>Monſieur de M.</hi> clearly gives them another name,
<note place="margin">p. 6.7.</note> he calls it <hi>beſeeching</hi> or <hi>demand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the aſſiſtance of our Brethren.</hi> But men of all Religions do agree, this to be a quite different thing, from that part of Religion which we call <hi>Prayer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And to make this matter ſo plain, that it can neither be miſunderſtood nor denied: Suppoſe a Man viſited with the Peſtilence, or any other dangerous Diſtemper, to deſire his Phyſitian to apply his beſt Skill to recover him: Is this Prayer or Religious Invocation? No; they will not ſay it is. But if the ſame Perſon deſires the <hi>B. Virgin,</hi> or St. <hi>Roche,</hi> or St. <hi>Sebaſtian</hi> to reſtore him to health. This they will confeſs to be Prayer. And the reaſon of the Differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is not, that the Phyſitian is deſired to help the Patient, by his skill in natural Remedies; and the Saints by their Interceſſion with God. For ſuppoſe that the Patient ſends
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:60697:8"/>for the Prieſt, and deſires him to pray for him, they will not ſay that this Deſire is a Prayer to the Prieſt, or a Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Invocation of him: They will tell you, that the Sick Man deſires or <hi>demands the aſſiſtance</hi> of the Prieſts Prayers. But ſtill if he calls upon the <hi>B. Virgin,</hi> or any of the Saints departed, to help him by their Prayers; this is properly, and in the account of Religion, praying to them. What then is the reaſon of the Difference; for here is a Requeſt made to the Prieſt and to the Saint, and the ſame Requeſt too: why is one Prayer, and the other not? Now though we ſhould not perfectly agree with our Adverſaries, about the reaſon of the Difference; yet ſo long as it is and muſt be acknowledged, that the honeſt Requeſts, we make to one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother upon Earth, are not that part of Religion which we call Prayer; but that the Requeſts, which we make to the departed Saints, are Prayer; ſo long, I ſay, as this is granted 'tis plain, That this their common Argument, <hi>It is lawful and profitable, to deſire the aſſiſtance of our Brethrens Prayers here upon Earth, and therefore it is lawful and profitable, to call upon thoſe in Heaven to aſſiſt us with their Prayers;</hi> is very deceitful. For this is as much as to ſay: Thoſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts which <hi>are not Prayer,</hi> may be lawfully made to Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; and therefore thoſe which <hi>are Prayer,</hi> may be made to Creatures, as lawfully as thoſe that are not.</p>
               <p>Now if you deſire to know, what it is in this caſe that makes the difference: I think the Anſwer is very plain. For the difference is not to be taken. 1. From the Matter of the Requeſt, for that is the ſame: Nor 2. from the Perſons themſelves to whom the requeſt is made; for if the Saint departed were here, why would my requeſting of the ſame thing, be Prayer to him, and not to the Prieſt? And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore 3. It muſt neceſſarily lye in the different Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Prieſt, and the Saint; that the former is with me, and the latter is abſent from me. Requeſts made to the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:60697:8"/>
                  <hi>Faithful,</hi> are made to thoſe that are <hi>within the compaſs of civil Converſation:</hi> But the ſame Requeſts made to the <hi>B. Virgin</hi> and the <hi>Saints,</hi> are made to thoſe that are departed out of the compaſs of civil Converſation. And this is that which makes them not to be Prayer in the former caſe, and to be Prayer in the latter.</p>
               <p>But if it be further inquired, why it is <hi>Prayer</hi> to ask the ſame things of thoſe that are diſtant from civil Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which to ask of thoſe that are within the compaſs of it, is <hi>not Prayer?</hi> The Reaſon ſeemes plainly to be this, That when I addreſs my ſelf to one that is within the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs of civil Converſation, in which Men uſe to hear or to underſtand one another; my Aſſurance that he hears me, does no way aſcribe to him a Knowledge or a Preſence, which is <hi>above the Condition of a Creature.</hi> But if I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke the <hi>Saints</hi> every where with Aſſurance that they hear me; I have no other reaſonable ground of ſuch Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance, then that they are every where preſent at the ſame time: For if I acknowledge, that there is a certain limited Compaſs, within which they can hear and know; let this Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit be never ſo wide, how can I be aſſured, that they are not out of that Compaſs when I ſpeak to them? But the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> pray every where to every <hi>Saint,</hi> believing that they are heard. <hi>It is certain,</hi> ſays one of them,
<note n="(e)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Bellar. de ſanct. Beat. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 20.</note> 
                  <hi>that the Saints know what we bring forth by the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of the Heart only.</hi>
                  <note n="(f)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Peſant.</hi> 1: <hi>Thom. qu.</hi> 12. <hi>Art.</hi> 10. <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>put.</hi> 7.</note> 
                  <hi>It is of Faith,</hi> ſaith ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>that the Bleſſed know our Prayers which we pour out to them, elſe it were in vain to make them.</hi> Now a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt does undoubtedly become <hi>Prayer,</hi> or <hi>Religious In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation,</hi> when the making of it attributes any Divine Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative or Perfection, to the Being that is called upon; and therefore, becauſe Immenſity of Preſence is an incommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicable Perfection of God; and becauſe alſo Requeſts made to thoſe, that are out of all lines of civil Communication,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:60697:9"/>being made in Faith, do aſcribe that Power to them which is proper to God only: Therefore ſuch Requeſts are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly Prayer, or Religious Invocation.</p>
               <p>It is indeed very poſſible, that he that prays to the <hi>B. Virgin,</hi> and to the <hi>Saints,</hi> may not believe that they are Omni-preſent; but if he prayes, as they pretend to do in the <hi>R.</hi> Church, with Aſſurance, that they hear him, his Prayer implies it, and himſelf by Conſtruction of the Fact aſcribes it to them. For let him, if he can, produce any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reaſonable ground of Aſſurance that they hear him whereſoever and whenſoever he addreſſes to them. But inſtead of that M. <hi>de Meaux</hi> tells us, That <hi>the Church contents her ſelf to teach with All Antiquity</hi> (not all An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity I am ſure) <hi>thoſe Prayers to be very profitable to ſuch who make them, whether it be the Saints know them, by the Miniſtry and Communication of Angels, who according to the Teſtimony of the Scripture, know what paſſes amongſt us,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exp. p.</hi> 8.</note> &amp;c. <hi>whether it be, that God himſelf makes known to them our Deſires by a particular Revelation: or laſtly, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be that he diſcovers the Secret to them in his Divine Eſſence, in which all Truth is comprized.</hi> Now if his Church could have <hi>taught</hi> us, upon what grounds they are aſſured, that the Saints do hear them either, this way or that way; or that God has in general revealed to us, that they hear or know the Prayers we make to them, one way or other, and therefore, that it is profitable to pray to them; ſhe had not been <hi>content to teach,</hi> that the Saints do know them ſome way or other, though ſhe knows not how or why. For what foundation that they hear us, can be gathered from ſuch uncertain and looſe Conjectures, as theſe are? Can any Man convince me that a thing is done, by telling me that it might be done by ſome way or other, for any thing he knows to the contrary? And is this kind of Arguing, a ſufficient Ground to eſtabliſh ſo ſolemn a part of Religion,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:60697:9"/>as the Invocation of Saints? I know 'tis poſſible for God to reveal to my Friend in the <hi>Eaſt-Indies,</hi> what I ſay here in <hi>England:</hi> But am I ſure, that if I ſay to him an <hi>Ora pro no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis</hi> at this diſtance, it reaches him forthwith? It were no difficult matter, if it were needful, to find them trouble enough to clear theſe very Conjectures from Abſurdity; but as long as they are only Conjectures; they can be no Foundation of a certain Perſwaſion. Whereas therefore, <hi>M. de Meaux</hi> ſays, <hi>It is manifeſt, that to ſay a Creature may have the knowledge of theſe Prayers, by a Light communicated to him by God, is not ſo elevate a Creature above his Condition.</hi> I ſay, it is as <hi>manifeſt,</hi> that this is no ground of Certainty, that the Saints hear our Prayers at all; and if this be all they have to ſay, and yet will pretend to pray to them with Faith; there is but one ground left for that Faith, <hi>viz.</hi> That the Saints are every where preſent, and are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>elevated above the Condition of Creatures:</hi> Which though ſome of themſelves do not believe, yet their Aſſurance to be heard, being altogether unreaſonable without that belief; <hi>their Prayers</hi> do give the Omni-preſence of God to Creatures, which is indeed the great reaſon, why their Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſes to the Saints are properly <hi>Prayers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This therefore I lay down, and let them remove it if they can; that to invocate any Creature, who is out of the compaſs of civil Converſation, <hi>i.e.</hi> with whom I cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe, as we do with one another, by ſpeaking within the known diſtances of Hearing, or by Writing, or Meſſages or the like, is in it ſelf a vain and fooliſh thing, becauſe he is out of diſtance. But if I pretend, that it is profitable to invoke the Saints, and this upon Aſſurance that they hear me, tho I can neither tell which way in particular, nor can ſhew in general, that they do certainly hear me ſome way, that does not infer their Omni-preſence; there is no remedy, but my Invocation of them muſt by conſequence confeſs, that they are <hi>Omnipreſent.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:60697:10"/>
               <p> Let therefore thoſe of our Communion ſay, that by calling upon God, they do acknowledge his Omni-preſence, as well as his other Infinite Perfections: and that they are ſuch Acknowledgments, which make their Invocation of God, <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ligious Invocation,</hi> or that which is <hi>Prayer</hi> in the account of Religion: And therefore, that they dare not call upon the Saints departed; becauſe they being without the compaſs of civil Converſation, or of ſuch means of Communication, as we have with one another in this World; we cannot be reaſonably aſſured, that they hear us, unleſs we will ſuppoſe them to be omni-preſent; which as we do not believe, ſo we dare not do any thing that looks as if we did believe it.</p>
               <p>Thus have I ſhewn, what in our Judgment makes the difference, between asking fit things of our Brethren upon Earth, and asking the ſame things of our Brethren in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; why one is not Prayer, and the other is; <hi>viz.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Living are within our compaſs, and the Dead are out of it. But whatever it is that makes the difference; ſince the honeſt Requeſts, we make to one another in this World, <hi>are not Prayer,</hi> and the Requeſts we make to the Saints in Heaven <hi>are Prayer;</hi> it does not follow, that we may requeſt the ſame things of <hi>Theſe,</hi> as we may of <hi>Thoſe:</hi> For if the Argument be put into proper Expreſſions, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can be more apparently inconſequent; for then it would run thus: Becauſe I make my Requeſts known to thoſe, to whom I do not offer the <hi>Religious Worſhip of Prayer</hi> in ſo doing, therefore I may repreſent my Deſires to thoſe too whom I cannot call upon, but my deſires become the <hi>Worſhip of Prayer, or Religious Invoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And from hence it appears, that tho' this Act of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Worſhip, be given by thoſe of the <hi>R.</hi> Church to the the meaneſt Saint; yet after the moſt plauſible Defence
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:60697:10"/>they make of their practice in ſo doing, it is not to be given to the moſt excellent Creature, and therefore not to the <hi>B. Virgin</hi> her ſelf. And by this we may judge, what a Cauſe they have to maintain, who call upon the <hi>Saints,</hi> and eſpecially upon the <hi>B. Virgin,</hi> in ſtrains ſo unſuitable to the condition of Creatures; as they are whom they invoke: when becauſe they are but Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, they ought not to invoke them at all, ſince they are out of that compaſs of Converſation, in which only we could ſpeak to them as to Creatures, with Faith that they hear us.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>§. 4.</head>
               <p>To come to the next particular; when they kneel to the Images of the B. Virgin and the Saints, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, and <hi>humble themſelves</hi> and Pray before them; we are given to underſtand, there is no harm in all this; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>they <hi>attribute no other vertue to the Images,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">p. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>but that of exciting the remembrances of thoſe they repreſent;</hi> and <hi>their intention is not ſo much to honor the Image,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">p. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>as to honor the Apoſtle or the Martyr in the preſence of the Image.</hi> As if the Image were <hi>preſent,</hi> to ſee and obſerve the Honour that is done the Apoſtle or Martyr: For it is no great honor that any body gets, by being honored in the preſence of mere Wood or Stone, that can neither ſee nor hear. This was an odd expreſſion of M. <hi>de Meaux,</hi> this of <hi>honoring the Martyr in the preſence of the Image,</hi> no way ſutable to the deſign of his Expoſition; but fitted only to the Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſuch People, who have been made to believe, by the <hi>weeping</hi> and <hi>ſmiling</hi> of Images, and by the <hi>rowling</hi> of their <hi>Eyes,</hi> and by the <hi>ſhaking</hi> of their <hi>Heads and Bodies,</hi> &amp;c. that they are a kind of animated things. But to let this paſs; what though M. <hi>de. Meaux attributes no other virtues to Images, but that of exciting Remembrance?</hi> What tho he
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:60697:11"/>takes a very commendable Care in his <hi>Dioceſs,</hi> to make the People ſtop there? Does he not know by experience, do not all wiſe Men know it, and many honeſt Men in the Communion of that Church confeſs it, that in thoſe Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges which the people are taught to preſent themſelves be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, with all the Ceremonies of Reſpect and Veneration; there is another fatal <hi>Virtue,</hi> and that is to <hi>excite devotion toward themſelves,</hi> even to the demanding of Favours from them and putting Truſt in them? Is it not as notorious, that the wretched People are guilty of worſhipping the Images of the Saints, no otherwiſe than they do the Saints themſelves, as that they Worſhip the Saints no otherwiſe then they Worſhip God himſelf;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ain. in Civit. D. Lib.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 27.</note> as <hi>Ludov. Vives</hi> complained. If it be ſaid that theſe Abuſes may be provided againſt, and Images may be ſtill <hi>Honor'd</hi> (for <hi>Honor</hi> is the Word, though <hi>Religious worſhip</hi> is the Thing) I would know, why men ſhould make Proviſions in this caſe, as if they were wiſer than God, who to prevent theſe miſchiefs has forbidden Image-worſhip altogether. If there were any ſuch Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages to be made of it, in compariſon to which the Danger of it were nothing at all, how comes it to be ſo ſeverely Prohibited? But when we conſider, for whoſe ſake chiefly they pretend the Profitableneſs of Image-worſhip; we ſee how true it is, that the Wiſdom of Man is but Fooliſhneſs, when it would mend the proviſions of God. For Images are by all means to be retain'd and honor'd, becauſe they are the Books and Remembrances of the <hi>Common</hi> People; and Helps to their Piety and Devotions; who therefore cannot be without them:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Trid. ſeſſ.</hi> 25. <hi>De. Invoc. S.</hi>
                  </note> But M. <hi>de Meaux,</hi> knows that theſe are moſt apt to be led into the worſt Superſtitions by Images, and that it is one of the hardeſt things in the World to prevent it.</p>
               <p>M. de <hi>Meaux</hi> tells us, <hi>their Intention is not ſo much to honor the Image, as the Apoſtle or Martyr.</hi> He will ſay too,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:60697:11"/>that 'tis the Intention of the Church, that none of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſhould intend more then this comes to. But let him tell me, how or where the Church has expreſt her ſelf, with the leaſt degree of that Zeal, which the redreſſing of ſuch horrible abuſes in this matter, as are every where known, does ſtill require. The Superſtition of the vulgar in their Communion is notorious, and which is ſtill worſe, the Doctrines leading to the moſt Superſtitious Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions and Practices in this kind, were and are notorious; for inſtance; That the <hi>ſame worſhip is due to the Image, which is due to the Prototype:</hi> And are not theſe things uncenſured by the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> to this day? If indeed we could once ſee that Church beſtir her ſelf, againſt the groſs Exceſs of Image-worſhip, as ſhe does againſt thoſe that do not worſhip Images at all, we might allow ſomething to this Expoſition of their <hi>Intentions.</hi> But as far as we can ſee, they that worſhip the very Images them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and put confidence in them, go for very good <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks;</hi> while we that dare not worſhip them at all, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God has forbidden it, are for our forbearance uſed, as they uſe <hi>Hereticks.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But ſetting all this aſide, what ſignifies the <hi>Intention</hi> of the Church, if it ran through all the Members of it, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt an expreſs Prohibition in the Scriptures? It is not lawful to do that with a Diſtinction, which is forbidden without a diſtinction. God hath ſaid, <hi>Thou ſhalt not bow down to</hi> Images, <hi>nor worſhip them.</hi> If indeed he had elſewhere made an Exception to this Rule, it had been lawful for us to have made uſe of his permiſſion, it had been neceſſary for us to have obſerved his command in the excepted Caſe. But where God hath not excepted or diſtinguiſhed, we ought not to do ſo: unleſs we will o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen a door, to evacuate all divine Laws whatſoever, by ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrary Diſtinctions and Reſervations.</p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:60697:12"/>
               <p> In ſhort, that Worſhip which they pretend to give to the Saints by their Images, has theſe two terrible Preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dices againſt it.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That the Honor, which they give to the Saints by their Images, ſuppoſing none of it to be loſt by the way, is not to be given to the Saints themſelves; as we have ſhewn already.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That the Worſhip of Images, let it be explicated with all the Fineneſs and Arts of Diſguiſe they are Maſters of, is after all to be utterly excluded out of Religion. This being a Worſhip, which God will by no means endure ſhould be given to himſelf, having univerſally prohibited it. <hi>Thou ſhalt not make to thy ſelf any graven Image, nor the likeneſs of any thing that is</hi> &amp;c. which is to my under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, as plain a Prohibition of all Image-worſhip what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, as theſe words would have been an Injunction of it, viz. <hi>Thou ſhalt make to thy ſelf</hi> ſuch or ſuch <hi>Images and Pictures, and ſhalt bow down before them and worſhip them,</hi> if this had been ſaid inſtead of the contrary. Now indeed if this had been ſaid, it had been extremely neceſſary to diſtinguiſh, between <hi>Relative</hi> Worſhip and <hi>Abſolute</hi> Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, between Worſhip <hi>terminated upon the Image,</hi> and <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to the perſon repreſented</hi> by the Image; between ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king it for a <hi>God</hi> or a <hi>Saint,</hi> and taking it only for <hi>ſome Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentation</hi> of the one or the other. But as in that caſe ſuch diſtinctions had been very neceſſary, ſo as the caſe ſtands they are vain and impertinent. For if Image-wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip had been commanded or permitted, ſtill we had been to worſhip Images, but as Images: But it being forbidden, we are not to worſhip them at all. I ſay if it had been allowed, we muſt indeed have worſhipped them with a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction; but as it is forbidden, we muſt not worſhip them tho with a diſtinction, becauſe 'tis forbidden without any diſtinction, and as univerſally as words can expreſs any thing.</p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:60697:12"/>
               <p> M. de <hi>Meaux</hi> ſays, that <hi>after the ſame manner, we ought to underſtand the Honor which they pay to Reliques after the Example of the Primitive Church.</hi> The Example of the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Church, ſhall be conſidered in its place. In the mean time, If the Worſhip of <hi>Images,</hi> and the Worſhip of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques,</hi> are to ſtand or fall together, we have already ſeen, what will become of this; having ſhewn how unſuccesfully they plead for the other. But if <hi>M. de Meaux,</hi> pleads for the Practice of the people, or even the Doctrine of his Church in this Point; he muſt pardon us, if we do not think fit, to take general Apologies, for a reaſonable In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducement, to do thoſe things, which he was not willing to name in particular. <hi>We may ſay in general,</hi> ſays M. <hi>de Meaux; That if Proteſtants would but conſider, how the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection which we bear to any one propagates it ſelf, without being divided, to his Children, to his Friends; and after that, by ſeveral degrees to the Repreſentation of him, to any Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains of him, and to any thing which renews in us his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance. If they did but conceive, that Honor has the like Progreſſion, ſeeing Honor is nothing elſe, but Love mixed with Reſpect and Fear: In fine, if they would but conſider, that all the exterior Worſhip of the Catholick Church, has its Source in God himſelf, and returns back a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain to him: They would never believe, that this Worſhip, which he himſelf alone animates, could excite his Jealouſie.</hi> M. <hi>de Meaux,</hi> conſidered very well, that it was much better, to put us off with this general Account, than to mention the Particulars he goes about to Juſtifie. It ſeems, the Worſhip of <hi>Reliques,</hi> is intended for the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of the <hi>Martyrs,</hi> and the Worſhip of the <hi>Martyrs,</hi> for the Honor of <hi>God.</hi> But what kind of Superſtition might not be defended by ſuch Apologies as theſe; if men's <hi>Blood, Bones, Teeth, Hairs, Coats, Girdles, Shoes,</hi> and ſuch like little things, may be <hi>incenſed;</hi> if they may be <hi>expoſed,</hi>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:60697:13"/>with a <hi>Venite ad adorandum,</hi> to receive the Proſtrations of the people,
<note place="margin">Catech. R. <hi>de Cultu ſanct.</hi>
                  </note> in the preſence of <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf, whom they ſuppoſe to be bodily preſent upon the Altar: if they may be ſought unto for <hi>great Graces,</hi> and <hi>for miraculous Cures;</hi> if they may be carried about, to preſerve a man from Fire, from Storms, from Peſtilence, from the Danger of Battle, and from ghoſtly, as well as bodily, Enemies: If all this, I ſay, be but the Effect of <hi>a Progreſſion of Honor,</hi> and may be brought off with a Proteſtation, that the Worſhip <hi>is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimated by God alone,</hi> and is performed for his ſake.</p>
               <p>M. <hi>de Meaux</hi> ſays, That <hi>if God, as jealous as he is of the Love of men, does not look upon us, as dividing our ſelves betwixt him and his Creatures, when we Love our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, for the Love of him; the ſame God, though jealous of the Honor which his Faithful pay him, cannot look upon them, as dividing that Worſhip, which is due to him alone, when out of Reſpect to him, they honor thoſe whom he hath honored.</hi> But as there may be an inordinate Love of our Neighbour, whom yet God hath commanded us to love; ſo there may be an inordinate Honor, given by us, even to thoſe whom God hath honoured: And if we go beyond the Bounds that God hath ſet us, in loving the one, and honouring the other; if we love our Neighbour, as we ſhould love God only; if we honor the Martyrs and the Saints, as God only ought to be honored; it will I preſume, be no ſufficient Excuſe to ſay, that it was done out of <hi>Reſpect to God.</hi> The thing which M. <hi>de Meaux</hi> ſhould have ſpoken to, but has not, is this, That the Honor they pay to Reliques, is not part of that Worſhip, which is due to none but God. With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out this 'tis in vain, to flouriſh out a general Notion which no man denies, <hi>viz.</hi> That we may ſo Love the Fathful, and Honor the Martyrs, and the very <hi>Reliques</hi> of Martyrs, as not to divide between them and God, the Love and Worſhip which is due to him alone. The truth is, M. <hi>de
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:60697:13"/>Meaux</hi> had a very hard Task in the <hi>Expoſition</hi> of the Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, which they give to <hi>Reliques.</hi> For, whereas he had ſome Colour to inſiſt upon the moderation of his Church, in the Buſineſs of <hi>Images,</hi> ſince the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares, that there is no Virtue in them, for which they ought to be reverenced, or truſted in; yet he wanted ſuch a Declaration as this, as to the buſineſs of <hi>Reliques,</hi> and could not ſay, that either the <hi>Council,</hi> or the <hi>Catechiſm</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares againſt believing <hi>any Virtue in Reliques;</hi> ſince not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, the Caution they have uſed in the manner of Expreſſion, both the one, and the other teach the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary. So that the Superſtition of <hi>Reliques</hi> in the <hi>R.</hi> C. is greater than that of <hi>Images.</hi> And therefore, M. <hi>de M.</hi> had nothing to do, but to ſet off the whole Matter by general Apologies, becauſe it would not bear a Defence of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars. But of this, I ſhall ſay no more, becauſe the Expoſition he makes of their Doctrine and Practice, as to this matter, is very like to that which he makes of the general difference, between that Worſhip which they give to God alone, and that which they give to the B. V. and the Saints. Which is the next thing I am to conſider.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <head>§. 5.</head>
               <p>They teach, That <hi>the Adoration which is due to God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, conſiſts principally in believing he is the Creator and Lord of all things; and in adhering to him, with all the Powers of our Soul, by Faith, Hope and Charity, as to him alone, who can render us happy, by the Communication of an Infinite Good, which is himſelf. This interior Adoration,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exp. p.</hi> 4.</note> 
                  <hi>has its exterior Marks; of which the principal is Sacrifice, which cannot be offered to any, but to God; becauſe a Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice is eſtabliſh'd to make a publick Acknowledgement, and a ſolemn Proteſtation of God's Sovereignty, and our abſolute De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance.</hi>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:60697:14"/>Thus the Worſhip they give to God only is deſcribed. Concerning the Worſhip they give to the B. <hi>Virgin,</hi> and the <hi>Saints,</hi> thus M. de <hi>Meaux</hi> ſpeaks: <hi>The Church teaches us, that all Religious Worſhip ought to termi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate in God, as its neceſſary End; and that if the Honor which ſhe renders to the B.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>p.</hi> 5.</note> 
                  <hi>Virgin, and to the Saints, may in ſome ſenſe be called Religious, it is for its neceſsary Relation to God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We ſhall now be better able to examine the Difference, which he puts in general between the <hi>Adoration which is due to God alone,</hi> and that Honor which they <hi>render to the B. Virgin and the Saints,</hi> becauſe we have ſeen in great part, <hi>in what this Honor conſiſts,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What M. de <hi>M.</hi> has ſaid concerning the inward Adora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of God, is exceedingly well ſaid. But if we go on, and take altogether, we cannot but diſcern, That this great Man had laboured his Thoughts into ſuch words, as ſhould provide with great appearance of Piety for the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of God, that <hi>We</hi> might not be offended; while yet he was to ſave ſome of it for the <hi>B. Virgin and the Saints,</hi> that he might not ſeem to deſert the Cauſe of his Church.</p>
               <p>For whereas he diſtinguiſheth between the inward and outward Worſhip, which is due to God only, he avoids that Diſtinction, in ſpeaking of the Honor which they render to the <hi>B. Virgin</hi> and the <hi>Saints;</hi> for it had been a dangerous way of expoſing the Doctrine of the pretended <hi>Catholicks,</hi> to tell us what <hi>inward</hi> or <hi>mental</hi> Worſhip is to be given them.</p>
               <p>Whereas the Title of the Section is,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sect.</hi> 3.</note> That <hi>Religious Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip is terminated in God alone;</hi> when he was to ſpeak of the Honor they render to the B. Virgin and to the Saints; he qualifies it with this Suppoſition, <hi>If it may in ſome ſence be called religious.</hi> Now to ſay, <hi>If it be Religious;</hi>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:60697:14"/>nay <hi>if it may be called R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ligious,</hi> and that but in <hi>ſome ſenſe</hi> too, are very new and ſurprizing ways of expreſſion; and would make one ſuſpect that all of them are not fully ſatisfied in giving a Worſhip to the B. Virgin and to the Saints, which without all Queſtion is, and therefore ought to be called, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Worſhip; as thoſe that have gone before them in this Cauſe, have without ſcruple called it.</p>
               <p>He gives this Reaſon, why Sacrifice is to be offered to God only: <hi>Becauſe a ſacrifice is eſtabliſhed to make a publick ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgment and a ſolemn profeſſion of Gods Soveraignty and our abſolute dependance.</hi> But when he ſhould give a proportionable Reaſon, why his Church renders to the B. Virgin and to the Saints, the Honor of Praying to them, which is one inſtance he preſently names; he ſlips it over and pretends no more, then that <hi>all Religious Worſhip ought to terminate in God, as its neceſſary end, and if it may be called Religious 'tis becauſe of its neceſſary Relation to him.</hi> Now he ſhould have ſaid, <hi>Prayer</hi> is eſtabliſhed to make a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Acknowledgment, and ſolemn Proteſtation, as well of the Power and Excellency of the B. Virgin and the Saints, as of the perfection of God. But though the nature of his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe required ſome ſuch reaſon, yet the nature of his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign would not bear it, which was to remove the <hi>fright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Ideas</hi> of his Religion, which we have entertained, and to repreſent it in a more agreeable and pleaſing Form, than we have yet known it by.</p>
               <p>Other Obſervations of this kind might be made, to make it probable, that it coſt even M. de. <hi>M.</hi> ſome little trouble to contrive his diſcourſe into this plauſible Appearance, and to ſhew that 'tis no eaſie matter, at the ſame time to make a ſmooth Repreſentation of their Religion and not to change it. But I ſhall now offer my Reaſons, to ſhew the Unſatisfactorineſs of his Expoſition in this cauſe, as he hath formed it.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:60697:15"/> 1. Setting aſide their Profeſſion of <hi>one God,</hi> which is ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed in the Queſtion concerning his particular Worſhip: I find no outward Mark, of the Adoration that is due to God only, mentioned, but that of <hi>Sacrifice,</hi> which indeed M. de <hi>M.</hi> ſayes is <hi>the principal</hi> But in a point of this conſequence, I wiſh he had been pleaſed to name he reſt But I think I may appeal to the Sincerity of M de <hi>Meaux,</hi> whether by Sacrifice he means any thing more than the <hi>Sacrifice of the Maſs,</hi> in which t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ey pretend to offer up offer up <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> the Son of God his natural Body Soul and Divinity, as a Propitiation for the Quick and the Dead: For my part I cannot find, but they give all other outward marks of Adoration to the B. Virgin but this; ſo that the Worſhip given to God, and that to her are diſtinguiſhed I fear but by one mark. And what a rare Account is this of Gods incommunicable Worſhip if that mark too ſhould prove to be one of their own Inventions; if ſuch a ſacrifice as that, was not appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by God; if indeed it be repugnant to the plain Authority of the Scripture; as the <hi>expoſition</hi> of our Doctrine hath irrefragably ſhewn in a very little Compaſs! This is my firſt Ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eption, That all the outward marks of Religious Worſhip, which God hath eſtabliſhed, they make common to God and the Saints; and that which they give to God only, they have made themſelves.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Even this very Sacrifice of the <hi>Maſs,</hi> is offered up by them, in honour of the B. <hi>Virgin</hi> and the Saints. For thus the Oblation runs in their Miſſals. <hi>Accept, O Holy Trinity, this Oblation which we offer to thee, in honor of the most glorious Virgin, the Mother of God,</hi> &amp;c. Now ſurely they would not offer God himſelf in Sacrifice to a Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. But it comes ſomething near it, to offer up ſuch a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice in honor of a Creature. For while this is done, how can it be ſaid, that Sacrifice is reſerved to be a <hi>Proteſtation</hi> of that Honor, which is <hi>due to God only.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:60697:15"/> 3. They <hi>burn Incenſe</hi> to the <hi>B. Virgin</hi> and the Saints, which being done as a Religious Rite in their Honor, will hardly avoid being a Sacrifice. For though this Rite of burning Incenſe, was no part of the Religion that <hi>Jeſus</hi> or his <hi>Apostles</hi> taught, nor uſed at all in the <hi>Antient</hi> Church; yet it ſhould ſeem to be no leſs a Sacrifice now, then it was among the <hi>Jews,</hi> or then it would have been, if it had been transferred from the <hi>Synagogue</hi> into the <hi>Church.</hi> I ſuppoſe, if the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> had thought fit, to introduce the Oblations of <hi>Beasts</hi> and <hi>Birds</hi> into her Religious Worſhip; ſhe could not deny, but ſuch Oblations had been properly Sacrifices, and were to be made to God only: And that though it were <hi>Judaiſm</hi> to offer them at all; it were yet <hi>Idolatry</hi> to offer them to any but to God. But what ſhould make any ſuch difference, between <hi>Slaying of Victims,</hi> and <hi>burning of Incenſe;</hi> that the former ſhould belong to God only, and not the latter, I cannot comprehend. For the <hi>Altar of incenſe was moſt holy unto the Lord;</hi> it was overlaid with Gold, which the Altar of <hi>Burnt Offerings</hi> was not; and it was more holy then the Altar of burnt-Offerings, as ſtanding in the more Holy place; and <hi>none but the Seed of</hi> Aaron <hi>was to come near to offer incenſe before the Lord.</hi> No wonder therefore, that <hi>Hezekiah</hi> brake in pieces the <hi>Braſen Serpent,</hi> when they burned Incenſe to it; for this was no leſs than offering Sacrifice to it. To conclude, the Idolatry which the <hi>Heathens</hi> ſought to bring the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> to, was no other then to take a little Incenſe in their hands, and throw it into the Fire of their Altars. But yet they burn Incenſe to the <hi>Images</hi> and <hi>Reliques</hi> of the B. <hi>Virgin</hi> and the <hi>Saints:</hi> And then how can they pretend to ſacrifice to God only? But,</p>
               <p n="4">4. Setting all this aſide, let us conſider, that they grant Sacrifice is to be offered to God only, becauſe it is <hi>eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed to make a publick Acknowledgment, and a Solemn
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:60697:16"/>Proteſtation of Gods Soveraignty, and of our abſolute Depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance.</hi> Now if this be true, then whatſoever is eſtabliſhed for the ſame purpoſe, is <hi>holy to the Lord</hi> alſo. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Religious Invocation by Prayers for good things, by Confeſſions of Sin, by vows of Repentance and Duty, and by Thanksgivings for benefits received, is to be offered to God only. For in truth, theſe are <hi>acknowledgments and Proteſtations of Gods Soveraignty, and of our abſolute De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendence.</hi> Nay in truth, they are more noble and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Sacrifices, than thoſe <hi>Victims</hi> and other more ſenſible Oblations, which God required under the Law, or before it, and which he does not require now. But that which I lay the greateſt ſtreſs upon is this, That thoſe material Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices, were ſo many Rites and Ceremonies of <hi>Invocation,</hi> diverſified according to the ſeveral ends of Invocation, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for confeſſing of Sin, or obtaining a benefit, or return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Praiſes for Benefits received. Hence it is, that <hi>Prayer</hi> and <hi>Sacrifice</hi> are put one for the other in the Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures as when it is ſaid; <hi>The Sacrifice of the wicked is an abomination to the Lord,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pro.</note> 
                  <hi>but the Prayer of the upright is his delight:</hi> By which words it is plain, that the Sacrifice of the Wicked, is his Prayer, and the Prayer of the upright is his Sacrifice. Now Prayer, and Sacrifice ſtrictly ſo call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, were both Acts of Worſhip; but Prayer more excellent than Sacrifice, becauſe Sacrifice was the Rite of Prayer, and a Rite which God required no longer, than till that moſt precious Sacrifice of the Son of God was offered for us; the Merit of which alone it is, that made the Prayers of good men in all ages acceptable to God.</p>
               <p>And by the way, it would be conſidered by the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> That when thoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> perfect Sacrifices, which prefigured the oblation of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> once for all, were offered under the Law; the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Gods People were then made only to God. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> now
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:60697:16"/>that the Prayers of the Church are ſanctified, by the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhment of the Sacrifice of the Son of God, to offer any of them to a Creature, is rather a greater Diſhonour to God than, it would have been before. For if the <hi>Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>archs</hi> and the <hi>Jews</hi> were to pray to him only, to whom alone they offered Sacrifice, <hi>i. e.</hi> to God; much more ſhall the Sacrifice of the Son of God, which hath been actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally offered for us, infer our Obligation to make all our Prayers and Religious Invocations to God only, to whom we have Acceſs by the merit of that Sacrifice.</p>
               <p>But this I inſiſt upon, That if we compare the legal Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices, with the Prayers of Gods People under the Law, theſe were no leſs <hi>Proteſtations of Gods Soveraignty and man's abſolute dependence</hi> then thoſe were; and that the <hi>Houſe of God,</hi> was no leſs denominated by a Service peculiar to him, in being called <hi>an Houſe of Prayer,</hi> then if it had been cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>an Houſe of Sacrifice,</hi> as it was an Houſe of Sacrifice too. A Houſe of Sacrifice to the <hi>Jewes,</hi> and a Houſe of Prayer to all <hi>Nations.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now, if theſe more Spriritual and reaſonable Sacrifices of a Penitent and broken Heart, a believing and humble Heart, a devout and thankful Heart offered in Religious Invocation, are ſuch <hi>Acknowledgments</hi> as M. de <hi>M.</hi> ſpeaks of; then are they not to be offered to the B. Virgin and the Saints, but to God only. And what now is it that M. de <hi>M.</hi> means, by <hi>terminating the Honour they render to the B. V.</hi> upon God? Is it this, That the Honour done to her, by Invocating her with Prayers, Hymns, Confeſſions of Sin, Vows, and Devoting themſelves to her Service, is all inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the Church for the Honor of God? I would then know, why any Sacrifice may not alſo be offered directly to the Virgin, the Church intending, that the Honor of it ſhould terminate upon God, and believing that he has all the Honor of it at laſt. No, ſay they, <hi>Sacrifice is eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:60697:17"/>to make a publick acknowledgement of Gods Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty.</hi> But then I add, that Religious Invocation is eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed to make ſuch an Acknowledgment too. So that if Terminating Religious Worſhip upon God, will warrant giving it to the B. Virgin, and the Saints, their Church may give to them that Worſhip of <hi>the more ſenſible Sacrifices,</hi> which yet they pretend to deny. And if no Worſhip is to be given to the Saints, which is eſtabliſhed to make a So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn Acknowledgment of Gods Soveraignty, and our depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, they muſt deny to the B. V. and to the Saints, <hi>that more Spiritual Worſhip</hi> of Prayers, Hymns, and Vows, which they give. Nor will they ever be able to avoid theſe difficulties, but by coming out of the Clouds, and confeſſing according to the plainneſs and the ſimplicity of the Scriptures, That all Religious Worſhip is due to God, and to him only, inaſmuch as <hi>Religious Worſhip</hi> is eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to make an Acknowledgment of Gods Soveraignty, and our abſolute Dependance: And <hi>publick Acts of Religious Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,</hi> to make publick and ſolemn Acknowledgments thereof.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <head>§. 6.</head>
               <p>Thus I have conſidered the Defence, that M. de <hi>M.</hi> has made of the Worſhip of the B. V. and the Saints, as it is practiſed in the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> and I promiſe my ſelf, that whoever ſhall ſeriouſly conſider what has been ſaid, willnot be encouraged, by the <hi>Expoſition</hi> of this Practice, to venture upon it. I know that many of the <hi>R.</hi> Church, fortifie themſelves, againſt all our Arguments upon theſe Points, by this Perſwaſion: That ſo long as they do not make Gods of the Saints, but believe and profeſs, that there is but one God, infinite in all Perfections; all the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors they give to the B. Virgin and the Saints, are to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terp reted by this Proteſtation: That they have no other
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:60697:17"/>God, but the Creator of the World, nor Lord, but the Saviour of mankind. But if they in this manner aſſure themſelves, and would encourage others: I beſeech them to conſider, and would to God, they would all conſider but this one thing: That if the Sin of Idolatry could not take place, where there is ſuch a Profeſſion, and ſuch a Faith in one God (though I more than fear the contrary;) yet the <hi>Saint-Worſhip</hi> of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, does approach ſo very near it, and is ſo very like it, that even this, (if no more were to be ſaid) ſhould be a ſufficient Reaſon to deter us from <hi>It.</hi> A Woman that is faithful to her Husband, will not only forbear doing the utmoſt Injury to him, by giving his Bed to another; but ſhe will avoid all thoſe Familiari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Careſſes with any other man, which are ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, which lead to the laſt Treachery, and which would provoke her Husband's Jealouſie. Now God has deſcribed his peoples Relation to him, by the Relation of a Wife to her Husband, not only in the <hi>Old Teſtament,</hi> but in the <hi>New;</hi> from whence it is, that the Worſhip of other Gods is called Fornication, Whoredom and Adultery. Thus God charged the <hi>Jews,</hi> for <hi>inflaming themſelves with Idols,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 57.5.7.</note> 
                  <hi>under every green Tree,</hi> and <hi>ſetting up their Beds upon every lofty and high Mountain,</hi> and <hi>enlarging their Bed,</hi> becauſe they had many Idols. Thus it was ſaid of <hi>Iſrael,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jerem.</hi> 3.6.9.</note> that ſhe had <hi>through the Lightneſs of her Whoredoms, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fil'd the Land, and committed Adultery with Stocks and Stones.</hi> This is the Language of the whole 16th. Chap. of <hi>Ezek.</hi> where God threaten'd to judge the <hi>Jews,</hi> as Women that break Wedlock are judged, and would give them their Reward in Fury.</p>
               <p>Now ſuppoſing, that there were no other Idolatry in the Nature of the thing, no other ſpiritual Whoredom and Fornication, but Worſhipping that for God, which is not God; and that if we do but make this difference, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:60697:18"/>the Worſhip that we give to God, and that which we give to his Courtiers and Favorites, that ſtill we Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge them to be Creatures, and not <hi>Gods,</hi> Servants, and not <hi>Lords;</hi> and ſo do not give them that laſt and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhing Honor, which to give would, by the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of all, be ſpiritual Adultery in the higheſt degree: Suppoſing this, I ſay; yet let us in the Name of God con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, that to give Religious Worſhip to Creatures, as well as to God; to fall down to Images, as well as to God; and to give almoſt quite throughout the ſame outward Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of Honor, of Faith, of Love, of Religious Expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Dependence to the B. V. and to Saints and Angels, which we give to God; if it be not downright whoredom, is yet a whoriſh Behaviour, and more than ſufficient to provoke the Lord to Jealouſie. I cannot but ſpeak in the Language of the Scripture, upon an Argument that the Scriptures ſo largely treat of in this Language.</p>
               <p>It is worthy of much Obſervation, that God gives this very Reaſon, why he prohibited the Worſhipping of Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges: <hi>For I the Lord thy God, am a jealous God.</hi> And that we might not think it a light matter, to provoke his Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie; he adds, <hi>and I viſit the Sins of the Fathers, upon the Children to the third and fourth Generation of them that hate me.</hi> I know who they are, that would fain be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the Worſhip of no other Images, but thoſe of the Gods of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> to be forbidden in the ſecond Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment. But I muſt needs ſay, upon this Occaſion, that if that had been the only deſign of that Commandement; it is very ſtrange, that God ſhould note the Worſhipping of the Heathen Gods, with no other penalty, than that which his <hi>Jealouſie</hi> would inflict: For to have any other <hi>Gods</hi> beſides him, is without all queſtion, ſpiritual Whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; and had been threatned with Divorce, if the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibition of ſo great a Crime, had needed the of Sanction of
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:60697:18"/>any expreſs Threatning. But when he threatens the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of Images, with the Effects of his Jealouſie: it ſeems plain, that he means ſuch Image-Worſhip, as is conſiſtent with acknowledging him to be our Only God. And yet this is the leaſt of all thoſe Reaſons, by which it appears to me, that he forbids in this Commandment, the Worſhip of all Images whatſoever. I deny not therefore, but a man may kneel, may kiſs, may incenſe, may proſtrate himſelf, and pray before an Image; and all this while aſcribe no Divinity to it, nor take it to be his God. So likewiſe he may Pray, and make Vows, and offer Thanks and Prayſes to the Saints, and to the B. Virgin, and not take them nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for his Gods. But becauſe God is the peerleſs Majeſty of Heaven and Earth, he will be ſerved with a peerleſs Worſhip; he will therefore have no ſuch things as theſe done in Religion, nor Creatures to have Reſpect ſhewn them, that look ſo like to the Worſhip which he requires himſelf. Why do I ſay, <hi>ſo like?</hi> That which they give to the B.V. and to the Saints, is almoſt the very ſame. But if we do ſuch things as theſe, it will not ſerve our turn, to plead, That we ſtill keep the inward Adoration of Spirit and Truth intirely for him, though we thus honor his Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures with Religious Rites, and Services; any more than it would excuſe a Woman, that had given all the Favors and Liberty to another Man, that could provoke her Husband's Jealouſie, to ſay, (though ſhe could ſay it with Truth;) that ſhe remembred all the while who was her Husband, and whatever Liberties beſides ſhe uſed, that ſhe had ſtill kept his Bed undefiled.</p>
               <p>This Conſideration I could not forbear to uſe; and that in Compaſſion to thoſe, whoſe Prejudices will not let them feel the Senſe of thoſe Reaſonings, by which we prove the <hi>Roman</hi> Church to be guilty of downright Idolatry. For if the fear of God's <hi>Jealouſie,</hi> would keep them from giving
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:60697:19"/>thoſe Honors to the Saints, which look ſo like Divine Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, if they are not ſo; we ſhould gain our end upon them, though not by the force of the beſt arguing the Caſe will bear: And this is our End, That God may not be any more diſhonour'd, and their Salvation hindred, by the unchriſtian Doctrines and Practices of this ſort. I have therefore now proceeded upon this Suppoſition, that they are not guilty of perfect Idolatry, in t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oſe things which we complain of, and yet ſhewn what urgent Cauſe there is upon another Account, for a Reformation of them. But I conclude this, with profeſſing, That I have ſuppoſed them not guilty of that fearful Crime, only to make way for another Argument, ſince all Arguments are to be uſed in ſo important a Matter, that have a Foundation of Truth; but not in diſtruſt of thoſe Arguments, which prove them guilty of it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <head>§. 7.</head>
               <p>The ſecond thing I propounded was, to ſhew the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings of this ſtrange Worſhip amongſt Chriſtians, which they offer in the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> to the B. Virgin, and to the Saints. For I muſt not forget, that M. de <hi>Meaux</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends, that his Church in theſe things teaches <hi>as the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Church</hi> taught, and that ſhe does what ſhe teaches with all <hi>Antiquity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But what if nothing of all this, was either Taught or done in the Church for 360 years after <hi>Chriſt?</hi> M. de <hi>M.</hi> ſayes, that <hi>thoſe of the Pretended Reformation (obliged by the ſtrength of Truth) begin to acknowledge, that the cuſtom of Praying to Saints, and honoring their Reliques, was Eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed even in the fourth Age of the Church.</hi> This he takes all occaſions to inſinuate; and with theſe colours he ſerves himſelf to repreſent the <hi>Reformation</hi> as odiouſly as he can
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:60697:19"/>deviſe. Thus he tells us in his <hi>Paſtoral</hi> Letter; <hi>But above all what horror are they worthy of,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Paſt. l. p.</hi> 29.</note> 
                  <hi>who caſt the Accuſation [of Idolatry] upon the whole Church, and alſo on the Church of the firſt Ages?</hi> Where he takes it for granted, that the Honour and Innocence of the <hi>firſt Ages</hi> muſt ſtand or fall with the Cauſe of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church; and ſo takes occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to accuſe us of a great and fearful Crime, <hi>viz.</hi> That <hi>we caſt the accuſation of Idolatry upon the whole Church, even the Church of the firſt Ages:</hi> He had obſerved but juſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that <hi>thoſe who bear falſe and ſcandalous Witneſs againſt an Innocent Perſon, are Condemned to the ſame puniſhment which the Crime of which they bear Witneſs, did deſerve, had it been found true.</hi> And therefore <hi>we deſerve before men, the Horror which is due to Idolatry, and ſhall receive the juſt puniſhment thereof in the ſight of God.</hi> If this Rule be true, and we muſt incur the Penalties of <hi>Idolatry,</hi> if we falſly accuſe others of it; M. de <hi>Meaux</hi> ought to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect upon himſelf; who having accuſed us of <hi>falſly accuſing</hi> the <hi>First Ages</hi> in this matter, ſupports his Accuſation by taking theſe two things for granted: Firſt, that we ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge <hi>the Illustrious Fourth Age to have requeſted the Prayers of Martyrs, and honored Reliques;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ibid.</note> as the pretended <hi>Catholicks</hi> have done ſince: Secondly, that the <hi>Fourth</hi> Age being granted them, the firſt <hi>Three</hi> muſt be theirs in courſe. If M. de <hi>Meaux</hi> be ſafe upon theſe Grounds; we have no great cauſe to apprehend the <hi>Horrors</hi> and <hi>Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> of falſe Accuſation. And if this be all he hath to ſay, 'tis but a very ſlender ground for an Appeal to the <hi>Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Church,</hi> and to <hi>all Antiquity.</hi> For neither have the. Reformed acknowledged heretofore,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Id.</hi> p. 8.</note> nor do they now <hi>begin to acknowledge,</hi> that <hi>the Customs</hi> of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church in theſe points, were eſtabliſhed in the Fourth Age of the Church. Nor if they did acknowledge it, would this Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acknowledgment give away the <hi>Primitive Church,</hi> and <hi>all
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:60697:20"/>Antiquity</hi> in favour of Praying to Saints, and worſhipping of Images and Reliques; unleſs the firſt three Ages were leſs <hi>Antient</hi> and <hi>Primitive,</hi> than thoſe that followed.</p>
               <p>That which we acknowledge, is not that <hi>Saint-Worſhip</hi> was <hi>Eſtabliſhed in the Fourth</hi> Age; but this, that towards the latter end of the Fourth Age, ſome unhappy occaſions were given, for the Eſtabliſhing of that Worſhip in after Ages; which we could wiſh had never been given, and which the Great Men of thoſe Dayes (we have reaſon to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve) would have prevented, if they had been Prophets, as well as holy Men, and foreſeen the Miſchieſs, into which they were ripened, by the Superſtition of after-times.</p>
               <p>I ſhall therefore demonſtrate, that 'tis a vain thing for the pretended Catholicks to preſume, that they have the Authority of the three Firſt Ages, for the worſhip of <hi>Saints Images</hi> and <hi>Reliques,</hi> upon ſuppoſition that the Doctors, towards the cloſe of the Fourth Age, were theirs in theſe Points. And then I ſhall not fear, to give the trueſt Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count I can, of thoſe Practices at that time, which grew af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward into the Superſtitions we now complain of.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Monſieur de Meaux</hi> ſayes, <hi>It will not appear very likely that</hi> M. Daille <hi>ſhould underſtand the ſentiments of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the three firſt Ages, better than thoſe who gathered, as I may ſay, the Succeſſion of their Doctrine after their deaths.</hi> Theſe Gentlemen, I perceive, will content them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with any pretence, to ſhift off the Tryal of their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines and Practices, by the Authority of the three Firſt Ages. For whether that be <hi>likely,</hi> or not which M. de <hi>Meaux</hi> here puts; yet I hope we may look into the Writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of the moſt Primitive Fathers, to ſee how things went in their times. And <hi>it is very likely</hi> that M. <hi>Daille</hi> might underſtand the ſentiments of the Fathers of the <hi>Three</hi> firſt Ages, as well as he underſtood the Sentiments of thoſe of the <hi>Fourth.</hi> And ſo long as we can have recourſe to the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:60697:20"/>undoubted Writings of the three firſt Ages, we may get the Doctrine of thoſe Fathers this way, with a little more Aſſurance, then by gueſſing what their Sentiments were, from the Books of their Succeſſors: Which every reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Man muſt acknowledge, unleſs it be reaſonable to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe that the Fathers of the Three firſt Ages, did not <hi>under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoud their own Sentiments,</hi> ſo well as the Fathers of the Fourth <hi>underſtood them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now in the firſt place, the profound Silence of the three Firſt Ages, and the better half of the Fourth, as to the Worſhip of the B. <hi>Virgin</hi> and the <hi>Saints,</hi> and their <hi>Images</hi> and <hi>Reliques,</hi> ſhould be enough to determine the firſt Point in queſtion. And this Silence is not only directly confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by ſome of our Adverſaries, but as effectually confeſſed by the reſt, that labor to find ſome hints of theſe Practices in theſe primitive Fathers; but by ſuch Interpretations and Conſequences, that 'tis almoſt as great a ſhame to conſute, as to make them. Now the Silence of theſe Fathers ought not to be rejected, as an incompetent Proof, becauſe it is but a Negative. For ſince we pretend, that theſe Practices are Innovations and were never heard of in the Ancient Church: It is not reaſonable to demand a better Proof of it, than that in their Books, ſome of which give large and particular Accounts of their Worſhip, and of their Doctrines concerning Worſhip, we can no where meet with the leaſt Intimation or Footſtep of them. Would our Adverſaries have us bring expreſs Teſtimonies out of the Fathers againſt theſe things, as if they wrote and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted by the Spirit of Prophecy, againſt thoſe Corruptions that ſhould ariſe, ſeveral Ages after they were dead? We have, as I ſhall ſhew, other ways of diſcovering their Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timents, beſides this, that they make not the leaſt mention of theſe Services. But to <hi>demand</hi> more than their <hi>perpetual Silence</hi> in theſe Caſes, is unreaſonable; becauſe no ſatisfacto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:60697:21"/>Account can be given of it, but this, That the Worſhip we ſpeak of, was indeed no part of their Religion. Had it been ſome indifferent Rite or Ceremony, that we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend about; this Argument from the Silence of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, againſt its Antiquity, might with ſome Colour be rejected; becauſe it were unreaſonable to expect, that they ſhould take notice in their Writings, of every Cuſtom of how little moment ſoever. And yet we find, that in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters even of this ſlight nature in compariſon, they have not been wanting, to give us very much Information. But it is altogether incredible, that ſo notable and famous a Part of the the Worſhip of Chriſtians, as that which is now given to the B. <hi>Virgin,</hi> and to the <hi>Saints,</hi> ſhould not be mentioned by any one of them, if it had been the Cuſtom of thoſe times. <hi>Juſtin Martyr, Athenagoras, Tertullian, Minutius Felix, all</hi> the <hi>Apologiſts,</hi> or at leaſt <hi>one</hi> of them, would have ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken ſome notice of it; eſpecially, ſince this part of their Religion, would have needed Expoſition and Defence, more than all the reſt; for it would have made them obnoxious to the Recriminations of the Heathens; and brought all their own Arguments upon themſelves, which they had uſed againſt the Heathens, in Defence of their own Worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping the one God, and him only.</p>
               <p>But perhaps they all agreed toconceal this <hi>Saint-Worſhip</hi> from the Heathens, for the ſame Reaſon why <hi>Salmeron</hi> thinks, the Apoſtles and Evangeliſts concealed it at firſt from both <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles, becauſe,</hi> forſooth, <hi>it had been hard to require it of the Jews</hi> (who had been taught to pray to God on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Salmer. in</hi> 1 <hi>Tun.</hi> 2. <hi>Diſp.</hi> 8.</note> and to Worſhip none but him) <hi>and</hi> by publiſhing it, <hi>Occaſion had been given to the Gentiles to think, that many Gods were now offered them, inſtead of that multitude of Gods which they had forſaken.</hi> A very likely Reaſon, thus far; That if this had been the Doctrine of the Church, it was highly neceſſary to keep it ſecret, till Heathen Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:60697:21"/>were extinguiſhed; and none ſhould be left to up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braid the Chriſtians, with removing the old Gods of the Heathens, to make way for new ones of their own. And without all doubt, thoſe that were prevail'd upon in every Perſecution, by Force and Flattery, to revolt from Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity; though they had been falſe to the reſt of their Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, yet were true to this Secret of it; and never diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered to the Heathens, that (whatever the Church pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,) they had been taught to ſay <hi>Ave Maries</hi> to the B. Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, and to Worſhip her, and the dead Saints and Martyrs, with <hi>Prayers</hi> and <hi>Hymns, &amp;c.</hi> I thank this <hi>Jeſuit</hi> howe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, for confeſſing ſo manifeſt a Truth, that this Adoration of Saints was not fit to be expoſed to the <hi>Gentiles.</hi> But if Matters were carried thus, I think they were not carried with great Sincerity. This might be like the Policy of <hi>Jeſuits;</hi> but it did not by any means become the Simplicity of <hi>Chriſtians.</hi> And yet I think, a <hi>Jeſuit</hi> would hardly have <hi>carried</hi> a Secret <hi>in his Sleeve,</hi> ſo dangerous to be diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and ſo impoſſible to be concealed. For that the Church ſhould have the good Fortune, to conceal it for above 300 Years, from the Idolatrous Philoſophers, and Prieſts of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> was of all other things, that paſſed in that long time, the moſt miraculous; and requires ſuch a Faith to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it, as believes a thing the more, the more incredible it is. But though this, in the Opinion of all indifferent perſons, will be a ſufficient Prejudice againſt ſuppoſing, that the Church kept her Doctrine and Practice from the Knowledge of her Enemies; Yet I believe it will be a ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger Prejudice againſt it, amongſt thoſe (of which number I profeſs my ſelf to be one) that honor the Memories of the Ancient Martyrs, and love them for their Conſtancy to the Death, in adhering to our dear Lord and Maſter <hi>Jeſus;</hi> that this crafty Deſign, is no way reconcileable to that Spirit of Integrity, which the Goſpel frames us to,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:60697:22"/>if we are True <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> and of which they, if any, were undeniable Examples. One would think therefore, that if the <hi>Heathens</hi> knew no ſuch Doctrines and Practices amongſt the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> that the <hi>Christians</hi> had none ſuch to be known. And in the Opinion of <hi>Salmeron</hi> himſelf; had thoſe known any ſuch thing, theſe had not failed to have heard of it. Why then did they not charge the Chriſtians with Worſhipping the B. Virgin, when nothing would have been more pertinent and appoſite? I will give one In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of this Queſtion, ſo clear and full, that it ſhall render all others needleſs. There was nothing that <hi>Celſus</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted upon, againſt the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> Worſhipping <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> with more Spite and Triumph, then that <hi>Jeſus</hi> was, as he called him, <hi>a moſt vile Perſon; Taken, Beaten</hi> and <hi>Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ied.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Orig. contra celſ. lib.</hi> 2.3.</note> It was for this he ſcorned the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> that they ſhould count him the <hi>Son of God;</hi> and <hi>Worſhip him now dead,</hi> who lived and died ignominiouſly. It muſt be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſie to a Chriſtian,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ibid. lib.</hi> 7.8.</note> to write or to read his Blaſphemies upon this Occaſion. But there is one place that I muſt not forbear; and that is, Where the foreſaid Wretch, brings in a <hi>Jew,</hi> and with the <hi>Jew,</hi> does himſelf upbraid <hi>Jeſus,</hi> That he was <hi>Born in a little Town of</hi> Judaea, <hi>and that of a wandring Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, miſerably poor, that ſpan for her living; who was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo for Adultery thrown out of doors,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Orig. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Cont. Cel.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>by the Carpenter her Husband; and being thus driven away by him, and wandring up and down in a baſe faſhion, brought forth</hi> Jeſus <hi>in a Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</hi> Thus did that <hi>accurſed Villain,</hi> blaſpheme the Bleſſed Virgin, in deſpite to <hi>Jeſus</hi> her moſt Holy Son; I ſay in deſpite to him, becauſe he was worſhipped by the <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</hi> By bringing forth the Execrable Stories of the <hi>Jews</hi> concerning the Mother, the Impious Infidel deſigned to make the Church of God aſhamed of Worſhipping her Son; whom he ſought to diſparage this way, as well as by objecting the Poverty of his Life, and the Ignominy
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:60697:22"/>of his Death. But ſuppoſe, I beſeech you, that the Church in thoſe days had honored the Mother of <hi>Jeſus,</hi> little leſs than <hi>Jeſus himſelf;</hi> that ſhe had been called the <hi>Queen of Heaven;</hi> that the Story of her <hi>Aſſumption</hi> had been then invented; that ſhe had been Worſtipped as the <hi>Lady of the World,</hi> and ſerved with Prayers, and Vows, and Incenſe, and with all, or with any of thoſe Religious Rites, that ſhe is now ſerved with: would that ſpiteful Wretch, have failed to reproach the enemies of his Gods with ſo plain a matter of Reproach? Did he think they had reaſon, to be aſhamed of making ſo helpleſs and ſo <hi>unfortunate</hi> a man, as the Pagans took <hi>Jeſus</hi> to be,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ibid. Lib.</hi> 8.</note> the object of a <hi>moſt excellent Worſhip;</hi> and would he not have thought it a greater ſhame, if they had given a <hi>ſuperex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent</hi> worſhip, to ſo helpleſs and ſo <hi>ſcandalous</hi> a woman, as the falſe Miſcreant reckoned the Mother to be? Did they inſult over the Chriſtians for making a God of the <hi>Son</hi> of ſuch a <hi>Mother?</hi> What would they have ſaid, if the Church had given then the leaſt occaſion to ſuſpect, that it had made a Goddeſs of the Mother her ſelf? But of this not one word is to be met with, in all the Reproaches of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidal; no nor of <hi>Trypho</hi> or <hi>Coecilius,</hi> or any of the moſt bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter enemies of the Chriſtian names, for the three firſt Ages; where it lay as fair to be taken up, as Argument and Occaſion could make it. What Account then is to be given of this Omiſſion? It was no Omiſſion of theirs at all; The Church had not yet given them this Handle againſt it ſelf: No ſuch things as theſe were known amongſt <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians,</hi> and therefore, their Enemies did not lay them to their Charge: Their Enemies, I ſay, who falſly accuſed them, as to other matters, upon the moſt ſlight and frivo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Occaſions. They accuſed them of Worſhipping an <hi>Aſſe's</hi> Head; of killing a <hi>Child</hi> at their Solemn Aſſemblies; and of <hi>Adultery</hi> and <hi>Inceſt,</hi> as you may ſee in <hi>Minutius
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:60697:23"/>Felix,</hi> and elſewhere; and all this upon the moſt ridiculous Grounds imaginable. But it ſeems the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> paid Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Worſhip to the <hi>Virgin,</hi> and to <hi>dead Men</hi> and <hi>Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men;</hi> and their watchful Enemies were content to ſay ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver a word of it. Alas! theſe wiſe Men did not know, that the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> derided them, for ſuch things as theſe; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps they were always deaf, when it was told them, that the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> did the ſame things themſelves; or they had quite forgotten it, when it was moſt proper to remember it; or were ſo ſilly, as not to diſcern the Advantage they were to make of it; or ſo imprudent, as to accuſe them of other things which could be eaſily diſproved, rather than to accuſe them of thoſe things which could not be denied. <hi>The Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of this World,</hi> were now grown Fools <hi>in their Generation.</hi> He that can believe theſe things, let him believe them!</p>
               <p>I ſhall add this only,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cyril. contra</hi> Julian <hi>l.</hi> 6. See Mr. <hi>Mede</hi>'s Apoſtacy of the later times.</note> that when the leaſt Occaſions were once given, to ſuſpect that the Martyrs were worſhipped by the Church, the Heathens immediately laid hold on the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, eſpecially <hi>Julian</hi> and <hi>Eunapius,</hi> who urged the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſation with all the ſtings of Malice; as their Predeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors in this Cauſe againſt <hi>Chriſt,</hi> would certainly have done, had there been the leaſt Colour for it.</p>
               <p>But to return to the Virgin <hi>Mary:</hi> We have ſeen that in theſe latter Ages, the Doctrine of her Worſhip is grown to be no mean part of the Body of Divinity, with the Doctors of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church. There is no end of writing Books in her Honor, and to excite and direct Devotion to her. A Sermon cannot be preached, but ſhe muſt be addreſſed to with an <hi>Ave Mary:</hi> Nor a large Volume Written, but 'tis odds, that it is concluded with <hi>Praiſe to God, and to the</hi> Virgin <hi>Mother Mary.</hi> One would therefore expect, to find all things full of Veneration and Addreſs to the B. Virgin, in the Writings of the Primitive Fathers, that is, to meet with it at every turn in their Expoſitions of the Faith, in
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:60697:23"/>their Exhortations to Devotion and Piety, and in all their Homilies to the people. But if you look for any ſuch thing, I will be bold to ſay, you will loſe your labour; un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs it were ſome Satisfaction to find, that the World is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much altered from what it was, and the State of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion not a little changed.</p>
               <p>But the worſt is, that what theſe Fathers ſay of her, is but very little in Compariſon; and that not of ſet purpoſe, but incidentally and occaſionally, as they were led to it by other things. I know not how the Fathers can be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed, but that the Scriptures ſpeak, as ſparingly of her, as they.</p>
               <p>It were ſomething however, if their occaſional Paſſages concerning her, intimated a greater Regard to her Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice in their Practice, than they have ſhewn in their Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings; or if they diſcovered but ſome obſcure Prints and Footſteps of ſuch a Devotion to her, as we ſeek for. Let us therefore ſee, after what manner they ſpeak of the B. Virgin.</p>
               <p>I obſerve, that the higheſt Strains in her Praiſe,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Juſtin Dial. cam Tryph. p.</hi> 327. Paris.</note> run up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a Compariſon between her and <hi>Eve.</hi> Thus <hi>Juſtin Martyr,</hi> who ſays very little elſe of her tells us, that <hi>Eve being a Virgin conceived by the Word of the Serpent,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>p.</hi> 290.</note> 
                  <hi>and brought forth Death: But the Virgin</hi> Mary <hi>receiving the Meſſage</hi> of the Angel, <hi>conceived in Faith, therefore that which was born of her was Holy,</hi> viz. <hi>the Son of God.</hi> He proves alſo againſt <hi>Trypho,</hi> that Chriſt was to be born of a Virgin, according to the Prophets.</p>
               <p>After <hi>Juſtin</hi> comes <hi>Irenoeus,</hi> and with greater circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance purſues the forementioned Compariſon, againſt theſe ſtupid <hi>Hereticks,</hi> that denied God to be the Creator of all things, and that he uſed his own Works. For againſt theſe <hi>Irenoeus</hi> amongſt other Arguments, produced this, That <hi>Chriſt</hi> took Fleſh of <hi>Mary.</hi> And then he proceeds to ſhew, how convenient it was, that he ſhould be Born of a <hi>Virgin.</hi>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:60697:24"/>Firſt he oppoſes the <hi>diſobedience</hi> in the caſe of the Forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den <hi>Tree,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> ab. 5. <hi>c.</hi> 18.19.</note> by which Sin came into the World, to that <hi>obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience</hi> which was performed upon a <hi>Tree,</hi> by him that brought Life to the World. He oppoſes alſo the <hi>Cheat</hi> that was put upon <hi>Eve,</hi> to the <hi>Truth</hi> that was told <hi>Mary.</hi> He oppoſes the <hi>Virgin Eve,</hi> now <hi>deſigned to be a Wife,</hi> to the <hi>Virgin Mary</hi> who was alſo <hi>eſpouſed;</hi> and the Virgin <hi>Eve</hi> deceived by an <hi>evil Angel,</hi> to the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> believing a <hi>good Angel.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Word which I tranſlate <hi>Comforter,</hi> is in Latin <hi>Advocata,</hi> from whence <hi>Bellarmin</hi> and <hi>Fevardentius</hi> conclude very abſurdly in behalf of Invocation of Saints, tho <hi>Irenaeus</hi> had meant, what we uſually underſtand by <hi>Advocate.</hi> But by the fidelity of the <hi>Latin</hi>-Tranſlator in keeping to the Eccleſiaſtical uſe of words, it ſeems evident, that the Greek word in <hi>Irenaeus</hi> was <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, which how it is to be Tranſlated ſee M. <hi>Daille,</hi> who has largely treated this matter, and I doubt not to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ay, has made an end of it. De <hi>Relig. Cultus Object.</hi> p. 41. &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>And,</hi> ſayes he, <hi>as</hi> Eve <hi>was ſeduced and forſook God, ſo</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>was induced to obey God, that the Virgin</hi> Mary <hi>might be a Comforter of the Virgin</hi> Eve: <hi>and that as Mankind was through a Virgin bound over to Death, ſo they ſhould be releaſed through a Virgin. One thing being thus rightly ballanced againſt another, the diſobedience of a Virgin, by the the Obedience of a Virgin.</hi> The ſum of all is this, That there appeared a notable Congruity in divers reſpects, that as <hi>Eve</hi> a Virgin led the firſt man <hi>Adam</hi> into tranſgreſſion, in whom all Mankind fell; ſo the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> brought forth him into the World, the <hi>ſecond Adam,</hi> the <hi>Lord from Heaven,</hi> who was to redeem all Mankind. No honeſt Man will go about to make leſs of theſe Paſſages, but he muſt be a very ſubtle man, that can make more of them.</p>
               <p>And yet <hi>Fevardentius</hi> triumphs in this Teſtimony, as if he had found here the <hi>Primitive Church,</hi> and <hi>all Antiquity,</hi> for the Invocation of the B. Virgin. And no leſs ſatisfied he was, with a like ſtrain of <hi>Irenoeus</hi> againſt thoſe Hereticks, in another place,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Adv. Haer. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 32.33.</note> who ſaid, That <hi>Christ took nothing from the Virgin Mary,</hi> and by conſequence that ſhe was not really his Mother, nor he really, but only ſeemingly, a Man. Now amongſt other things <hi>Irenoeus</hi> argues the contrary, from
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:60697:24"/>the congruity of our Saviours being born of a <hi>Virgin,</hi> that a Virgin might bring as much <hi>good</hi> to the World, as a Virgin had done <hi>miſchief;</hi> whereby it became plain, that God de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed the <hi>Devil</hi> in a congruous way, who by the Virgin <hi>Eve</hi> had ſeduced <hi>Adam,</hi> and brought death upon his Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. But why did not <hi>Irenoeus</hi> complain, that this Hereſy overthrew the very Foundation, upon which the Church gave a ſuper-excellent Worſhip to <hi>Mary,</hi> viz. becauſe ſhe was the Mother of God? nay, why did not he ſilence this wild Conceit, by alledging the Worſhip which ſhe every where received upon this account? <hi>Fevardentius</hi> elſewhere makes a mighty matter of <hi>Irenoeus</hi> his preſſing <hi>Hereticks</hi> with <hi>Catholick Tradition.</hi> Why therefore was not ſo ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious and convincing an Argument, as the <hi>Catholick Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> and <hi>practice</hi> of worſhipping the <hi>Virgin Mary,</hi> brought fourth upon this occaſion? Even becauſe there was no ſuch Tradition or Practice to be alledged, as any man that is not overruled with prejudice muſt confeſs. 'Tis a ſign that an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Teſtimonies run very low with them, when they are fain to make much of theſe.</p>
               <p>But if <hi>Irenoeus</hi> forgot this Argument, 'tis ſomething ſtrange that <hi>Tertullian</hi> after him ſhould forget it too. For writing againſt the ſame ſtupid opinions, he uſes juſt the Argument that <hi>Irenoeus</hi> had done before him. <hi>The Image and Similitude of God,</hi> ſaith he <hi>being captivated by the Devil, God recovered it by</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">aemulâ ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratione. Tert. de carne Chriſti. c. 27. Adv. Praxe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am c. 27.</note> 
                  <hi>a Work that defeated the Devil in his own way. For the word that was a Foundation of Death had crept into</hi> Eve, <hi>being yet a Virgin, and agreeably by the word that ſhould reſtore life, was to be received by a Virgin; that Mankind who by means of that Sex fell into Perdition, might through the ſame Sex be recovered to Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</hi> Eve <hi>had believed the Serpent,</hi> Mary <hi>hath believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> Gabriel. <hi>The Offence which the former hath committed in believing, the latter hath blotted out by believing.</hi> And
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:60697:25"/>what he means by <hi>blotting out</hi> Eve's <hi>Offence,</hi> is plain from what follows, that <hi>Mary brought forth him who was to ſave even his Murderers,</hi> and that <hi>Chriſt was to come of her for the Salvation of Man.</hi> What <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſays of her beſide, is very little and by the bye; as that ſhe was a <hi>Virgin,</hi> becauſe <hi>Chriſt was ſaid to be made of a Woman:</hi> And that being born of her, <hi>he was therefore of the Houſe of</hi> David; and the like.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus,</hi> to illuſtrate a Moral Leſſon, tells us, That <hi>Mary</hi> was a perfect Virgin <hi>after the Birth of her Son,</hi> and mentions a particular proof of it, which ſome affirm'd.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rom. lib.</hi> 7.</note> And farther he ſays not, that I can remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber.</p>
               <p>His Scholar <hi>Origen</hi> acknowledged alſo the perpetual Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginity of <hi>Mary:</hi> And in his <hi>Homilies</hi> upon the firſt Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of St. <hi>Luke,</hi> where he could not avoid ſpeaking of her, he hath theſe paſſages.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>In Luc. Hom.</hi> 7.</note> 
                  <hi>Some body,</hi> ſays he, <hi>I know not who, hath run into ſuch a madneſs as to affirm that</hi> Mary <hi>was renounced by our Saviour, inaſmuch as after his Birth, ſhe was joyned to</hi> Joſeph.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Conte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. pl. of Life,</hi> &amp;c.</note> Now if the Church had then believed the Story of her <hi>Aſſumption</hi> (which hath been ſo <hi>poetically</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed to us of late:) If the Church had then, for an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and fifty years together ſerved her as the <hi>Queen of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> with ſolemn Rites of Worſhip: That man who ventured to diſparage the B. Virgin in this faſhion, was fooliſh to Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. But if <hi>Origen</hi> knew, that the Church had given her theſe Honors from the beginning; he wiſe was enough to have ſtopped this Madman's mouth with that Argument. or rather to have ſaid nothing of him; ſince no body could need any inſtruction to hold him for a ridiculous Fellow. But he thought fit to inſtruct the people, how they ſhould anſwer this man; and that in this manner: <hi>If Mary was pronounced Bleſſed in</hi> thoſe hymns that were uttered by the inſtinct of <hi>the holy Spirit; How can any man ſay, that our Saviour denied her.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:60697:25"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Origen</hi> ſpeaks very honorably of the <hi>B. Virgin;</hi> but yet he repreſents her as an inſtance of humane Frailty, and one that needed Forgiveneſs of ſins, as well as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles: and that becauſe ſhe was offended, as he (it ſeems) was perſwaded at the Paſſion of <hi>Chriſt. What,</hi> ſays he, <hi>do we think that when the Apoſtles were ſcandalized, that the Mother of our Lord was free from it?</hi> And ſo he interprets thoſe words, <hi>A Sword ſhall pierce through thy own Soul alſo,</hi> by this paraphraſe, <hi>The Sword of unbelief ſhall pierce thy own Soul, and thou ſhalt be ſmitten with the edge of Doubtful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi> I doubt it will not be convenient, to enquire of <hi>Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen</hi> any further.</p>
               <p>As for <hi>Athenagoras, Minutius Felix,</hi> St. <hi>Cyprian, Arnobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us Lactantius;</hi> they have left us nothing at all concerning her; unleſs St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſays ſomewhere that <hi>Chriſt</hi> was conceived in the Womb of a <hi>Virgin, &amp;c.</hi> But if that be all, I am ſure he neglected ſome very inviting occaſions of put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting his People in mind of a great deal more; which he ought not to have neglected, if the Doctrine of the <hi>Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive</hi> Church concerning the <hi>B. Virgin,</hi> had been the ſame with that of the <hi>pretended Catholick</hi> Church at this day.</p>
               <p>And ſo we are gotten out of the three firſt Ages. But per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps <hi>Athanaſius</hi> makes amends for all that were before him, in the Sermon upon the <hi>Annuntiation</hi> of the <hi>Bleſſed Virgin.</hi> That Sermon I confeſs is a very ſurpriſing thing to any man, that conſiders there was not the leaſt preparation for the Doctrine it would pretend to eſtabliſh, in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going Ages. But then this (as well as many other things, that go under the name of <hi>Athanaſius</hi>) is none of his; as <hi>Bellarmin,</hi> and others of his party <hi>(obliged by the Strength of Truth)</hi> have actually confeſſed. And in all probability, it was written no leſs than 348 Years after his Death. In his genuine Works, there is more frequent mention of the Virgin, then in the Fathers before him; eſpecially in his
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:60697:26"/>Orations againſt the Arrians, which he wrote about the Year 360. But we muſt go further down, to find where her Worſhip began, for as yet there is no Appearance of it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hilary,</hi> who wrote about the ſame time, ſays nothing new in this Matter.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hilar. Pictav. Com. in Matth.</hi> p. 497.</note> He does Induſtriouſly aſſert the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginity of <hi>Mary,</hi> which, and the like things, were done by ſome of thoſe that went before him. But of her Worſhip not a word.</p>
               <p>To conclude, the Fathers do generally ſpeak of her, without the Addition of any Title of Honor. For the moſt part they call her <hi>Mary:</hi> ſometimes the <hi>Virgin;</hi> the <hi>Mother of our Lord</hi> rarely, and the <hi>mother of God</hi> never, I think, till the Church was obliged to guard the belief of the Divine Nature of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> by all kind of proper Expreſſions. And even then, this honourable Appellation, was uſed not for her ſake, but to ſecure the right Faith of our Lord's Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity, eſpecially againſt the <hi>Nestorian</hi> Hereſie. In ſhort, the Proteſtants do cuſtomarily mention the Virgin Mother, with honorable Additions, beyond what the Fathers of the Three Firſt Ages did. But we <hi>Worſhip</hi> her juſt as they did, that is,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.10.</note> not at all. For my own part, when I conſider that ſhe had the Glorious Priviledge to be the <hi>Mother of God,</hi> I ſhould have much ado to forbear regretting the lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Regard wherewith ſome of the Fathers ſpeak of her ſometimes, but that I find our Saviour himſelf, in thoſe
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 2.49. <hi>Ch.</hi> 11.27, 28. <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.4.</note> three Sayings concerning her, which are reported in the Goſpels, not to Magnify her over greatly. And the Truth is, I ſhould have wondred at that too, had not the exceſs of later Devotion to her put me in mind, that the H. Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters were guided by a Spirit of <hi>Prophecy,</hi> and have there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore recorded nothing that <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſaid to his moſt H. Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but what might be of uſe in ſuch times as theſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:60697:26"/>
               <head>§. 8.</head>
               <p>Let us now ſee whether the Religion of <hi>Praying to Martyrs and Saints,</hi> and <hi>Worſhipping their Images</hi> and <hi>Reliques,</hi> has the Authority of the <hi>Primitive Church</hi> and <hi>all Antiquity.</hi> It may very well be preſumed, that it has not, unleſs we think that the Fathers preferred the other Saints before the B. Virgin. But to ſay the Truth; tho hitherto the Virgin and the reſt of the Saints were equal, as to any Religious Worſhip, neither ſhe nor they being yet thought of for that purpoſe; yet when Superſtition at length began to creep into the Church, the Martyrs got the ſtart of the Virgin. In proceſs of time her Worſhip overtopped theirs; but theirs began before her turn came. The moſt holy <hi>Religion</hi> of the Goſpel was delivered all at once; and, which is moſt conſiderable, it is the Religion which God hath <hi>ſealed,</hi> and ſo it was, and is all of a piece. But the <hi>Corruption</hi> of that Religion coming on by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, as contingent Occaſions gave Birth and Growth to it, could not be regularly contrived, but would need a great deal of patching and mending, to bring it to a Face of Uniformity.</p>
               <p>As for Praying to Saints; I know not how any Man can imagin, that the Primitive Fathers taught or uſed it, who conſiders in what Terms they taught that <hi>God only</hi> was to be Invocated: That they count<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Worſhip of <hi>Invocation,</hi> a better Sacrifice than thoſe which had been offered to God, as the Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> required, and which all acknowledge were to be offered to God <hi>only;</hi> and that they argued the Divini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> from hence that Prayers were to be offered to him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Irenoeus</hi> tells us, that the <hi>Church did nothing by In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocations of Angels, or Incantations to them, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther evil Curioſity. Fevardentius</hi> pretends, that this
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:60697:27"/>excludes <hi>evil</hi> Spirits only from being invoked. But let any unprejudiced Man judge by what follows.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iren. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 57.</note> 
                  <hi>But</hi> ſays he, <hi>ſhe directs her Prayers chaſtly, purely, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly to the Lord that made all things.</hi> Now accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to <hi>Fevardentius</hi> he ſhould have added, <hi>and to good Spirits alſo.</hi> For 'tis a vain thing to ſay, that he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to oppoſe thoſe only that Worſhipped malicious Spirits; ſince if this had been his Intention, the plain laws of Diſcourſe had obliged him rather to omit the <hi>Worſhip of God</hi> in this oppoſition, than the <hi>Worſhip of good Spirits.</hi> And doubtleſs upon this ſuppoſition, he would have ſaid, that <hi>we do not uſe Prayers and Hymns to evil, but to good Spirits.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I cannot but ſet down here the words of the Church of <hi>Smyrna</hi> in their Golden Epiſtle, concerning the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdom of <hi>Polycarp.</hi> It ſeems the <hi>Jews</hi> had ſuggeſted, that if the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> could gain his Body, they would perhaps forſake <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and Worſhip him, (their Love and Reverence of that holy Man, their Biſhop, was ſo well known:) Againſt which ſuggeſtion the <hi>Smyrnians</hi> thus declare themſelves. <hi>Theſe men know not that we can neither forſake Chriſt, who ſuffered for the Salvation of all that are ſaved, the Innocent for the Guilty; nor Worſhip any other. Him truly being the Son of God, we adore: But the Martyrs and Diſciples and Followers of the Lord, we justly love, for that extraordinary good mind, which they have expreſſed toward their King and Maſter; of whoſe happineſs God grant, that we may par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take, and that we may learn by their Examples.</hi> This Teſtimony of the Church of <hi>Smyrna</hi> I rather produce in this place; becauſe in two Ancient Manuſcripts ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the moſt learned Arch. B. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher,</hi> the <hi>Latin</hi> Tranſlation of their Proteſtation runs thus.
<note place="margin">See <hi>Act. Uſſer. Polic.</hi> or <hi>Anſw. to the Jeſuita Challenge? Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Saints.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>We Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians can never forſake Christ, who vouchſafed to ſuffer ſo great things for our ſins, nor give away the Worſhip of Prayer to any other.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:60697:27"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Clemens Alexandr.</hi> defines Prayer by its Relation to God, in which (as
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>Bellarmin</hi> acknowledges) he was followed by divers Fathers in the Fourth <hi>Century.</hi> But nothing can be more plain, than this Paſſage of his. <hi>Since there is but one good God, both We and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels pray to him</hi>
                  <note n="(b)" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>Strom.</hi> l. 7. p. 721.</note> 
                  <hi>alone; that thoſe good things may be given us, which we want, and thoſe continued which we have.</hi> If half ſo plain a Teſtimony could have been produced out of the genuine Writings of theſe Fathers, for praying to others beſides God, as theſe are for praying to God alone; I fear we ſhould have been counted very impudent, in our Appeals to the <hi>Primitive</hi> Church, and the beſt Antiquity. The ſame Perſon had ſaid not long before, <hi>We do juſtly honor God by Prayer, and with Righteouſneſs we ſend up this beſt and most Holy Sacrifice.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And I find this to have been another gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Notion of the Worſhip of Prayer amongſt the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cients, that it was a Sacrifice much better, than thoſe more ſenſible Sacrifices, that were either offered by the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> or required by the Law of <hi>Moſes;</hi> and more pleaſing to God. Thus ſays <hi>Tertullian; We ſacrifice for the Health and Safety of the Emperor, but we do it to our God, and his God; and we do it, as God hath commanded, with</hi>
                  <note n="(c)" place="margin">Pura prece.</note> 
                  <hi>pure Prayer,</hi> or <hi>purely with Prayer:</hi> for ſo he is to be underſtood, in as much as he oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the <hi>Purity</hi> of Prayer, to the
<note n="(d)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Odoris aut ſanguinis. Yert. ad Scap. c.</hi> 2.</note> Sacrifices of <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſe</hi> and <hi>Victims.</hi> And therefore, ſays he, <hi>We pray rather for the Health of the Emperor, deſiring it of him who can give it.</hi> This ſmart Writer, did in his way, very plainly repreſent our Doctrine in the fore-mentioned Saying. <hi>We Sacrifice,</hi> ſays he, <hi>but to our God, and his God.</hi> There he repreſents Sacrifice, as due to God only: <hi>But we do it, as God hath command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, with pure Prayer.</hi> There he repreſents Prayer as
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:60697:28"/>a Sacrifice more Excellent, than that of <hi>Odors</hi> and <hi>Blood,</hi> which the <hi>Gentiles</hi> offered. And can any thing be more evident, than that he appropriates this Sacrifice ſo to God, that it ought not to be given to any elſe? Thus alſo he proves againſt the <hi>Jews,</hi> That <hi>we muſt now ſacrifice to God, not earthly, but ſpiritual Sacrifices; for 'tis written, A contrite Heart, and an humble Heart,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ad. Jud. c.</hi> 5.</note> 
                  <hi>is a Sacrifice to God;</hi> and elſewhere <hi>Offer the Sacrifice of Praiſe, and pay thy Vows to the moſt High.</hi> And therefore, a little after he affirms <hi>Christ</hi> to be <hi>the High Preist of eternal Sacrifices,</hi> in Oppoſition to thoſe that are aboliſhed. Nay, he ſays that the <hi>pure Offering,</hi>
                  <note n="(e)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Simplex o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratio Adv. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rei. c.</hi> 1.</note> foretold in <hi>Malachy,</hi> which all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions ſhould bring, is the <hi>Simplicity of Prayer from the pure Conſcience,</hi> which he elſewhere deſcribes by <hi>Bleſſing,</hi> and <hi>Praiſe,</hi> and <hi>Hymns;</hi> and ſo is the ſame with <hi>Pure Prayer</hi> mentioned before. This is enough to ſhew, that in his days, the Church would no more have offered <hi>Invocations</hi> of <hi>Prayer</hi> or <hi>Praiſe</hi> to any but to God; then they would have offered <hi>Victims</hi> to any but to him, if they had been continued in the Service of the Church.</p>
               <p>And by this we may ſee, in what ſort we are to underſtand that Offering for the Martyrs, which we read of in <hi>Tertullian</hi> and St.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>De Coronâ. c.</hi> 3. <hi>De Exhort. c.</hi> 13. <hi>Demen.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Cyprian.</hi> Says <hi>Tertullian, We make Oblations for them that are departed, in Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of their Birth-days, i. e.</hi> of the Days wherein they were crowned with Martyrdom. And thus St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> writing to the Church of <hi>Carthge,</hi> concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Celerinus,</hi> and making mention of his Uncles <hi>Lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentinus</hi> and <hi>Ignatius</hi> ſays,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cypr. Epiſt.</hi> 34. Rig.</note> 
                  <hi>We offer Sacrifice for them, you may remember, as often as we celebrate the Days upon which the Martyrs ſuffered, with an Anniverſary Commemoration.</hi> And thus he writes to the Clergy of <hi>Carthage,</hi> concerning the Confeſſors, that ſhould dye
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:60697:28"/>in Priſon. <hi>Note down the days of their death,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Id. Epiſt.</hi> 37.</note> 
                  <hi>that we may Celebrate their Commemorations amongſt the Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of the Martyrs, &amp;c.</hi> The meaning of which is, that they <hi>gave Thanks,</hi> and <hi>offered Praiſes</hi> to God for thoſe holy Perſons by name, who had conſtantly ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered Death, for the Faith of Chriſt. Theſe were the Sacrifices they offered for the Martyrs, the <hi>Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices of Praiſe;</hi> not excluding, what by other Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities is evident enough, <hi>the Sacrifice of Prayers</hi> for them too, and for all the departed Saints, that they might at length obtain the promiſed Reſurrection. I do not ſay, that the Worſhip of <hi>Chriſtians</hi> conſiſted on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of theſe Sacrifices.
<note place="margin">See Mr. <hi>Mede</hi> upon <hi>Mincha purum.</hi>
                  </note> They had the <hi>Oblation of Bread and Wine</hi> beſides, <hi>before</hi> the <hi>Euchariſt;</hi> and the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentative Sacrifice</hi> of our Lord's Body and Blood <hi>in</hi> the <hi>Euchariſt.</hi> It is enough, that the Religious Invo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations of the Church, were held to be the Worſhip of Sacrifice, and that of
<note n="(f)" place="margin">Sacrificio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum officia po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiora Adv. Maſſ.</note> a <hi>more excellent Kind,</hi> then the <hi>earthly Sacrifices</hi> of Jews and Gentiles, as <hi>Tertal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> calls them. And let the <hi>pretended Catholicks</hi> tell us, to whom the Worſhip of Sacrifice ſhould be offered but to God. They have, I confeſs, kept the Stile of the Antient Church; and pretend to <hi>Sacrifice</hi> to God, and to him only. But the Change which they have made in the Doctrine and Practice of the Church, hath obliged them to apply that <hi>Style,</hi> otherwiſe than the Antient Church did.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exp.</hi> §. 3.4.</note> When they ſpeak of <hi>offering Sacrifice,</hi> as Monſieur de <hi>Meaux</hi> does in his Expoſition, we are according to the uſe of that Phraſe in their Writers, to underſtand nothing but the pretended <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of the Maſs.</hi> But why muſt not the people be taught, that the Worſhip of Prayers and Hymns is a Sacrifice too? For this was the current Doctrine of the Primitive Church. There is a good Reaſon for it; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they do not pay this Worſhip to God alone, as the Primitive Church did.</p>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:60697:29"/>
               <p> And now as for thoſe paſſages, concerning <hi>Oblations</hi> and <hi>Sacrifices</hi> already produced,
<note place="margin">See <hi>Conſtit. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtol. lib.</hi> 7. <hi>c.</hi> 3.</note> and many more to the like purpoſe, that might be produced out of the Fathers; I do not know how far a willing mind might go, to apply them to the <hi>Sacrifice of the Maſs.</hi> And when that is done, it is but a little ſtraining more, and they will interpret <hi>Gregory Nazianzen</hi> to their own mind too; who in his Funeral oration upon St. <hi>Baſil,</hi> thus ſpeaks of him. <hi>And now he is in Heaven,</hi>
                  <note n="(g)" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>as I think he offers Sacrifices for us and Prayers for the People.</hi> But I am confident <hi>Nazianzen,</hi> did not ſo much as <hi>think</hi> that <hi>Baſil</hi> ſaid <hi>maſs in Heaven</hi> for him and the People.</p>
               <p>To proceed, <hi>Origen</hi> is as expreſs to this purpoſe as his Maſter <hi>Clemens Alex.</hi> He ſaith <hi>we muſt pray to him</hi>
                  <note n="(h)" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>Orig. contr. Celſ. lib.</hi> 8.</note> 
                  <hi>alone that is God over all, and we must pray to the word of God his only begotten, and the firſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born of every Creature; and we muſt humbly beſeech him, as our high Prieſt, to preſent our prayer (for it is known to him) to his Father and the Father of them that live according to the word of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is enough for one man to ſay, in ſo plain a caſe. And yet I will add, what he ſays about this matter, from another common Argument, <hi>viz.</hi> that the Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of <hi>Chriſt</hi> is clearly gathered from our making pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers to him. For upon thoſe words of the Apoſtle. <hi>With all that call upon the Name of the Lord Jeſus,</hi> he ſaith,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Orig. in</hi> Decim. <hi>ad</hi> Rom. <hi>lib.</hi> 8.</note> that <hi>the Apoſtle pronounces Jeſus Chriſt to be God, in that his name is called upon;</hi> and that <hi>to call upon the name of the Lord, and to adore God, is one and the ſame thing.</hi> The Reaſon of this which I have ventured to offer is, That <hi>Prayer</hi> does aſcribe, <hi>Omnipreſence,</hi> as well as other divine Perfections, to the Being to which it is made. And this is that reaſon which <hi>Tertullian,</hi> as I think,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Yert. de Orat: cap.</hi> 1.</note> hath expreſſed in theſe words: That <hi>Faith offers its Religion to him only, of whom it is confident
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:60697:29"/>that he ſees and hears every where.</hi> For by <hi>Religion</hi> he meant Prayer, which is the Subject of that diſcourſe to which theſe words belong. Thus <hi>Novatian</hi> alſo:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Nov. de Trin. c.</hi> 14.</note> If <hi>Chriſt be only a man, how is he every where preſent to thoſe that call upon him; ſince this is not the nature of Man but of God to be preſent in all places!</hi> And in the ſame place, If <hi>Chriſt be only a Man, why is a Man invoked as a Mediator in prayers; ſince the Invocation of Man, muſt be judged ineffectual for the procuring of Salvation?</hi> And to name no more, <hi>Athanaſius</hi> frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly uſes this kind of Argument. For ſpeaking of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, made to the Son of God, he ſays,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Athan. Orat. contra Arrian.</hi> 2.4.</note> 
                  <hi>the Saints do not think it just, to invoke him to be their Helper and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge, who was made</hi> or created. And no man would pray to receive any thing from the <hi>Fathers and the Angels, or from any of the other Creatures:</hi> from whence he concludes that becauſe the Apoſtle in 1 Theſſ 3.11. does not only pray to God the <hi>Father,</hi> but alſo to our <hi>Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> that therefore <hi>Christ</hi> is God. It ſeems it was not then the way of Chriſtians to joyn God, and St. <hi>Michael,</hi> God and the <hi>Virgin,</hi> God and <hi>all the Saints,</hi> in Invocations of prayers. There were then no ſuch things known, as <hi>Confeſſion</hi> to God and to St. <hi>Michael,</hi> and to the <hi>Bleſſed Virgin,</hi> and to the <hi>Saints;</hi> as giving <hi>Glory</hi> to the Holy Trinity and to the <hi>Virgin;</hi> as ſaying <hi>Jeſus Mary help.</hi> &amp;c. had a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing of this Nature been done in thoſe times. I doubt here had been a good Argument loſt, by which the Fathers proved <hi>Chriſt</hi> to be God. Nor would <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thanaſius</hi> have been ſo meer a Child, as to attaque the <hi>Arrians</hi> with an Argument, to which the Doctrine and Practice of the Church, had afforded ſo obvious and effectual an Anſwer.</p>
               <p>To all which I ſhall add but that Canon of the <hi>Laodicean Synod,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Synod. Laod. cap.</hi> 35.</note> that <hi>Chriſtians ought not to forſake
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:60697:30"/>the Church of God, and depart aſide and Invocate Angels Therefore if any man be found uſing this ſecret Idolatry, let him be accurſed, becauſe he hath forſaken our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> I make no queſtion, but if there had been occaſion Saints had been put into the Canon as well as <hi>Angels.</hi> But then what word could they have thought of, inſtead of <hi>Saints,</hi> to anſwer <hi>Corners [Angulos]</hi> which <hi>Crab</hi> thruſt into the old <hi>Latin</hi> Tranſlation inſtead of <hi>Angels [Angelos]</hi> is not very eaſy to imagine. Concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing which pleaſant Forgery, ſee Bp <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſhers</hi> Anſwer to the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> Challenge. <hi>p.</hi> 469. &amp;c.</p>
               <p>And now if we conſider, the Doctrine of theſe pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Fathers concerning Prayer, I ſuppoſe we ſhall not wonder, that in thoſe places where we might well have expected ſome inſtance of praying to Saints, or ſome Recommendation of it (if any ſuch Practice had been amongſt them) that I ſay there is nothing at all,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cypr. de Lapſ. p.</hi> 177.</note> no not the leaſt intimation of it. Not where St. <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian</hi> ſo vehemently admoniſhed thoſe, that were <hi>fallen</hi> in perſecution, to pray to God for themſelves, and to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat the <hi>Brethren</hi> to do ſo too:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Tert. de Pani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiâ. c.</hi> 9.</note> Not where <hi>Tertullian</hi> deſcribes the Humiliations and Proſtrations of the <hi>Peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents;</hi> in both which places one would have expected, that the Interceſſion of the <hi>Saints</hi> and <hi>Martyrs,</hi> ſhould have been implored: Not where <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribes the <hi>Service</hi> of the Church in her Religious Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies; nor in any of the ancient <hi>Apologies,</hi> nor in any ancient account of the Religious Worſhip of <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Apost. Constit. lib.</hi> 7, 8.</note> no not in the <hi>Apoſtolical Conſtitutions</hi> (though a later work then it pretends to be) where the order of the Churches Service is very particularly deſcribed: We are not to wonder at it. I ſay for the declared Doctrine of the Church was againſt it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:60697:30"/>
               <head>§ 8.</head>
               <p>As for the <hi>Worſhipping,</hi> or as <hi>M. de Meaux</hi> calls it, the <hi>Honouring</hi> of Images, we might ſpare the pains of inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring what the ſence of the Ancient Church was concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it; it is ſo hard to believe that they ſhould worſhip the <hi>Images</hi> of the Saints, who did not ſo much as pray, or give any Religious Worſhip to the <hi>Saints</hi> themſelves. But this practice is ſo far from having the Countenance of the <hi>Primitive</hi> Church, and <hi>All</hi> Antiquity; that in the beſt Ages, there were men of great name in the Church, that did not believe ſo much as the <hi>Art</hi> of <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magery</hi> and <hi>Picture</hi> lawful to be practiſed by a Chriſtian. Saith <hi>Clemens Alex.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Protrept. ad Gentes.</note> 
                  <hi>We are plainly forbidden to meddle with that cheating Art: For the Prophet</hi> [Moſes] <hi>ſaith, Thou ſhalt not make the likeneſs of any thing either in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven or in Earth. Tertullian</hi> hath a great deal to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe in his Diſcourſe of <hi>Idolatry.</hi> But thoſe words are, to my thinking, very remarkable. <hi>Well did the ſame God require the likeneſs of a Serpent to be made by an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Command,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Tert. de Idol.</hi> c. 5, 6.</note> 
                  <hi>who by his Law forbad the making of any likeneſs. If thou obſerveſt the ſame God, thou haſt his Law: Make no likeneſs. If alſo thou lookeſt to the Precept of making an Image afterward, do thou alſo imitate</hi> Moſes: <hi>Make no Image whatſoever againſt the Law, unleſs God alſo command thee in particular ſo to do.</hi> Which words are ſo plain and full, that they leave no room for that frivolous pretence, that theſe Fathers intended no other Images, but thoſe of the Heathen Gods. And that inſtance of the <hi>Brazen Serpent,</hi> which was no Idol, till the Jews made it one, clearly ſhews the contrary.</p>
               <p>But if it be ſaid that the Authority of theſe men is to go for nothing, becauſe they were miſtaken in condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:60697:31"/>
                  <hi>Image-Work</hi> ſo univerſally as they did; I grant, that their zeal againſt <hi>Image-Worſhip</hi> tranſported them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the bounds of Reaſon; eſpecially <hi>Tertullian,</hi> who in the foreſaid Book tells us,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ibid.</hi> c. 2.</note> that <hi>Artificers of Statues and Images, and all carved or engraven works of this kind, were brought into the World by the Devil.</hi> But this I ſay, that if Images had in thoſe days been uſed in <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Churches, ſo much as to excite the <hi>Devotion</hi> of the Faithful, much more to receive their <hi>Adoration;</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther would theſe Fathers have condemned the making of Images; nor, if they had, would the Church have born with ſo great an Outrage upon their Doctrine and Practice. Some one at leaſt would have appeared in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half of the <hi>Catholick</hi> Church, as <hi>Melchior Canus</hi> has done in behalf of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church againſt the <hi>Eliberine</hi> Council in this matter; who ſticks not to ſay, that <hi>Their Law for taking away Images,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Canus, loc. Theol.</hi> l. 5. c. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>was not onely imprudent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but impiouſly eſtabliſhed.</hi> The Cenſure which he ſo long after paſs'd upon that Council, had been faſtned up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on theſe men preſently, by more than one, as good as <hi>Canus,</hi> if <hi>Image-Worſhip</hi> had but been allowed then, as it is now eſtabliſhed in the <hi>Roman</hi> Communion. They were not ſo tame as to ſuffer their Worſhip to be affron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by their own Members, without taking notice of it. But the truth is,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Euſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>h.</hi> Hiſt. lib. 7. c. 18. <hi>Iren.</hi> l. 1. c. 24.</note> the Monuments of the Ancient Church affords us no accounts of Images any where, but either in <hi>Libraries,</hi> or
<note n="*" place="margin">Concerning the Image of the <hi>Syropheni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian Woman,</hi> &amp;c. ſee Dr. <hi>Still.</hi> againſt <hi>T. G.</hi> p. 253.</note> at a Houſe-door, or in the <hi>Holes</hi> of <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks,</hi> or in the <hi>Temples</hi> of falſe Gods. We read indeed of one <hi>Picture</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> or ſome Saint, which <hi>Epiphanius</hi> found in a Curtain of the Church of <hi>Anablatha;</hi> but he took it down and tore it in pieces. Such accounts as this are not for the credit of <hi>Image Worſhip;</hi> which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed came into the Church at the tail of other Corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. And the Fathers are ſo unanimous and poſitive a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:60697:31"/>it, that I will ſhut up this matter with the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of a great many Fathers in one teſtimony, <hi>viz.</hi> that of the <hi>Eliberine</hi> Council held about the beginning of the fourth Age. <hi>It is our pleaſure,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Concil. Elib.</hi> Can. 36.</note> 
                  <hi>that Pictures ought not to be in the Church, lest that which is worſhipped or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dored, ſhould be painted upon Walls.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As for the <hi>Reliques</hi> of Saints and Martyrs, we hear of none for the three firſt Ages, but their <hi>Bodies;</hi> nor any thing concerning them, but that they were interred with all poſſible Reſpect that could be expected from <hi>Men,</hi> and which is more, from <hi>Chriſtians.</hi> The honour which by the cuſtom of the World we learn is proper to the Bodies of the Dead, is to give them a decent Interment. This was maintained and cheriſhed by the ancient <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Orig. contra Celſ.</hi> lib. 5. <hi>Tertul. de A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimâ.</hi>
                  </note> not onely becauſe reaſonable Souls once lived in thoſe Bodies which they committed to the ground, which was an Inducement common to men; but becauſe alſo thoſe Bodies and Souls were to be once again joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at the Reſurrection, which was an Inducement pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to <hi>Chriſtians.</hi> It was the ſame kind of honour which they ſhewed to the Bodies of Martyrs, though heightned with the expreſſions of a more than ordinary love. Thus, after the Martyrdom of St. <hi>Stephen, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout men</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Acts 8.2.</note> 
                  <hi>carried him out</hi> to be buried, <hi>and made great lamentation over him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The like account did the <hi>Smyrnians</hi> give of their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing the Bones of <hi>Polycarp,</hi> which they reckoned <hi>more valuable than precious Stones, more precious than Gold. M. de Meaux</hi> ſure would not deſire a farther <hi>progreſſion of Love and Honour.</hi> But with this degree they contented themſelves: for ſay they,
<note n="†" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>Sm. Epiſt.</hi> ſupr.</note> 
                  <hi>We committed them to bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial where it was uſual.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And thus <hi>Pius</hi> the firſt of that name, Biſhop of <hi>Rome. Take care,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>of the Bodies of the Holy Martyrs, as
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:60697:32"/>of Gods Members,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cura, quemad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modum cura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verunt. Curare</hi> here, is the ſame with <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>Pius.</hi> Epiſt. 2. Tom. 1. Con. See <hi>Cypr.</hi> Ep. 37. <hi>Cypr.</hi> Epiſt. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>after that manner that the Apoſtles took care of</hi> Stephen<hi>'s.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus the Clergy of <hi>Rome</hi> in their Epiſtle to the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy of <hi>Carthage,</hi> when St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> was abſent: To ſpeak of <hi>a matter of very great conſequence. If the Bodies of Martyrs or others be not buried, it is a very dangerous fault in thoſe that are to look after this buſineſs.</hi> So that in thoſe days, it ſhould ſeem to be a Charge entruſted to ſelect Perſons, that the Bodies of Martyrs and other Chriſtians, ſhould be buried; and this not onely at <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thage,</hi> but at <hi>Rome</hi> too.</p>
               <p>But why ſhould I multiply Teſtimonies in ſo plain a caſe? Had the <hi>Reliques</hi> of Martyrs and Saints been worſhipped in thoſe beſt times, as they were afterward, how come it to paſs that in all the Monuments of thoſe times, no mention of any ſuch thing is to be found? When the Trade of Reliques began in the Church, there was noiſe enough made of it, and the beſt Authors ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint us with the News. But it had been no News, if the Trade had been begun before. Why was no ſuch thing objected to the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> by their watchful Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, for three hundred years together? For we no ſooner come to hear of Stories of Reliques in the Church, but we find the <hi>Pagans</hi> at the heels of this Innovation, and upbraiding the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> with the ſuperſtition of it. Why meet we not with ſome intimation of laying up Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques in Churches under the Altar? There was room enough for ſo conſiderable and neceſſary a circumſtance, (and the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> makes more than a circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of it) in that particular deſcription of the faſhion and Ornaments of the Church built by <hi>Paulinus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Tyre.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Euſeb.</hi> Hiſt. lib. 20. c. 4.</note> Why meet we with no Tranſlations of <hi>Bodies</hi> from one place to another, for their greater honour? Perhaps we ſhall be told of the men from the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> that
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:60697:32"/>came to <hi>Rome,</hi> and challenged the Bodies of St. <hi>Peter</hi> and St. <hi>Paul,</hi> as of right belonging to them; and of their carrying them two Miles out of Town to a place called <hi>Catacumboe,</hi> and all the other Adventures that <hi>Gregory</hi> tells upon this buſineſs. But then there will ariſe a great queſtion,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Greg.</hi> lib. 3. Ep. 30. <hi>Baron.</hi> A. D. 221. N. 4.</note> whether we are to believe with <hi>Gregory</hi> that they were <hi>Eaſtern Believers,</hi> or with <hi>Baronius,</hi> that they were <hi>Thieviſh Greeks?</hi> or rather it will be no queſtion, that the whole Relation is fabulous from one end to the other.</p>
               <p>In ſhort, why have we all this time no account of Miracles wrought by Reliques, of carrying them about in Proceſſions, of expoſing them to receive the Adorati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the People, of wearing them as a ſpecial ſecurity againſt Spiritual and Temporal Evils, or of any inſtance of this kind of Religion? I anſwer, It is a fond thing to imagine, that the Religion of Worſhipping the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques</hi> of the Saints, ſhould be in uſe amongſt them, who gave no Religious Worſhip to the <hi>Saints</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
               <p>But it is not to be wonder'd at, that they who pray to the <hi>Souls</hi> of the Saints and Martyrs, who are ſo far <hi>abſent</hi> from us, that they hear us not, ſhould be guilty of another weakneſs, and Worſhip their <hi>Bones</hi> and other <hi>Reliques,</hi> which neither hear nor ſee, though they are <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This account of the Sentiments of the Three firſt <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,</hi> and indeed of the better half of the <hi>Fourth</hi> we gather from the Writings of the Fathers, and from the undou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bted Monuments of thoſe Times. Monſieur <hi>de Meaux</hi> knew that theſe things had been diligently expounded by thoſe of the Reformation, and particularly by <hi>M. Daille.</hi> And what does he oppoſe to this, to ſave his pretences to <hi>All Antiquity</hi> harmleſs? Says he,
<note place="margin">Exp. p. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>Without
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:60697:33"/>any farther examination what might be the Sentiments of the Fathers of the Three firſt Ages, I will content my ſelf with what</hi> M. Daille <hi>is pleaſed to grant, who allows us ſo many great men who taught the Church in the Fourth Age.</hi> Now <hi>M. Daille</hi> neither made any ſuch allowance, nor had he any reaſon to make it. But ſuppoſe he had, muſt all that he had written concerning the ſence of the Three firſt Ages, about the <hi>Object of Worſhip,</hi> go for nothing? If this example of Writing is ſit to be followed, I know not why I ſhould give my ſelf any farther trouble, and not rather conclude thus:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rereſius</hi> de Tradition. par. 3. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> That <hi>without any farther exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination what may be the Sentiments of the Fathers of the following Age, I ſhall content my ſelf with what ſome great men of the</hi> Roman <hi>Church are pleaſed to grant, and which is evidently proved againſt all the reſt that deny it,</hi> viz. <hi>That the Fathers of the Three first Ages must be allowed to us.</hi> And ſo leave it to the World to judge who has moſt rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to be <hi>content.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
               <head>§ 9.</head>
               <p>But having undertaken to give ſome account of the beginnings of the preſent Superſtitions of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> in the matter of Saint-Worſhip, and the Adoration of the Images and Reliques of the Saints: And becauſe it is impoſſible to do this, without going beyond the firſt Ages, till we come to the Reign of <hi>Julian;</hi> I muſt ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture beyond him, and conſider the ſtate of the Church toward the latter end of the Fourth Century, with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to theſe queſtions. <hi>Some</hi> of the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> pretend that Antiquity to be on their ſide, which I have ſhewn is with us. But as far as I can perceive, they <hi>all</hi> pretend to be very confident they ſhall carry it thus high at leaſt; and Monſieur <hi>de Meaux</hi> takes it for granted, that we
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:60697:33"/>begin to allow them thoſe later Fathers. I ſhall endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to repreſent the caſe as impartially as if I were yet to chuſe my Opinion; and I am very much miſtaken if it will not appear in concluſion (though there is a little more colour for their challenging the latter end of the Fourth Age, in favour of their Doctrine and Practices in theſe things, than for appealing to higher Antiquity) that upon a true conſideration of the grounds upon which they challenge theſe later Fathers as their own, it had been more adviſable for them to have come down much lower to find Preſidents whereby to juſtifie them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. It had been a very Ancient cuſtom of the Church for <hi>Christians</hi> to meet at the <hi>Coemiteries</hi> or Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying-places of the Martyrs and the reſt of the Faithful, there to celebrate Anniverſary Commemorations of the <hi>Martyrs.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ep. <hi>Smyr.</hi> ubi ſuprà.</note> Thus the Church of <hi>Smyrna</hi> having intimated that they had buried the Body of St. <hi>Polycarp</hi> in the uſual place, they added, that in <hi>that place, God willing, they ſhould aſſemble together to celebrate the Birth-day of his Martyrdom with all the joy they could expreſs:</hi> And the reaſon of this Cuſtom they expreſs in this manner: <hi>Both to Commemorate thoſe who had already undergone the tryal of Martyrdom, and to exerciſe and to prepare thoſe that were to follow, for the like Conflicts.</hi> But they did not meet here to celebrate the <hi>Memories</hi> of the <hi>Martyrs</hi> one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but at other times alſo for the celebration of Divine Service.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Euſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>b.</hi> Hiſt. lib. 7. c. 11.</note> For we find that <hi>Valerian</hi> and <hi>Gallien</hi> forbad the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> to celebrate Aſſemblies, or to meet at thoſe places which they called <hi>Coemiteries,</hi> which paſſages and the like imply that it was <hi>ordinary</hi> for them to Aſſemble there: And it is not improbable that they uſed thoſe places for more privacy, when there was danger of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution; and that the prohibition of Aſſemblies in thoſe <hi>Coemiteries,</hi> was the utmoſt ſtrictneſs of prohibiting their
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:60697:34"/>Aſſemblies: For it is plain that they had their <hi>Churches</hi> beſides in Cities, which they built and repaired according to their ability.
<note place="margin">Id. lib. 8. c. 1.</note> And ſo in that favourable time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Gallien</hi> and <hi>Diocleſian,</hi> we find that they added new Churches in every City, to thoſe which they had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. But whether they were wont to meet at the <hi>Coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miteries</hi> (at other times beſides the Anniverſary days of the Martyrs) for privacy, or perhaps for the Commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of thoſe places, when they did not conſult pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vacy, as ſome think, or whether it was out of ſpecial re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to the <hi>Memories</hi> of thoſe Martyrs, I ſhall not need to diſpute; for it is a clear caſe that they ſervently loved thoſe excellent men and women, and honoured their Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mories, who had laid down their lives for the Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of <hi>Jeſus.</hi> This was one reaſon of celebrating their Anniverſary Commemorations, in which they did what highly became them, and carefully kept themſelves with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in this Compaſs, that Religious Worſhip was to be given to God only.</p>
               <p>But when under <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great the profeſſion of Chriſtianity was not onely ſafe, but the way to Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Greatneſs, the <hi>Memories</hi> of the <hi>Martyrs</hi> were more frequented than they had formerly been, and ſtate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Churches were built over their Sepulchres; and the Emperour, the Clergy, and the People, ſeemed to vie with one another who ſhould expreſs the greateſt zeal in carrying on ſo pious a work; which extraordinary fervor, conſidering the time, was not to be wondered at; for the Church was but now deliver'd not onely out of a raging Perſecution, but from the apprehenſion of any more, and therefore could not but reflect upon the <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs</hi> with all tenderneſs of affection. And ſince they were not now alive, to partake in the proſperous and triumphant ſtate of the Church, it was natural to give
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:60697:34"/>their <hi>Names</hi> and <hi>Memories</hi> all that ſhare in it which was poſſible to be given; eſpecially ſince the preſent peace and glory of the Church, was under God, ſo deeply ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the noble examples of their Fortitude and Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. The Commemorations of the Martyrs had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formerly a double end, to do honour and expreſs a dear affection to them; and withal to prepare and to excite the Virtue of thoſe that were to ſuffer afterward, which latter end without all doubt was the moſt neceſſary; but there being now ſo little occaſion for that, the piety of theſe proſperous times ran out more plentifully in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing honours to thoſe Champions of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> that had born the heat of the day, and left this Age to enjoy that victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and ſweet peace wherewith God had now crowned his perſecuted Church.</p>
               <p>And as this Zeal was no more than what might be expected from Humane Affection, raiſed by <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Piety; ſo if men could have told where to ſtop, it had been as much for the honour of <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> as the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes to which it grew afterwards were a diſgrace to it.</p>
               <p>From <hi>Conſtantine</hi>'s coming to the Empire, to the Reign of <hi>Julian,</hi> there paſſed above fifty years; and in this time the Reverence of the Martyrs was grown to ſome exceſs, beyond Primitive Examples. For it was not onely thought reaſonable to build Churches over their Sepulchres, but it ſhould ſeem there were many that thought their Prayers would ſpeed the better for being made over the Tombs of the Martyrs; and not content with this, they began at length to ſearch for their Bones; and it grew to be the Piety of this Age, to diſturb the Aſhes of the Dead, which it was the Piety of the former Ages to leave in their Graves without di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbance. But as yet their Prayers were directed to
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:60697:35"/>God onely; we have yet no examples of calling upon the Saints and Martyrs. <hi>Julian</hi> himſelf who aggravated the reſpect ſhewn to the Martyrs to the utmoſt, could not charge them with this, and he very well underſtood their practice.
<note place="margin">Apud <hi>Cyrill.</hi> l. 10. contra <hi>Julian.</hi> p. 335.</note> But, ſays he, <hi>Since Jeſus has ſaid that Sepulchres are full of uncleanneſs, why do you call upon God over Sepulchres?</hi> It's true, he alſo charged them with Worſhipping the Martyrs, and upbraided them, that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving forſaken the Religious Rites of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> they had gone over to the <hi>Jews,</hi> and yet had not kept to their Religion neither, which had been ſomething. For, <hi>then,</hi> ſays he,
<note place="margin">Id. lib. 6. p. 201.</note> 
                  <hi>you would have worſhipped one God inſtead of many, and not one man</hi> [Jeſus] <hi>or rather many miſerable men:</hi> meaning the Martyrs. But this was onely a ſpiteful conſtruction of the cuſtom of <hi>Chriſtians</hi> in paying their Devotions to God over the Sepulchres of the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs.</p>
               <p>Not long after <hi>Julian,</hi> comes <hi>Eunapius,</hi> a moſt bitter wretch; by whoſe Cenſures we may eaſily obſerve, that the Devotion of Chriſtians towards the Martyrs was ſtill growing to a greater height. I perceive he is cited both by Proteſtants and Papiſts; by Proteſtants, to ſhew the beginnings of that Superſtition we complain of; by Papiſts, to ſhew that the Invocation of Saints, and the Worſhip of Reliques, was at leaſt ſo Ancient. This Infidel ſpeaking of <hi>Monks</hi> (a ſort of men which this Age firſt brought forth) ſays, that they <hi>heaped together Bones and Sculls of men that had been puniſhed for many Crimes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eunapius</hi> in vitâ Aedeſſi.</note> 
                  <hi>holding them for Gods; and proſtrating themſelves before ſuch as had been chaſtized by order of the Courts of Juſtice; and believing the better of themſelves for being polluted at their Sepulchres. So that they who were but mere ſlaves, and thoſe none of the beſt, but ſoundly laſht, and carrying ſtill the ſcars and marks of their villany in their very Ghoſts,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:60697:35"/>are now called Martyrs, and made the Miniſters and Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers of Prayer to the Gods.</hi> Thus did the baſe Villain reproach the bleſſed Martyrs of <hi>Jeſus,</hi> in contempt of the <hi>Monks,</hi> and indeed of all the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> in thoſe times. For though it ſhould ſeem that the Trade of <hi>Reliques</hi> was chiefly driven by the <hi>Monks,</hi> yet 'tis evident that great account was made of Reliques in almoſt all pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; which together with the daily reſort of devout <hi>Christians</hi> to the <hi>Memories</hi> of the Martyrs, gave <hi>occaſion</hi> to this Infidel thus to upbraid them. For no man will believe <hi>all</hi> to be true which he here charges even the <hi>Monks</hi> with. A malicious Enemy always ſays the worſt that he has any colour or pretence to ſay. And if ſuch occaſions and pretences had been afforded by the Ancient <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> as by theſe, we ſhould certainly have heard the ſame objections from <hi>Lucian</hi> or <hi>Celſus,</hi> or ſome one Pagan Writer of thoſe times, who were as able, as ſpite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and vigilant Adverſaries as <hi>Julian</hi> and <hi>Eunapius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But whereas <hi>Eunapius</hi> pretended, that theſe <hi>Monks</hi> called the Martyrs, <hi>Miniſters and Meſſengers of their Prayers;</hi> he might poſſibly have no other reaſon for it, but the common obſervation that Chriſtians went to the Sepulchres of the Saints, there to make their Prayers. For although they directly applied themſelves to none but God when they were there; yet the chuſing of thoſe places for their Devotions, eſpecially with a profeſſion of hoping to ſpeed the better for ſo doing, was occaſion e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to <hi>Eunapius</hi> to ſay, that they made the Martyrs, <hi>the Miniſters and Meſſengers of their Prayers.</hi> But for ought any man can tell, <hi>Eunapius</hi> might come to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand that theſe <hi>Monks</hi> did, what I queſtion not was the cuſtom of ſome <hi>Chriſtians</hi> towards the latter end of this Age; that is, that they called to the Martyrs at their Memories, as if they were preſent there, of which I ſhall
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:60697:36"/>give a farther account in its proper place. It is certain, that many Miracles were ſaid to be done upon Prayers made where the Reliques of the Martyrs were, that is, at their Memories.</p>
               <p>And ſome thereupon believed that they were done at their Interceſſion, and, joyning their own Prayers with the Prayers of the Chriſtian that came thither. In which they were more confirmed by ſome confident Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports of Viſions and Apparitions of the <hi>Martyrs</hi> to thoſe that had obtained their ſuits.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aug.</hi> de Curâ pro Mortis, c. 16.</note> Now of thoſe who belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the Martyrs were within hearing, it is very likely that ſome called to them with an <hi>Ora pro nobis;</hi> and then no wonder that <hi>Eunapius</hi> charged the <hi>Monks</hi> with raking for dead mens Bones, and making dead men <hi>the Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers of their Prayers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As for the Miracles ſaid to be done in thoſe times, they are urged by the <hi>Romanists</hi> as an invincible argument of Gods approving the honour that was given to the Saints and their Reliques in that Age of the Church. But I wiſh they would attend to what St. <hi>Augustine</hi> ſays, who after a pretty large account of Miracles that were wrought in his time, and ſome too at the <hi>Memories</hi> of Martyrs, plainly ſays, that whether they were wrought by the Miniſtry of <hi>Martyrs</hi> or <hi>Angels</hi> (for that he knew not) they were wrought to give Teſtimony to that <hi>Faith for which the Martyrs died,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aug.</hi> de Civ. Dei, lib. 22. c. 9.</note> and particularly to the Reſurrection of <hi>Christ,</hi> and to our Reſurrection at the laſt day. There is no reaſon to ſuppoſe that every circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the Devotion of <hi>Christians</hi> that received mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous relief, muſt be atteſted by thoſe Miracles which God wrought in farther confirmation of the truth of <hi>Christianity.</hi> God has made uſe even of wicked men for the working of Miracles; and I cannot underſtand why a Miracle may not be wrought in behalf of a <hi>ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere</hi>
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:60697:36"/>man, without approving his <hi>weakneſs,</hi> any more than the others <hi>wickedneſs</hi> is approved by Gods making uſe of him to teſtifie the truth. But I would be content to let them uſe this Argument from Miracles, without contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, if they would extend it no farther than in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of that uſe of Reliques which we yet meet with: In the fourth Age they ranſacked all places for them, and when, as they thought, they got 'em, they put them in fine Linnen, or in curious Boxes and Repoſitories, and laid them up in the Church. But whatever good they expected from theſe Treaſures, they did not yet worſhip them; they did not <hi>Incenſe</hi> them, and expoſe them to receive the <hi>Adorations</hi> of the People. <hi>Vigilan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius,</hi> it ſeems, had asked, with ſome deriſion, <hi>Why dost thou kiſs and adore a little Duſt put up in fine Linnen?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hieron. Adv. Vigil.</hi> Tom. 2. p. 158. <hi>Colon.</hi>
                  </note> To which St. <hi>Hierom,</hi> that went as high as any in the Age for honouring <hi>Reliques,</hi> anſwered, <hi>Who, O thou gid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy-brain'd man, ever adored the Martyrs? Who has taken a man for God?</hi> Indeed St. <hi>Hierom</hi> thought that holy <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques</hi> made the Devils <hi>roar</hi> for very pain; but yet he did not think that they were to be <hi>adored,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ibid.</note> no not the <hi>Martyrs</hi> themſelves, but <hi>God</hi> onely. We could wiſh that all Superſtition were baniſh'd from amongſt <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> but if the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> would be content with ſuch things as St. <hi>Hierom</hi> blames in ſome <hi>ſilly men</hi> and <hi>religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous women,</hi> that <hi>had a Zeal, but not according to knowledge;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ibid.</note> viz. <hi>burning Wax-Candles by day-light in honour of the Martyrs,</hi> we would be content too: for theſe are tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable faults, and ſuch as ſhould not break the Peace, though they were better mended. I would ſay to any contentious man, what St.
<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> 
                  <hi>Hierom</hi> ſaid to <hi>Vigilan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius, What doſt thou loſe by it,</hi> if others are a little fooliſh?</p>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:60697:37"/>
               <p> I confeſs, I ſhould beg of theſe Gentlemen, for the honour of our Religion, and of the teſtimony of Miracles, not to pretend the Miracles of the fourth and fifth <hi>Ages,</hi> as a teſtimony to every <hi>Punctilio</hi> of Honour done in thoſe times to the <hi>Reliques</hi> of the Saints, &amp; to the opinion which ſome conceived of them. And as I ſaid before, it would be more diſcreetly done to let thoſe Miracles go, as St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> did, for a notable confirmation of the Truth of that Religion for which thoſe Martyrs died, by whoſe <hi>dead Bodies</hi> God was pleaſed to do ſome wonderful things. But it is by no means adviſable to ſtretch them in favour of ſome other things; whereof the lighting of Candles for the Martyrs may go for one; and the unwillingneſs of ſome of 'em to build Churches, unleſs they could get <hi>Reliques</hi> to lay there, for another; and the ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering of <hi>Reliques</hi> in little pieces up and down, may paſs for a third; and ſtealing them, for a fourth; which I know not how came to be excuſed at leaſt, as an effect of great and religious Zeal, by ſome men of no mean note. I do not think ſuch things as theſe are very eaſie to be defended; and therefore it were much better that Miracles were not brought in to juſtifie them. But leaſt of all ſhould they be urged in favour of that kind of Worſhip which the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> now gives them; and not onely to the <hi>Bodies, Bones,</hi> or <hi>Aſhes,</hi> but to the <hi>Girdles, Slippers,</hi> and little <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tenſils</hi> of the Saints and Martyrs; which kind of things anciently were not thought of. God wrought Miracles by the hands of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> and the reſt of the Apoſtles, when they were alive. Now if we had their Bones, or ſome pieces of them, and God ſhould be pleaſed to work Miracles by them ſtill; there would be, I am confident, no more reaſon upon this account to give their Reliques any Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Worſhip, now the Apoſtles are dead, than there
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:60697:37"/>was to worſhip the Apoſtles themſelves upon the ſame account, when they were alive. Moreover, God wrought Miracles by the <hi>Brazen Serpent,</hi> and yet when the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple had faln to <hi>burn Incenſe</hi> to it, it was broken to pieces, to his great honour, who oppoſed a Zeal with know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, to the blind Zeal of the People.</p>
               <p>But to deal freely, I am not fully ſatisfied that theſe Miracles by the Bodies of Saints and Martyrs, were half ſo frequent as the noiſe that was made of them in this Age, or in the next, would make us believe. I more than fear that thoſe times were too credulous, or that the Writings of thoſe Fathers have met with more foul play, than has been yet diſcovered, though no ſmall diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coveries of that kind have been made ſince the Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. It is ſome prejudice againſt the credibility of thoſe relations, that in the three firſt Ages, we hear nothing of Miracles wrought by Reliques; which we are not to wonder at, becauſe they lay quiet in their Graves: and the Ancient Church was ſo little concerned in this Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion of <hi>Reliques,</hi> that the Bodies of Martyrs that ſuffered under <hi>Diocleſian</hi> and <hi>Licinius,</hi> that is,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ambroſ. de Exhort. ad Virg. Sozom.</hi> lib. 9. c. 2.</note> at the end of the third, and the beginning of the fourth Age, lay undiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, till Chance or pretended Revelations brought them to light; which is a manifeſt Argument, that the Ancient Church knew nothing of theſe matters, and that they had their beginning in the declenſion of the fourth Age. Again, If the Bodies of <hi>Martyrs</hi> ordinarily diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered themſelves by a gift of Miracles, I wonder how it came to be ſo ordinary a thing to counterfeit Reliques, as it was. For who would dare to put off the Bones of a Malefactor for the Bones of a Martyr, if it was known that true Reliques would diſtinguiſh themſelves from falſe, by true Miracles? And yet St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> himſelf complains of a multitude of <hi>Cheating Fellows</hi> in his time,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:60697:38"/>that <hi>were ſcattered up and down in the habit of Monks,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aug. de Opere. Monach.</hi> c. 28.</note> 
                  <hi>wandering about from Province to Province, ſent no whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, fixed no where, ſtaying no where; ſome of which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed the Trade of ſelling the Bones of Martyrs, if you will believe they were Martyrs Bones.</hi> It would require a Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lume to ſhew the boldneſs that was taken in after-times. God has given to a man but one Head, and one pair of Hands; but the Religion of Reliques has found more than one a piece for many of the Saints and Martyrs: And when they all work Miracles, I muſt needs believe that ſome of 'em are counterfeit Miracles; and if I can yet diſcern no difference, I would know why they ſhould not all go for counterfeit. For when God works Miracles, they are too plain for the moſt part to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied, even by thoſe whoſe intereſt it is to deny them.</p>
               <p>But when I conſider St. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi>'s Judgment in the caſe, I muſt confeſs my ſelf to be under a mighty preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice againſt the credibility of moſt Relations of this ſort that went in that Age. I well remember that he ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where gives expreſs caution againſt liſtning after Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles. But in one place, never to be forgotten, very per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinently to the occaſion of his diſcourſe, he argues in this manner:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Chryſ. Hom.</hi> 6. in 1 Cor. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Becauſe NOW there are no Miracles wrought, do not thou take this for an Argument, that none were wrought THEN</hi> [in the Apoſtles days:] <hi>For then it was profitable that they ſhould be wrought, but now it is profitable they ſhould not be wrought.</hi> But <hi>how,</hi> ſays he, <hi>does it come to paſs, that Signes ſhould be profitable Then, and not ſo Now?</hi> Then he ſhews, that the continuance of Miracles would leſſen the Rewardableneſs of Faith: and <hi>for this reaſon,</hi> ſays he, <hi>they are not now wrought.</hi> And <hi>that this is the Truth, you may ſee by what our Lord ſaid to</hi> Thomas: Bleſſed are they who have not ſeen, and yet believed. <hi>By how much therefore a more convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:60697:38"/>Miracle is ſhewn, by ſo much is the praiſe and reward of Faith leſſened; wherefore, if now alſo Miracles were done, the ſame inconvenience would follow.</hi> But for a farther Anſwer, he adds, that although they had now no Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, yet ſeveral Predictions had been accompliſhed, which was a continued confirmation of the truth of <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity;</hi> and moreover, that the <hi>good Lives and Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples</hi> of <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> were now more neceſſary for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction of Unbelievers, than Miracles: For ſays he, <hi>'Tis the want of Primitive Sanctity, rather than of Miracles, which makes men ſtill remain in their unbelief.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Which Teſtimony of ſo Judicious a man, is a plain Argument that Miracles were at leaſt very rare in his time; and that every Martyrs Bones did not do the ſame Wonders that <hi>Babylas</hi> his Bones were ſaid to have done in <hi>Julian</hi>'s time.</p>
               <p>I may therefore be well excuſed, if I impute that noiſe of Miracles which was ſo loud in this and the next Age, in great part to the credulity of the Age, and to the difficulty of ſtanding againſt that Torrent of Zeal for the honour of the Martyrs, which had carried moſt men already beyond the bounds of Antiquity.</p>
               <p>What ſhall a man make of that Story which St. <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rom</hi> tells of <hi>Hilarion</hi>'s Reliques? How <hi>Heſychius</hi> a holy man ventured his life to ſteal the Body of <hi>Hilarion</hi> the Monk out of the Garden of <hi>Cyprus</hi> where he was bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, to carry it to <hi>Paleſtine;</hi> and how <hi>Conſtantia</hi> took it ſo to heart, that ſhe died upon it. For this Religious Woman <hi>was wont,</hi> it ſeems, <hi>to watch whole days and nights at his Sepulchre, and for the helping of her Prayers, to talk with him as if he was preſent.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hieron. de vitâ Hilario<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis.</hi> Tom. 1. p. 98. <hi>Colon.</hi>
                  </note> I ſhould think it is not much for the Credit of Religion, to repreſent a holy man plundering a Grave, and a holy woman breaking her heart for the loſs of the Body: But if we muſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:60697:39"/>the Story, Miracles followed the ſtoln Body, and yet they tarried in the place from whence it was ſtoln: So that <hi>Heſychius</hi> indeed, and they of <hi>Paleſtine,</hi> were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable gainers; but <hi>Conſtantia</hi> was not ſo great a loſer as ſhe thought. For thus the Relation goes on: <hi>We ſee to this day a wonderful Contention between thoſe of</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtine <hi>and thoſe of</hi> Cyprus, <hi>one pretending to his Body, the other to his Spirit. And yet in both places there are great Miracles done every day, but more in the Garden of</hi> Cyprus, <hi>and that perhaps becauſe he loved that place beſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If Miracles were done in both places, I am pretty well ſatisfied that God did not thereby intend to demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate either the clearneſs of <hi>Heſychius,</hi> or the diſcretion of <hi>Conſtantia</hi> in this buſineſs, nor the violent paſſion of either of them for Reliques. I do not deny but they might both of them be holy Perſons, but it was not for ſuch things as theſe; and if this part of their Story had been omitted, their reputation for Sanctity had loſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing by it. What therefore was it that God teſtified by theſe Miracles? I anſwer with all ſubmiſſion, that he teſtified the truth <hi>of that Religion</hi> in which <hi>Hilarion</hi> died; of that Religion for which the Martyrs died, the moſt holy Religion which was firſt taught by <hi>Jeſus,</hi> then by the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> then by the Primitive Ages of Chriſtianity after the <hi>Apoſtles;</hi> not <hi>of any Sentiments</hi> or <hi>Practices</hi> which neither the Holy <hi>Jeſus</hi> taught, nor his Apoſtles; and which the Primitive Church was a ſtranger to. This I am ſure I have learned from St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> in the place before-mentioned,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aug. de <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nit. Eccleſ.</hi> c. 16.</note> who makes the teſtimony of thoſe Miracles that were wrought at the Memories of the Martyrs, to aim at nothing but the confirmation of the Faith for which they ſuffered. And if I ſhould ſay, that they who can be content with the old Religion, may and ought to be content alſo with the old Miracles, I
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:60697:39"/>ſhould ſay no other thing than what I could juſtifie by his Authority. And which is ſomething more, that we are now to try Doctrines not by new Miracles, but by the Scriptures, which we are ſure deliver to us the Will of God teſtified by Miracles. But if God is pleaſed to add new Miracles out of his abundant goodneſs, I do not doubt but ſuch Miracles are a Confirmation of the old Religion, as St.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>De Civit. De</hi> lib. 22. c. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>Auſtin</hi> tells us thoſe were which God wrought by the Memories of the Martyrs. But thoſe Miracles did by no means <hi>Canonize</hi> the weakneſs of any holy Perſon in the matter of Martyrs or Saints, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques; not the indiſcretion of <hi>Heſychius</hi> or <hi>Conſtantia;</hi> nor did they give any Authority at all to ſuch Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples.</p>
               <p>I ſuppoſe the Gentlemen of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> will grant this, without any trouble; but I queſtion whether they may not be diſpleaſed at the producing of this Story, which without any more ado, looks ſo like a <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr</hi> upon the great Author from whom I had it. But what a hard caſe is ours! Monſieur <hi>de Meaux</hi> and the pretended Catholicks, think to bear us down (who ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour the Reliques of the Saints no otherwiſe than the truly Primitive Church did) by the Authority of the later Fathers that lived towards the end of the fourth Age. It has been often ſhewn, that the Judgment and Practice of that Age in the matter of <hi>Reliques,</hi> is very dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent from what we now ſee in the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> But the Argument is ſtill urged upon us, as if nothing had been ſaid to it. What have we therefore to do, but to ſhew that ſo far as there is any Agreement between the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and that Age of the Church in the uſe of Reliques, they ſhould urge it very modeſtly, and without boaſting. We do <hi>profeſs a Reverence for thoſe excellent men,</hi> as <hi>M. de Meaux</hi> grants;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exp.</hi> p.</note> we acknowledge
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:60697:40"/>their <hi>Sanctity and Learning,</hi> and we praiſe God for the Benefits which the Church hath received by their means. But we do not think their Authority equal to that of the Apoſtles, or of the Fathers of the three firſt Ages. And we are very ſorry that the importunity of our Adverſaries puts us upon a neceſſity of confeſſing that theſe <hi>Great Men</hi> (as <hi>M. de Meaux</hi> deſervedly calls them) did in the heat of their concern for Reliques, ſometimes ſay and do ſuch little things, as plainly ſhewed they were but <hi>Men.</hi> We had been very glad if our Engliſh Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts would not have done this part of the Controverſie into Engliſh, nor obliged us to take off that Vail a little wherewith we have covered the leaſt commendable Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters of theſe excellent men. Nay we have <hi>that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence for their Sanctity and Learning,</hi> that we are ſtill very willing to believe their Writings to have been cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted in thoſe places which afford this kind of Stories. And though St. <hi>Hierom</hi> affirms that he wrote the Life of <hi>Hilarion,</hi> yet I muſt confeſs this is ſo weak a part of it which I have mentioned, that I am ſometimes almoſt perſwaded that ſome body has been making bold to mend him. I am ſure there appears ſuch a Spirit of Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Credulity in theſe paſſages at the end of St. <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larion</hi>'s Life; of Superſtition in the Perſons ſpoken of, and of Credulity in the Relator; that St. <hi>Hierom</hi> is a great deal more beholden to them that cannot be ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied they are his than to thoſe that can.</p>
               <p>But to proceed: I have already obſerved, that the Affection of this Age to the Martyrs, was expreſs'd by a frequent and continual reſort to their <hi>Tombs</hi> or <hi>Memories.</hi> And that when Chriſtians obtained the deliverance or relief which they ſought, it was believed to be in great part the effect of the Martyrs favour with God; which in many Perſons grew into a Perſwaſion that
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:60697:40"/>the <hi>Martyrs</hi> were preſent at their <hi>Memories.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aug.</hi> de Cura pro Mortuis, c. 16.</note> And in this perſwaſion they were confirmed by <hi>Apparitions,</hi> which were at leaſt believed to be ſeen there, ſince it gave occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to ſome queſtions then, and to a great controverſie afterward, whether they were the Souls of the Martyrs, or whether they were Angels that appeared.</p>
               <p>But the great queſtion is, whether in thoſe applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to the <hi>Memories</hi> of the Martyrs, they called upon God onely, or the Martyrs alſo. For here it is that the pretended <hi>Catholicks</hi> muſt find colour of thus much An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity, if any where. For their appeals to the <hi>Apoſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phes</hi> of ſome of the Fathers in their <hi>Panegyrical</hi> Orations upon the <hi>Martyrs,</hi> deſerve no conſideration. If indeed the Faithful were wont to call upon the Martyrs at their <hi>Memories;</hi> this has ſome appearance of an Argument for the pretended <hi>Catholicks.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſhall therefore firſt lay down the Fact, remembring all along, that it is the duty of an honeſt man to deliver things as they appear to him, and not to attempt the defence even of Truth, but onely with ſuch Arguments as he is well ſatisfied of the Truth of, himſelf. But when the Fact is ſtated, I ſhall not envy the beſt advantages that our Adverſaries can make of it.</p>
               <p>That account which St.
<note place="margin">Ad viginti Martyres ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit.</note> 
                  <hi>Austin</hi> gives of the Taylor that had loſt his Cloak, and went to the <hi>Twenty Martyrs</hi> to pray for another, has been often produced as a ſufficient demonſtration that the practiſe of that Age, was to call upon the Martyrs themſelves. But to this it is anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on the other ſide,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Viſum eſt ut iret ad memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riam S.</hi> Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phani, <hi>&amp; illis quantum poſſet oravet, ut Deus illi daret.</hi> De Civ. Dei. l. 22. c. 8.</note> that no more can be certainly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded from hence, than that the Taylor went to the <hi>Memory</hi> of the <hi>Twenty Martyrs,</hi> and there prayed to God: As it is ſaid of others, that they went to the <hi>Memory</hi> of St. <hi>Stephen,</hi> and there prayed that God would give them what they wanted, which is a defenſible interpretation
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:60697:41"/>of ſuch paſſages. For the Application that was made to the Martyrs by going to their <hi>Memories</hi> or <hi>Churches,</hi> and the hope of prevailing by their Interceſſions, did not neceſſarily imply any Invocation of the Martyrs: But the ſuppliant believing them to be preſent at their <hi>Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,</hi> and to obſerve the Prayers that were made to God there, might hope for the benefit of their Interceſſion without ſpeaking to them. As for St. <hi>Austin</hi> himſelf, what his Opinion was concerning the preſence of the Martyrs, I ſhall ſhew in another place.</p>
               <p>But ſome of St. <hi>Chryſostom</hi>'s Homilies are produc'd with no little aſſurance, to ſhew not onely that the Saints were invocated at their <hi>Memories,</hi> but that he approved it too. And indeed St. <hi>Chryſostom</hi>'s Authority in a doubtful matter, would bear a little boaſting. That Age did not afford a man ſuperiour to him in true Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, perhaps not his equal. But then it is but a fair re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, that thoſe Homilies be not obtruded upon us for his, of which it is very doubtful whether they be or not; thoſe for inſtance to the People of <hi>Antioch,</hi> the <hi>Greek</hi> Copies whereof could not be found in any Ancient Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brary. I interpoſe this, not for the ſervice of a Cauſe, but for the honour of St. <hi>Chryſostom,</hi> than whom, no man a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounds more with exhortations to pray to God, upon ſuch conſiderations as theſe.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Chryſ.</hi> in 4. Pſal.</note> 
                  <hi>Thou mayst always and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſantly call upon God, and ſhalt meet with no difficulty; for there is no need of Door-keepers to introduce thee, of Stewards or Procurators, of Guards or Friends; but when thou comest by thy ſelf, then will he most of all hear thee, even when thou beſeechest none elſe. We do not ſo effectually incline him when we intreat by others, as when we do it by our ſelves.</hi> How this can be reconciled with two or three paſſages, (which, if they be his, do manifeſtly imply his approbation of calling upon the Martyrs at their <hi>Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi>)
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:60697:41"/>I cannot for my part underſtand; eſpecially that in the Concluſion of the Homily upon <hi>Bernix,</hi> &amp;c. which I ſhall examine by and by. For to avoid contention a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout a matter not neceſſary to the Cauſe in hand, I will proceed upon that Teſtimony, as if it were St. <hi>Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stom</hi>'s. But whatever St. <hi>Chryſostom</hi>'s Opinion was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the thing it ſel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, I think it cannot reaſonably be denied, that we have his Teſtimony that it was done: For deſcribing the magnificence of the Monuments of the Saints,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Chryſ.</hi> in 2. <hi>Epiſt. ad Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth.</hi> verſ. fin.</note> which were <hi>more ſplendid than the Palaces of Kings, not onely for the greatneſs and beauty of their building, but which was more, for the great reſort of devout people thither;</hi> he goes on thus: <hi>For thither even he that is clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed with Purple, goes to embrace their Monuments, and laying by his statelineſs, he stands intreating the Saints, that they would intercede with God for him; and he that wears a Crown deſires the Patronage of a Tent-Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, and a Fiſherman who died long ſince.</hi> I cannot ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove <hi>Chamier</hi>'s rendring of this place, who ſuppoſes the Emperour is here brought in
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> not <hi>intreating,</hi> but one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>needing</hi> the interceſſion of the Saints. His <hi>Criticiſm</hi> is too ſubtile, and does not well accord with the place. But be that as it will; I muſt confeſs a ſew intimations of the Fact will ſerve to make me conclude, that very many devout people did, beſides their Prayers to God, which they made at the <hi>Memories</hi> of the Martyrs, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat alſo of the Martyrs themſelves the benefit of their Interceſſions to God for them; and that becauſe it was generally believed that they were preſent at their <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mories.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For if ſuch an Opinion ſhould prevail amongſt any conſiderable number of <hi>Chriſtians</hi> any where, that the Souls of Martyrs or other Saints, were to be converſed with in any certain place where the People could come
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:60697:42"/>within their hearing; it is hardly to be imagined that all, or indeed the moſt, ſhould reſtrain themſelves from going thither to deſire their Prayers. And their Guides, who themſelves believed the preſence of the Martyrs, would in all likelihood be more forward to commend them to reprove them for it, unleſs they ſhould be well aware of the ill conſequences it might produce. And therefore I do not wonder that this new conceit of the preſence of the Martyrs at their <hi>Memories,</hi> ſhould carry the Chriſtians of thoſe times thither very frequently, and many of them to deſire the Martyrs to pray for them. This perſwaſion helped forward the Devotion of the Age, and was apparently countenanced by ſome of the Fathers, and it ſhould ſeem was winked at by all, one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſeemed to doubt of it, as we ſhall ſee pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently.</p>
               <p>But St. <hi>Baſil</hi> made no queſtion of it, and therefore ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly approved the practiſe that was grounded upon it. For thus he ſpeaks concerning the <hi>Memory</hi> of the Forty Martyrs.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Baſil.</hi> in 40. <hi>Martyr.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Here,</hi> ſays he, <hi>a Religious woman is found praying for her Children, and deſiring a ſafe return for her Husband, that is abroad, and recovery for her ſick Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band.</hi> And then he adds, <hi>Let your Prayers be made with the Martyrs.</hi> I know this paſſage enforceth no more, than that the Prayers made in thoſe places to God would excite the Martyrs to joyn their Interceſſions with thoſe of the devout Chriſtian. And perhaps St. <hi>Baſil</hi> ſeems to approve this way, more than calling upon the Martyrs themſelves, becauſe he ſays, <hi>Let your Prayers be made with</hi> (not <hi>to) the Martyrs.</hi> But that ſome <hi>Chriſtians</hi> did ſpeak to the Martyrs too, and were not reproved for it, is, I think, very plain from what St. <hi>Baſil</hi> ſays in his Oration upon <hi>Mamas</hi> the Martyr: <hi>You remember the Martyr,</hi> ſays he, <hi>as many of you as have enjoyed him in Dreams; as many of
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:60697:42"/>you as coming to this place, have had his help towards your Prayer; as many of you as having called to him</hi>
                  <note n="(b)" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>Baſil.</hi> Homil. 26. de S. <hi>Mam.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>by name, have found him preſent by his works; as many Travellers as he hath brought home again,</hi> &amp;c. For here I cannot but think that <hi>Mamas</hi> his being <hi>called by name,</hi> ſignifies more than a bare wiſh that he would pray for thoſe that are ſpoken of: Eſpecially conſidering how very natural it was for a belief of the preſence of the Martyrs in ſome places, to breed the cuſtom of addreſſing to them, as a man would do to his Friend that is within the compaſs of hearing. So that I will not go about to put any other conſtruction upon theſe words, than this plain one, that ſome of St. <hi>Baſils</hi> Auditors had called to <hi>Mamas</hi> by name to pray for them, and to aſſiſt them in the procuring of that which they had deſired of God, or were about to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of him.</p>
               <p>And <hi>here</hi> (to uſe the words of the excellent Biſhop <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher) a man may eaſily diſcern the breeding of a Diſeaſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Anſwer to Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge, <hi>p.</hi> 444.</note> 
                  <hi>and as it were the grudgings of that Ague, that brake out after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards into a peſtilential Fever.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I am not inſenſible what colours this plain and honeſt dealing may afford to thoſe of the <hi>Roman</hi> Communion, who do not ſeek for Truth, nor are willing that others ſhould find it. What will they now ſay, but that we begin to confeſs <hi>the eſtabliſhment of the Invocation of Saints in the Fourth Age?</hi> Monſieur <hi>de Meaux</hi> has ſaid it alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy upon leſs occaſion given. But we cannot help it if our Conſciences be miſrepreſented by the <hi>Artifices</hi> of ſome of 'em, and <hi>ſuperficially</hi> looked upon by the reſt. For my own part, I had rather another man ſhould make a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingenuous advantage of my dealing truly in defence of the Truth, than go about to take away from him the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of uſing a pious Fraud, by being guilty of a pious Fraud my ſelf.</p>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:60697:43"/>
               <p> But I will now be bold to ſay, that there is ſo vaſt a difference between the practiſe of ſome Chriſtians in the Fourth Age, who reconciled themſelves to the Prayers of the Martyrs; and between the Invocation of Saints, which is now practiſed and contended for in the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> that the allowance of the former will by no means infer the latter: The fore-mentioned great man has ſhewn the difference in ſeveral particulars well worth every honeſt and prudent mans conſideration, that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires to inform himſelf in this matter.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ibid.</hi> from <hi>p.</hi> 445. to <hi>p.</hi> 457.</note> And to him I ſhall the rather refer the inquiſitive Reader for them; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I will here add two other differences which may of themſelves be ſufficient to ſhew that Monſieur <hi>de Meaux</hi> who ſays we begin to acknowledge that the <hi>Invocation of Saints was eſtabliſhed in the Fourth Age,</hi> would be very much beholden to us, if we ſhould make ſuch an Acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment. For when the Truth comes to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, it amounts to this, and no more: That there were but ſome <hi>beginnings</hi> and <hi>steps</hi> made towards this practiſe, at the latter end of the Fourth Age; and that theſe beginnings were <hi>not then establiſhed</hi> neither.</p>
               <p>For firſt, The inſtances produced to ſhew that devout people were wont to recommend themſelves to the Prayers of the Martyrs, do generally ſhew that they did it at the <hi>reſpective Memories</hi> of thoſe Martyrs, where the Martyrs were believed to be within hearing; which, as I ſhall preſently ſhew, makes a great difference in the caſe. In the mean time, I do not aſſert that it was uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally believed that the Souls of the Martyrs were preſent at their Memories;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aug.</hi> de Curâ pro Mortuis, <hi>c.</hi> 16.</note> for St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> himſelf durſt not affirm it; and though he thought men fared the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for the Prayers of the Martyrs, yet whether they heard thoſe who called to them at their <hi>Memories,</hi> or where-ever elſe they were thought to have appeared,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:60697:43"/>he profeſſed that it paſſed the ſtrength of his Underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding; and this although he allowed greater priviledges to the Martyrs than to other Saints. St. <hi>Austin</hi> could not digeſt an Opinion, that St. <hi>Hierom</hi> indeed made no difficulty to admit, that a Martyr could at the ſame time be in places very diſtant from one another.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hieron.</hi> Adv. Vigilant. Tom. 2. p. 158.</note> He that will conſult St. <hi>Hierom</hi> about his reaſon, may ſind it in a little compaſs; and when he has done, he will be ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied that I do not forbear the mentioning of it for any diſadvantage it would bring to our Cauſe. But that which I at preſent aſſert, is this: That where we find the Faithful deſiring any relief by the Prayers of the Martyrs (whether they prayed to the Martyrs themſelves, or not) we ſtill find them at the proper Memories of thoſe Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs. Thus St. <hi>Baſil,</hi> juſt now quoted: <hi>You that coming to THIS PLACE have found him an helper to your Prayer.</hi> Thus St. <hi>Hierom</hi> alſo repreſents <hi>Conſtantia</hi> at the Tomb of <hi>Hilarion</hi> in the relation already mentioned. And thus St.
<note place="margin">De Civ. D. lib. 22. c. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>Austin</hi> in that famous Chapter of Miracles done by the Memories of Martyrs, where that relief which was ſuppoſed to be obtained by the Twenty Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs, was asked at <hi>their Memory,</hi> and not at St. <hi>Stephen</hi>'s; as St. <hi>Stephen</hi> was ſuppoſed to help thoſe that prayed at his <hi>Memory.</hi> In like manner St. <hi>Chryſostom,</hi> who brings in the Emperour doing <hi>that</hi> honour to the Apoſtles St. <hi>Peter</hi> and St. <hi>Paul,</hi> as to <hi>ſtand intreating their Prayers;</hi> St. <hi>Chryſostom,</hi> I ſay, introduces him to their <hi>Monuments,</hi> or <hi>Memories,</hi> where it was that this honour was done to them. And ſo in the Oration upon <hi>Bernix, Proſdoce</hi> &amp; <hi>Domnina,</hi> we find this exhortation:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Chryſ.</hi> Tom. 5. Hom. 65.</note> 
                  <hi>Let us not onely up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this</hi> [Anniverſary] <hi>Feſtival, but upon other days alſo stick cloſe to them, and intreat them that we may obtain their Patronage.</hi> The ſame obſervation holds, if you go to the Oration upon the <hi>Aegyptian Martyrs,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Id. Tom. 5.</note> and to that
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:60697:44"/>upon <hi>Ignatius;</hi> and indeed it holds ſo generally that it ſhould in reaſon interpret any place that mentions Invo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the Martyrs, where it is not evidently expreſſed that it was done at their Memories;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aug.</hi> de Curâ ubi ſuprà.</note> I mean as I ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, their <hi>reſpective Memories:</hi> Unleſs ſome other place be diſtinctly mentioned, as in that place of St. <hi>Austin</hi> now referred to, where the preſence of the Martyr out of his <hi>Memory</hi> was ſuppoſed to be witneſſed by his <hi>appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> or by his <hi>works.</hi> But this was very extraordinary. The uſual way of ſolliciting the Prayers of a Martyr, was to go to his <hi>Memory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The hardeſt paſſage of all to be accounted for by this Rule, is that of St. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> where he tells the Widows that the <hi>Angels</hi> are to be intreated as well as the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ambroſ.</hi> De Viduis Tom. 4 Col. 505, 506.</note> For though later times have found Reliques of <hi>Angels,</hi> yet they had none then. The whole place is ſomething obſcure, yet I will try to give the beſt account of it that I can. His buſineſs was to perſwade <hi>Widows</hi> to continue unmarried; and he tells them, that by good works and devotion, they would gain the aſſiſtance of the Prayers of the Apoſtles and Martyrs, who would now help thoſe that were not a-kin to them, as effectually as they helped their kinred by their Prayers, when they were upon Earth. And then he has theſe words: I <hi>would to God that there was ſomebody who could ſo readily pray for us; or indeed that very</hi> Peter <hi>who prayed for his Wives Mother, and</hi> Andrew <hi>his Brother; for then they were able to obtain for their kinred, now they can obtain for us and for all.</hi> I can make nothing of this, but that St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> was not ſure St. <hi>Peter</hi> and St. <hi>Andrew</hi> were near enough to have their Prayers deſired, or to be ſpoken to; though the beſt way to engage their Prayers, and to have them near us, was to abound in <hi>Alms</hi> and <hi>Devotion.</hi> But then he adds: <hi>The Angels are to be intreated, who
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:60697:44"/>are given to us to be our Guardians: The Martyrs are to be intreated, whoſe Patronage we ſeem to challenge after a ſort, by having the Pledge of their Bodies. They can pray a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our ſins who have waſhed away their own ſins, if they had any, by their own Bloud.</hi> So that the concluſion ſeems to be this: that although the beſt way of enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging all the Apoſtles and Martyrs, was to abound in Alms and Prayers, yet it would be very good alſo for every one to intreat his Guardian-<hi>Angel</hi> to pray for him, and to deſire the ſame of thoſe <hi>Martyrs</hi> whoſe Reliques were a <hi>Pledge</hi> of their <hi>nearneſs</hi> and <hi>preſence.</hi> If this be not the meaning of St. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> (for I do not love to be confident about the meaning of a place that is not very clear) I ſhall be glad to be better inſtructed. If it be, this is a farther confirmation of what I have obſerved, that the calling upon Martyrs in thoſe days, went by their Reliques and Memories. And by the way, this ſingle inſtance of adviſing to intreat the Angels too, ſeems to proceed upon the common reaſon, <hi>viz.</hi> a ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of the preſence of thoſe Angels, that God had given for our Guard. And it was a current Opinion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt ſome of the Greek Fathers, (whom St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſtudied and imitated very induſtriouſly) that every good man had his Angel; though I am not ſatisfied that any but St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> carried the Opinion to this conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, that men ſhould intreat their Angels to pray for them.</p>
               <p>So that notwithſtanding the ſingularity of St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> in adviſing to call upon Angels, I ſee little reaſon why he ſhould be thought to ſpeak in this faſhion, meerly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he was in compariſon but a Novice in Chriſtianity, when he wrote this Book. Towards the end of his life he ſeemed to be as fond as ever he had been of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques of Martyrs, and very deſirous to make his Prayers
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:60697:45"/>over them,
<note place="margin">Paulinus in vitâ Ambroſ. Paris. Amb.</note> if <hi>Paulinus</hi> may be believed; who obſerved, that <hi>if the Holy Prieſt went to pray in a place at which he had never been ſeen to pray before, this was a token that he knew by Revelation the Body of ſome Martyr to lie hid thereabouts.</hi> So that although the Bodies he then ſpeaks of were ſoon tranſlated into the Church of the Apoſtles, yet St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> would looſe no time, but went forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with to ſay his <hi>Prayers to God</hi> at the places where they lay buried, and probably enough to <hi>ſpeak to them too;</hi> believing that they were there near enough to obſerve and hear him, and that they would aſſiſt him with their Prayers.</p>
               <p>Thus <hi>Sozomen</hi> tells us, that <hi>Theodoſius</hi> going out of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> in his Expedition againſt <hi>Eugenius,</hi> and coming to the ſeventh mile, there
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>prayed to God,</hi> and likewiſe
<note n="†" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Sozom.</hi> lib. 7. c. 24.</note> 
                  <hi>called to John the Baptiſt to help him.</hi> I ſhall not need to inſiſt upon the difference of Expreſſion, <hi>praying to God,</hi> and <hi>calling</hi> to the Saint, though ſeveral inſtances might be produced in favour of ſuch an obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation. For here alſo we find that the place where the Emperour <hi>prayed</hi> to <hi>God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ibid.</hi> c. 21.</note> and withal <hi>called</hi> upon the <hi>Baptiſt,</hi> was no other than that Church which he had built for a <hi>Memory</hi> of St. <hi>John</hi> Baptiſt. For it ſeems, certain Monks of the <hi>Macedonian</hi> Hereſie were ſaid to have found the Head of the <hi>Baptiſt</hi> at <hi>Hieruſalem;</hi> which after ſeveral removes, was at laſt brought by <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>odoſius</hi> to <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> in the Suburbs whereof he <hi>bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried</hi> it, and <hi>erected a ſtately Church over it.</hi> So that here the Reliques of the Martyr were a Pledge of his Preſence and Patronage; and here it was that <hi>Theodoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> did not onely pray to God, but called to the Saint for his Aſſiſtance too.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ruffin.</hi> Hiſt. lib. 2. c. 33.</note> 
                  <hi>Ruffinus</hi> indeed tells us, that he ſought help by the interceſſion of other Saints; but where was it? Not here at St. <hi>John</hi> Baptiſt's Memory;
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:60697:45"/>but where the <hi>Reliques of the Apoſtles and Martyrs were kept,</hi> that is in other <hi>Memories.</hi> But when the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour was come into <hi>Italy,</hi> and had the Enemy before him in the Field; though we find that he prayed, yet there is not the leaſt intimation of calling upon the <hi>Baptiſt,</hi> or upon any other Saint there. It is onely ſaid,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sozom.</hi> lib. 7. c. 24.</note> that <hi>proſtituting himſelf upon the ground, he prayed with tears, and God preſently heard his Prayers.</hi> But though the Victory was without all queſtion to be <hi>aſcribed to God,</hi> yet <hi>Sozomen</hi> relates a ſtrange ſtory, which he had taken, as it ſeems, upon common report, how the Devil aſcribed it to <hi>John the Bapiſt.</hi> For the ſame day that the Battel was fought, a man poſſeſſed being in the Church of St. <hi>John Baptiſt,</hi> was heaved up very high from the ground, and the Devil that was in him,
<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> 
                  <hi>railed at the Baptiſt, and reproached him for having loſt his head;</hi> but yet could not forbear confeſſing to him in this manner: <hi>Thou overcomeſt me, and defeateſt my Army.</hi> I confeſs I am apt to ſuſpect foul play in this prank of the Devil, if it were true; and do believe, that God ought to have had the Glory, not a whit the leſs for the Devils giving it to the Saint. But ſuch kind of reports were made uſe of to confirm People in an opinion of the preſence of the Martyrs at their Memories, (for the Devil's ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt here, was his acknowledgment of it) and in the practice of making addreſſes to them there upon that account.</p>
               <p>Nothing yet appears to the contrary, but that they who thought the Martyrs heard when they were ſpoken to, believed their preſence to be limited to ſome certain places, in the compaſs of which they were within hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. But I am not ſo vain as to undertake that there were none in thoſe days who called upon the Martyrs in all places indifferently: For while the Great men of
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:60697:46"/>that Age ſeemed to give a full ſcope to that ſtrain of zeal towards the Martyrs which was now going forward, it is to be feared rather, (though no ſuch thing appears) that ſome of the people made no difference between cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling upon their Martyrs at their <hi>Memories,</hi> or any where elſe. And ſo it certainly was when one of thoſe Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons was written that are ſafely attributed to St.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Serm. de Feſt. Nazarii &amp; Celſi.</hi> Tom 4.</note> 
                  <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But 'tis enough for my preſent purpoſe, that the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom of calling upon the Martyrs at their reſpective Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mories, was as yet very notorious. And this indeed was the ground of that Scoff of <hi>Vigilantius,</hi> for which St.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hierom.</hi> Adv. <hi>Vigil. ubi ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pra.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Hierom</hi> chaſtiſes him ſo ſeverely: <hi>What,</hi> ſays he, <hi>are the Souls of the Martyrs therefore ſo fond of their own Aſhes? do they hover about them, and are always preſent with them, leſt perhaps if any one comes to pray, they ſhould be abſent, and incapable of hearing him?</hi> To the matter of which Queſtion, St. <hi>Hierom</hi> was almoſt ſilent; but he laſhes him for abuſing and laughing at the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques of the Martyrs. The truth is, <hi>Vigilantius</hi> had hit that Popular Opinion, that the Martyrs were very much preſent with their Reliques, and conſequently, that the beſt way to be ſure of them, was to go to the Churches where their Reliques were, unleſs (which happened very ſeldom) they ſhould diſcover a particular affection to ſome other place, as St. <hi>Hilarion</hi> did to the Garden of <hi>Cyprus,</hi> after his Reliques were ſtoln out of it.</p>
               <p>Now therefore as the firſt Addreſſes that were made to the Martyrs had not the nature of <hi>Prayer</hi> or <hi>Religious Invocation</hi> in any other reſpect, ſo neither in this, that they aſcribed <hi>Omnipreſence</hi> to the Saints or Martyrs. For not onely the <hi>Belief</hi> of that Age, but the <hi>Practice</hi> of it too, in ſeeking the Interceſſion of the Saints, limited their preſence to ſome <hi>determinate places,</hi> and generally to
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:60697:46"/>their <hi>reſpective Memories.</hi> They that called upon the Saints at all, did not indifferently call upon them in any place, but (if we may gather the general practice from ſuch particular inſtances as we have) they invocated them in ſome certain place onely, where they were thought to be within hearing. Nor can I find that they thought it reaſonable to ſpeak ſo much as to one Saint, at the <hi>Memory</hi> of another; but rather to every Saint a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> his own.</p>
               <p>Which makes the Addreſſes of thoſe times to the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs, very different from the Invocation of Saints in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> which hath let her Children looſe to call upon every Saint in every place, as occaſion re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires; and has furniſhed them with <hi>Litanies</hi> of Suppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation to all the Saints, to be uſed in all places of the World.</p>
               <p>He that cannot ſee a wide difference between theſe two things, can ſee nothing. The firſt practice of all, ſetting aſide the ill conſequences of it, was to ſay the worſt of it, but a harmleſs Superſtition; that is, when as yet the <hi>Reliques</hi> of the Martyrs were intire, and there was but one <hi>Memory</hi> to one. The next ſtep indeed was ſomething dangerous, which began alſo in this Age, and that was allowing ſome of them ſeveral Memories in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant places, at every one of which, I believe they were ſpoken to by ſome or other; though it was yet pretty well, that they confined them all within ſome bounds. But the laſt Practice is an intolerable Affront to the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Majeſty, becauſe it does in effect aſcribe <hi>Omnipre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence</hi> to a Creature. The progreſs of the miſchief from ſo ſmall a beginning, to ſo ſtrange a concluſion, was plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this: By diſperſing the Reliques of the ſame Martyrs into two or more, and at length into many places, their <hi>Memories</hi> were by degrees ſtrangely multiplied; and
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:60697:47"/>that to ſpeak the Truth,
<note place="margin">Theod. <hi>de Cur. Graec.</hi> Affl. l. 8. <hi>de</hi> Mart.</note> not inconſiderably in the next Age, as appears by <hi>Theodoret;</hi> and ſo by degrees they were allowed a greater; and by the help of new Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques (when the old ones would bear dividing no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger) ſtill a greater compaſs of preſence; till at laſt Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition and worldly Policy together, would not allow any bounds at all to be ſet to their preſence, but would have them <hi>called upon</hi> no leſs than God in all places whatſoever.</p>
               <p>This account of the latter Practices of the fourth Age in this matter, and of the grounds of their Practice, may perhaps deſerve to be added to a great many others, whereby the difference of the Addreſſes to the Martyrs in that Age, from the <hi>Roman</hi> Invocation of Saints, has been ſhewn. I ſhall ſay no more of it, than that it may appear fair and reaſonable to any man that ſhall take the pains to compare one thing with another. At leaſt, it deſerves ſome conſideration, becauſe if the Addreſſes that were made in that Age to the Martyrs, were limited to ſome certain places; it will deſtroy an Appeal to that Age for an Invocation which is unlimited, and aſcribes Omnipreſence to the Saints. And therefore if in aſſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this difference, I have proceeded upon a miſtake of the Practice of that Age, the Gentlemen of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> are concerned to ſhew it. And when they do, it will be my part to ſhew that I am not fond of a <hi>Notion,</hi> but can with more eaſe reject it, when it appears to be falſe, than I entertained it while it ſeemed to be true.</p>
               <p>But then 2. As the Addreſſes of the Fourth Age to the Saints were not properly Religious Invocations, ſo nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther were they <hi>eſtabliſhed</hi> in the Church. There was no publick Rule or Order for them, but they were wholly the effects of a private and voluntary Zeal, encouraged by ſome of the Guides of the Church, and perhaps con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nived
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:60697:47"/>at by all. They were, I ſay, the actions of ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſingle <hi>Chriſtians</hi> in behalf of themſelves or their near Relations, but no part of the eſtabliſhed Service of the Church. The <hi>Liturgies</hi> were every where ſtill the ſame, and none but God was called upon in the Service per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed at the Religious Aſſemblies of the Church. If the pretended Catholicks could ſhew a Change in the Service of the Church about this time, favouring the Invocation of Saints, that indeed were ſomething. But then they muſt not refer us to the ſhameful Interpola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi>'s, and other ancient Liturgies. It were an eaſie matter to be very large upon this Head, but for a reaſon I ſhall mention preſently, we will for the preſent go no farther than to St. <hi>Auſtin.</hi> For if his Authority be of any weight with them, they will ſee that whatever was done in the way of private Worſhip by ſingle Perſons, there was no change of the Service of the Church in this reſpect, but that God onely was invo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated in the ſtated Aſſemblies of the Faithful. Let us therefore hear what St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſays, <hi>The Gentiles,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>have built Temples, raiſed Altars, and ordained Prieſts,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>De Civit. Dei</hi> lib. 22. c. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>and offered Sacrifices to their Gods. But we do not erect Temples to our Martyrs, as if they were Gods, but Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries as to dead men, whoſe Spirits live with God. Nor do we erect Altars upon which to ſacrifice to Martyrs, but to one God onely do we offer, the God of Martyrs, and our God; at which Sacrifice, as men of God who in confeſſing him have overcome the World, they are named in their place and order, but they are not invocated by the Priest who ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> plainly ſpeaks of the publick Service of the Church at the Aſſemblies of the Faithful, in which, if we will take his word, no Addreſſes were made, but to God onely. And he expreſly ſays that the Prieſt who
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:60697:48"/>adminiſtred the Service, did not invocate the Martyrs, but named them <hi>in order,</hi> as men that had overcome the World, that is, gave Thanks and Prayers to God for them. And here I am much miſtaken, or elſe there is an obſervable difference intimated between the volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Addreſſes of ſingle Perſons to the Martyrs at their <hi>Memories,</hi> and between the mention that was made of the Martyrs when the Faithful aſſembled for the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Service of God at the ſame <hi>Memories:</hi> For when in voluntary and private Devotion, the Saints were ſpoken to, it was ſtill at their reſpective <hi>Memories;</hi> but in the Aſſemblies of the Church for Divine Service, they were indifferently mentioned in their place and order, at all the Memories of the Martyrs, but not invocated. But that which I chiefly obſerve, is this: That neither was the Martyr, whoſe <hi>Memory</hi> was the place of God's publick Service, invocated in the Prayers of the Church; ſo that even the Addreſſes of that Age to a <hi>Martyr</hi> at his <hi>own Memory,</hi> were not eſtabliſhed by the Order and Service of the Church, but left to the voluntary Zeal of ſingle Perſons.</p>
               <p>And therefore thoſe Paſſages of this Father referred to by <hi>M. de Meaux,</hi> make nothing for Invocation of Saints. St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> it ſeems, (though it was a ſingular Opinion of his) thought <hi>it an</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">De Verb. Apoſt. Serm. 17.</note> 
                  <hi>injury to a Martyr to pray for him, by whoſe Prayers we our ſelves are to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended;</hi> and therefore the Martyrs were not mentioned in that place of the Service, where <hi>other dead Perſons were commemorated,</hi> viz. thoſe for whom Prayer was made. And ſays he,
<note n="†" place="margin">Tractat. in <hi>Joh.</hi> 84.</note> 
                  <hi>At the Holy Table we do not ſo commemorate them as we do others that reſt in peace,</hi> viz. as thoſe <hi>for whom we pray; but rather</hi> as thoſe <hi>that pray for us, that we may tread in their ſteps.</hi> Now though St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> was one of thoſe that doubted whether the
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:60697:48"/>Petitions of the Faithful arrived to the knowledge of the Martyrs, yet he doubted not that the Martyrs prayed for the Faithful, which is all that can be proved from theſe places. But what is this to the Invocation of them, which St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> alſo expreſly denies, in ſaying that <hi>they are not invocated by the Prieſt who Sacrifices?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And here we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ſt remember what the Ancient Fathers meant by the <hi>Chriſtian Sacrifice.</hi> Not only the Oblation of Bread and Wine brought by all the People, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented at the Holy Table, with the Prayers of the Prieſt, nor onely the Conſecration of thoſe Elements afterwards to be the Memorials of Chriſts Body and Blood, which they firſt laid before God, and then diſtributed to the Faithful; I ſay, we muſt remember that they did not onely mean theſe <hi>viſible</hi> Sacrifices, but likewiſe all the Prayers, Praiſes, and Thankſgivings of the Church, which were <hi>Vocal</hi> Sacrifices, together with <hi>Contrition of Heart,</hi> and all <hi>pious Affections</hi> anſwerable to the Outward Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices; by <hi>which</hi> the Faithful offer'd up
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Aug.</hi> de Civ. lib. 10. c. 6.</note> themſelves a Sacrifice to God. This was that <hi>Reaſonable Service,</hi> and <hi>unbloudy Sacrifice,</hi> which the Prieſt in behalf of all the People, ſolemnly offered up to God. So that St. <hi>Auſtin</hi>'s meaning is this: That the Faithful being aſſembled at the Memories of the Martyrs for Divine Service, the Martyrs are not Invocated by the Prieſt in any part of the Adminiſtration. And therefore the diſtinction of Sacrificial and Extraſacriſicial Prayers will not avoid this Teſtimony, ſince the Prayers of the Faithful at their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Aſſemblies, were all <hi>Sacrificial</hi> Prayers, as being part of the <hi>Chriſtian Sacrifice.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And St. <hi>Austin,</hi> whoſe Teſtimony this is, did in this notion of Sacrifice, clearly follow the Doctrine of the more Ancient Fathers: <hi>Let us obſerve,</hi> ſaith he,
<note place="margin">Ibid. c. 5</note> 
                  <hi>that where God ſaid he would not have Sacrifice, there it is ſhewn
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:60697:49"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="91" facs="tcp:60697:49"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="92" facs="tcp:60697:50"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="93" facs="tcp:60697:50"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="94" facs="tcp:60697:51"/>that he will have Sacrifice. He willeth not the Sacrifice of a ſlain Beaſt, but he will have the Sacrifice of a contrite Heart.</hi> And afterwards he addeth theſe inſtances, as the Ancients had done before him. The <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> ſaith, <hi>Offer unto God the ſacrifice of praiſe, and pay thy vows to the Moſt High, and call upon me in the day of tribulation, and I will deliver thee, and thou ſhalt gl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>fie me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>'Tis true, that he ſometimes diſtinguiſheth the <hi>viſible Oblations</hi> of the Church, from Prayers and Praiſes; as where he argues,
<note place="margin">Ibid. c. 19.</note> that the <hi>viſible Sacrifices</hi> are to be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered up to God onely; whoſe <hi>viſible Sacrifice</hi> we our ſelves are in our hearts; as in <hi>vocal Prayer</hi> and <hi>Praiſe</hi> we pray to God, and praiſe him onely, to whom we of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the devotion of the Heart. But though in that place he doth not call Prayers and Praiſes, <hi>Sacrifices,</hi> as he doth elſewhere very frequently; yet even there he ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth it for granted, that when the Faithful were aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled for praying to God and praiſing him, they addreſſed themſelves to none but to Him.</p>
               <p>It is ſo plain even from this Father, that the Invocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Martyrs and Saints, was no part of the Service of the Church, that I have thought ſit to inſiſt onely upon his Teſtimony; eſpecially ſince Monſieur <hi>de Meaux</hi> has been pleaſed to bring in the words of the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> explaining their practiſe in Invocating the Saints: <hi>Becauſe,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>the Council doth almoſt make uſe of the very words of this Holy Biſhop.</hi> Let us firſt hear the words of the Council: <hi>The Church does not offer Sacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to the Saints, but to God alone, who has Crowned them: The Prieſt alſo does not addreſs himſelf to St.</hi> Peter <hi>and St.</hi> Paul, <hi>ſaying, I offer up to you this Sacrifice; but rendring thanks to God for their Victories, he demands THEIR ASSISTANCE, to the end that thoſe whoſe Memory me celebrate upon Earth, would vouchſafe to pray for us in
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:60697:51"/>Heaven.</hi> Now let us hear the words of St. <hi>Austin,</hi> in that place to which Monſieur <hi>de Meaux</hi> refers. <hi>But we do not appoint Temples, Prieſthoods, Holy Rites, and Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices to the Martyrs, becauſe not They, but their God is our God. Indeed, we honour the Memories of the Martyrs as of holy men,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>But who of the Faithful ever heard the Prieſt, ſtanding at the Altar,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ibid. lib. 8. c. 27.</note> 
                  <hi>though erected for the Honour and Worſhip of God, over the holy Body of a Martyr, to ſay in the Prayers, I offer Sacrifice to thee,</hi> O Peter, <hi>or</hi> Paul, <hi>or</hi> Cyprian; <hi>when at their Memories 'tis offered to God, who made them both Men and Martyrs, and aſſociated them to the Angels in heavenly glory; that by this ſolemnity we may give thanks to the True God for their Victories, and that we by renewing in our ſelves the remembrance of them, may be excited by imitating them to ſtrive for ſuch Crowns and Palms as they have obtained</hi>
                  <note n="†" place="margin">Eodem in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocato in Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xilium.</note> 
                  <hi>THE SAME True God BEING INVOCATED FOR O<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>R ASSISTANCE.</hi> It ſeems there is <hi>almost</hi> no difference made by putting the <hi>Saints</hi> inſtead of <hi>God.</hi> Let Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur <hi>de Meaux</hi> lay his hand upon his Heart, and tell us honeſtly for once, whether <hi>Eodem invocato in Auxilium,</hi> do not refer to the True God ſpoken of before, and not to the Saints? And if ſo, what there is in this paſſage of the <hi>Holy Biſhop,</hi> that makes for the Invocation of Saints?</p>
               <p>And now Monſieur <hi>de Meaux</hi> may go on as long as he thinks fit to make Triumphs,
<note place="margin">Paſtoral Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <hi>p.</hi> 29.</note> upon our <hi>Acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that during the Fourth Century, the Church deſired the Prayers of Martyrs, and honoured Reliques.</hi> For he goes on in this ſtrain, in his late <hi>Paſtoral Letter,</hi> where he declaims ſo Tragically againſt thoſe that (if you will believe him) charge Idolatry upon the <hi>Illuſtrious Fourth Age; yea that very Age wherein the Prophecies of the Kingdom of Jeſus Chriſt were accompliſhed more manifeſtly
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:60697:52"/>than ever; when the Kings of the Earth till then Perſecutors of the Name of Jeſus, became according to the Ancient Oracles, his Adorers.</hi> My Lord the Biſhop of <hi>Meaux</hi> knew when it was convenient to uſe the ſtile of a perfect Gentleman.
<note place="margin">p. 30.</note> But ſince he wrote his Expoſition, the <hi>Caſe</hi> of ſome of his Countrey-men is ſomething altered, though the <hi>Cauſe</hi> be the ſame. <hi>Now</hi> the <hi>Blaſphemies</hi> of the Proteſtants put him into ſits of Amazement,
<note place="margin">p. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> and he cannot tell <hi>what Horrour they are worthy of.</hi> But to do him right, he keeps true to one old principle, that will I believe be dear to him as long as he lives:
<note place="margin">p. 16.</note> 
                  <hi>Once more, my Breth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren, let us not diſpute, let us not run into Controverſie.</hi> No, by no means; for it is much eaſier to <hi>declaim,</hi> than to <hi>diſpute,</hi> to take things for granted, than to prove them; and to make <hi>general</hi> ſlouriſhes, than to enter into exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of <hi>particulars.</hi> What can be more eaſie than to exclaim in this manner? <hi>The</hi> Ambroſes, <hi>the</hi> Auguſtines, <hi>the</hi> Hieroms,
<note place="margin">p. 30.</note> 
                  <hi>the</hi> Gregories <hi>of</hi> Nazianzene, <hi>the</hi> Baſilius<hi>'s, and the</hi> Chryſoſtomes, <hi>whom all Chriſtians have reſpected even till now as the Doctors of Truth!</hi> But hold a little; if great Names will do the buſineſs, let us ſee what we can do in this kind: <q>
                     <hi>Can you endure, my Brethren,</hi> thoſe who have forſaken the <hi>Ireneus</hi>'s, the <hi>Juſtin-Martyrs,</hi> the <hi>Clemens</hi>'s of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> the <hi>Tertullians,</hi> the <hi>Origens,</hi> the <hi>Cyprians,</hi> the <hi>Athanaſius</hi>'s, <hi>whom all Chriſtians do pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend even now to reſpect as Doctors of Truth?</hi> Thoſe, <hi>my Brethren,</hi> that were more Ancient than the <hi>Ambroſes,</hi> &amp;c. and moſt of whom laid down their lives in a Glorious Martyrdom, which none of the other did? It is true, <hi>Brethren,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">p. 29.</note> that ſome part of <hi>the Prophecies</hi> was fulfilled, when, the Empire took the Church into its protection; but we do not find it was foretold alſo, that the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians of that Age would be wiſer or better than their Forefathers.
<note place="margin">p. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> Does not Monſieur <hi>de Meaux</hi> tell us, <hi>that
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:60697:52"/>Antichriſt muſt come according to the Predictions of the Apoſtles.</hi> But when that happens, the times are not to be much the better for it. It was the admirable good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of God, to Crown the <hi>Church</hi> at laſt with Peace and Glory. But do not think the Authority of that Age is to be regarded the more, becauſe it was <hi>Illuſtrious</hi> for the <hi>Wealth</hi> and <hi>Splendor</hi> of this World, leaſt by the ſame reaſon you ſhould undervalue the Authority of the more Ancient Ages, which were <hi>Illuſtrious</hi> for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but <hi>Truth,</hi> and <hi>Godlineſs,</hi> and <hi>Martyrdom;</hi> which if you ſhould do, my Brethren, might we not well cry out, <hi>Oh prodigy, unheard of amongst Christians!</hi> that we ſhould begin to think it a better mark of a <hi>pure</hi> Church, to have it in its power to perſecute others, than to endure perſecution her ſelf after the example of <hi>Christ</hi> and his <hi>Apostles.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>It is an eaſie matter to requite a Declamation. But would not the Biſhop of <hi>Meaux</hi> ſay to this, that the <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neus</hi>'s, &amp;c. do not condemn what is now practiſed in the Church of <hi>Rome?</hi> So do we ſay that we are far from charging the <hi>Ambroſes,</hi> &amp;c. with Idolatry; and that the Doctrines and Practiſes of that Age, with reſpect to the points that we are upon, are ſo vaſtly different from what we now ſee in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> that if the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> be Idolatrous, it does by no means fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, that the Fourth Age was ſo. So that we muſt come to <hi>diſputing</hi> at laſt, whether we will or not, if we talk of theſe queſtions to any purpoſe.</p>
               <p>I have ſhewn the firſt ſteps that were made towards the <hi>Invocation of Saints,</hi> which I confeſs is an Innovation main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> that of all the reſt bids the faireſt for Antiquity: Becauſe there was a certain Addreſs to Martyrs uſed by many <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> and commended by ſome of the Fathers towards the latter end of the Fourth
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:60697:53"/>Age, which looks ſomething like it, till you come near to examine the matter throughly. But then you may diſcern ſo conſiderable a difference, that 'tis a vain thing to pretend that the <hi>Invocation of Saints,</hi> as now practiſed in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> was as Ancient as the Concluſion of the Fourth Age. All that we need to grant, is this: That thoſe <hi>beginnings</hi> are ſo Ancient, which firſt did give occaſion to it, and which with the help of <hi>Ignorance</hi> and <hi>Superſtition</hi> did at length bring it into the Church.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
               <head>§ 10.</head>
               <p>Hitherto the Honour done to the Martyrs was that of Founding Churches upon their <hi>Reliques,</hi> and frequenting them both for the publick Service of God, and for pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Devotions, in which the Martyrs themſelves were ſometimes called upon, as if they were preſent at their <hi>Memories.</hi> But this was done before their Images came to be ſet up in the Church, ſo much as for Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and long before they were thought of for Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip. We have already noted the Act of <hi>Epiphanius,</hi> in tearing the Picture of <hi>Christ,</hi> or ſome other Saint, (for he knew not well what it was) which he found upon a <hi>Veil:</hi> An act of Indignation ſo much the more remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, becauſe the Church where it was done was in the Dioceſs of <hi>John</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hieron.</hi> Tom. 2. Ep. 60. v. fin.</note> to whom therefore <hi>Epiphanius</hi> thought fit to give an account of it in that E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle which is to be ſeen in St. <hi>Hierom</hi>'s Works: And the reaſon he gives for what he did, is as remarkable as the Action was. <hi>When I ſaw this in a Church of Christ, that the Picture of a man ſhould be hanged up there, against the Authority of the Scriptures, I tare it,</hi> &amp;c. And again, <hi>I intreat thee to command the Presbyters of that place to provide for the future, that ſuch Veils being contrary to
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:60697:53"/>what our Religion allows, may not be hanged up in the Church of Christ.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But as for the Images of Martyrs and Saints, why ſhould I go about to prove that they were not yet brought into Churches, when the pretended <hi>Catholicks</hi> are fain to give reaſons why they were hardly to be met with amongſt Chriſtians even out of Churches. <hi>Petavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> excuſeth the matter thus: <hi>The Images of Christ and the Saints were not uſed, lest they ſhould be taken by the rude and unskilful people, for Idols, to which they ſhad been accustomed.</hi> And afterward:
<note place="margin">Petav. <hi>Dogm. Theol.</hi> Tom. 4. part. 2. c. 13. p. 582, 583.</note> 
                  <hi>Images are not evil of themſelves, nor forbidden by any Law of God; nevertheleſs, that no ſhadow of Superstition and Idolatry, might give of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence to the tender, and, as I may ſay, the unſetled minds of Christians, and that the Gentiles might not object to thoſe of our Religion who abhorred Idols, and diſſwaded men from them, that themſelves alſo had certain Images of their own; is likely they were but ſparingly uſed for about the first Four Ages, all which time the abominable Worſhip of Devils in Idols, together with a most cruel vexation of the Christian name, went on. At length the Fifth Age being come, after that the Church had gained her freedom, and began boldly to stretch forth her arms, Images began to appear in most places, and were ſhewn in Temples and Oratories; whereas hitherto though they had been in ſome uſe, yet they were not to be ſeen ſo promiſcuouſly and frequently.</hi> In good time! But if ſuch a man as <hi>Petavius</hi> could have ſhewn <hi>any uſe</hi> of Images all this while that any Art could draw to his purpoſe, he had not ſerved the Cauſe with this miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble account of the late ſetting up of Images. With the like to which <hi>Salmeron</hi> ſatisfied himſelf, as to the ſilence of the Scriptures about the Worſhip of Saints, as we have already ſeen. Now to make this appear <hi>likely,</hi> he inſiſts upon it, that the Ancients diſputed againſt the Temples
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:60697:54"/>and Altars of the <hi>Heathens,</hi> though when peace and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty was given to the Church, the <hi>Christians</hi> had magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficent Churches and Altars of their own. But nothing can be more vain, for from the firſt the Church had its Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars or holy Tables, and its holy Places too, ſuch as the times would permit. And therefore this Inſtance doth not reach to the Caſe of Images which they had not. But where the ſtate of the Controverſie lay between the Chriſtians and the Heathens about Temples and Altars, and what was the difference between the one and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, is too long to inſert here; and therefore I refer the Reader to Mr. <hi>Mede</hi>'s Diſcourſe concerning Churches, <hi>Par.</hi> 1. <hi>Book</hi> 2. where 'tis handled with exquiſite di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence.</p>
               <p>But if <hi>Petavius</hi> his reaſon hath any probability, why were not Images brought in preſently upon <hi>Constantine</hi>'s coming to the Empire, at leaſt after the death of <hi>Julian?</hi> For then the Church enjoy'd <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Power;</hi> unleſs it were to be ſaid, that by ſtepping boldly into that practiſe (aſſoon as they had gained power) which they had utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly condemned in their diſtreſs they knew that they ſhould bring the reproach of inſincerity upon their Profeſſion, and that therefore it was more adviſable to ſtep into it by degrees. But he that can believe this of the Ancient Church, muſt not pretend any great Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence for it.</p>
               <p>But whereas <hi>Petavius</hi> thought this to be the <hi>likely</hi> reaſon, why we hear not of Images ſo long together, <hi>viz.</hi> that it would furniſh the Heathens with objections. I ſhall not fear to oppoſe this Conjecture with another, and to ſay, that it is more <hi>likely</hi> and <hi>credible,</hi> that if the Antient Fathers had thought it lawful to bow down to <hi>Images,</hi> and to <hi>Worſhip</hi> them, they would have brought this practiſe in with one conſent; and that becauſe the
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:60697:54"/>
                  <hi>Gentiles</hi> had been accuſtomed to the worſhipping of Images: For it is incomparably more eaſie to bring men from worſhipping ſome Images to worſhip others, (as the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> knew by experience) than from worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping Images, to worſhip none at all. Nay, it is yet more likely that Images were brought into ſeveral Churches in the fifth Age, in compliance with the incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations of many of the <hi>Gentiles;</hi> who, now the Church ſhined with the Glory of the World, thronged into it, before they had worn off their Superſtition and fondneſs of Images; and that the reaſon why it was done no ſooner, was this: that the Zeal of the Ancient Church againſt <hi>Images</hi> being yet freſh in the minds of men, muſt needs hinder their coming into any uſe immediately, and leave it to be a work of ſome time. And it is not <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely</hi> that <hi>Petavius</hi> himſelf was well aware of theſe things, for otherwiſe he was not likely to confeſs, that in <hi>this Controverſie about Images, we are not to have regard to the Examples and Orders of the more ancient Church, but rather of latter times;</hi> which is in more civil terms to confeſs it was an <hi>Innovation:</hi> for ſurely this learned <hi>Jeſuit</hi> knew better, than to ſay that in a Controverſie about the <hi>Antiquity of worſhipping Images,</hi> we ought <hi>ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to regard latter times than the Ancient Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But they that will find Church-Authority for Image-Worſhip, muſt go down yet lower, even beyond the fifth, ſixth, and ſeventh Ages of the Church. Pictures were in the fifth Age brought into divers Churches, for <hi>Ornament</hi> and <hi>Inſtruction.</hi> The Hiſtories of the <hi>Old</hi> and <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> and at length the Paſſions of <hi>Martyrs,</hi> and ſtories of <hi>Saints,</hi> were to be ſeen upon the Walls of Churches. Indeed when the ſeventh Age was now coming in, we find the People of <hi>Marſeilles</hi> began to worſhip Images; which <hi>Serenus</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Greg.</hi> lib. 9. Ep. 9. ad <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renum.</hi>
                  </note> their Biſhop diſcern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:60697:55"/>broke 'em down. Which breaking of them, <hi>Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> the <hi>Great</hi> diſallowed, becauſe he thought <hi>Images</hi> were inſtead of <hi>Books</hi> to them that could not read; but the worſhipping of them he diſallowed as much as <hi>Serenus.</hi> It is likely enough that ſome unwarrantable regard to Images, began about the ſame time to obtain in other places. For in the ſeventh Age there were warm Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies about it, which grew to ſuch a heat in the Reign of <hi>Leo Iſaurus,</hi> that he commanded the Images to be broken down. But Superſtition had gotten ſuch an head, that this would not do; but his Son <hi>Conſtantine</hi> was forced to call together a Council, (which conſiſted of 338 Biſhops) to put an end to thoſe Troubles, if it might be done. And they did their parts effectually: for they did not onely decree againſt the <hi>worſhipping</hi> of Images, but the <hi>retaining</hi> of them. Now thirty years after this, towards the end of the <hi>Eighth</hi> Age, another Council was aſſembled at <hi>Nice,</hi> by the promotion of the Empreſs <hi>Irene;</hi> in which Image-Worſhip was ſtoutly maintain'd, but with ſuch kind of Arguments, that if I were for the Worſhip of Images, I ſhould be very well content to loſe the advantage of the Councils Authority, provided I might never be reproached with their Reaſoning. The Cauſe was upheld by <hi>Adrian</hi> I. then Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> who ſent the Acts of this ſecond <hi>Nicene</hi> Council to <hi>Charles</hi> the Great. <hi>Charles</hi> calls a Council of <hi>Italian, German,</hi> and <hi>French</hi> Biſhops at <hi>Frank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> in which it was determined againſt the <hi>Conſtantino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>politan</hi> Council, that <hi>Images</hi> might be <hi>retained;</hi> and ſmartly concluded againſt theſe <hi>Nicene</hi> Fathers, that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out impiety they could <hi>not be worſhipped.</hi> It was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lucky that the late beginning of <hi>Antiquity</hi> for the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of Images, ſhould be diſcredited by ſuch an Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and robb'd of all pretence to <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſality.</hi> And
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:60697:55"/>therefore <hi>Petavius,</hi> as others had done, comforts himſelf with that vain pretence that the Council of <hi>Frankford</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Petav.</hi> Dog. Th. Tom 5. Par. 2. Lib. 15.</note> underſtood not the ſence of the <hi>Nicene</hi> Biſhops. It is a <hi>vain</hi> pretence, becauſe the Acts of the <hi>Nicene</hi> Council lay before the Fathers of <hi>Frankford.</hi> But the <hi>Nicene</hi> Doctrine was condemned about 32 years after this at <hi>Paris,</hi> and was indeed generally oppoſed in the <hi>Weſtern</hi> Churches. So that it ſeems there is ſome reaſon why Image-Worſhippers ſhould not regard the <hi>Examples</hi> and <hi>Conſtitutions</hi> of the <hi>Antient,</hi> but <hi>rather</hi> of the <hi>latter</hi> times of the Church.</p>
               <p>But when began the Worſhip of the Bleſſed Virgin? And why have we forgotten her all this while? Even becauſe the <hi>Fathers</hi> forgat her firſt. 'Tis true, we find in <hi>Gregory Nazianzen</hi>'s
<note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>Greg. Naz.</hi> Orat. 18. T. 1.</note> Oration upon St. <hi>Cyprian,</hi> the ſtory of <hi>Juſtina</hi> the Virgin, calling upon the Virgin <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> to defend her againſt the unchaſt deſignes of <hi>Cyprian,</hi> who, if we may believe the Tale, was once a Conjurer at <hi>Antioch,</hi> &amp;c. But by St. <hi>Cyprian</hi>'s Life, written by <hi>Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> his Deacon, it is evident that this ſtory is void of all circumſtance of Truth.
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Bar.</hi> A. D. 250. N. 5. See Daillé <hi>de Object. Cultur.</hi> p. 51, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Baronius</hi> himſelf confeſſes as much: And by the endeavours that have been uſed to mend the Tale for the credit of <hi>G. Nazianzen,</hi> 'tis plain that there is no remedy, but it muſt go for an inexcuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble buſineſs. And therefore if ever there was cauſe from the matter of a Writing imputed to a man of great Name and Authority to conclude 'tis none of his; this equity is to be ſhewn to <hi>Gregory Nazianzen;</hi> it being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credible that a man of his Worth and Abilities, ſhould ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther invent ſuch a Lye, or be made to believe it. I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs 'tis hard on the one hand to believe that this ſtory ſhould be ſo dextrouſly ſhuffled into <hi>Nazianzen</hi>'s Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that the Impoſtor was never diſcovered; yet on the other hand, 'tis harder to believe that ſuch a man
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:60697:56"/>as he ſhould lend his Belief and his Breath to ſo abſurd a Fable.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Epiphanius</hi> alſo tells us of ſome <hi>Arabian</hi> Women that worſhipped the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epiph. Haeres.</hi> 79. lib. 3. Tom. 2. Adv. Collyrid.</note> by laying a Cake before her for ſome days, and offering it up to her, and then eating it amongſt themſelves. But that which he ſays upon this occaſion, is by no means for the comfort of her Worſhippers. <hi>Let us,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>put on the Spirits of men, and beat down the madneſs of theſe Women.</hi> I know it will be ſaid, that this reproof of thoſe that <hi>ſacrificed</hi> to the B. <hi>Virgin,</hi> reaches not thoſe that do not ſacrifice to her, but worſhip her without ſacrifice. But I am ſure <hi>Epiphanius</hi> makes no ſuch diſtinction. <hi>For,</hi> ſays he, <hi>who of the Prophets ever allowed that a Man ſhould be worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, much leſs a Woman?</hi> If it was the Doctrine of thoſe times, that the B. Virgin was more glorious than the <hi>Cherubim</hi> and <hi>Seraphim; Epiphanius</hi> did ſtrangely forget himſelf, and the Perſon he was ſpeaking of, when he ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed a Man might rather be made an Object of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Worſhip than a Woman, though the B. Virgin.</p>
               <p>For thus he goes on: <hi>Though the Virgin be a choſen Veſſel, ſhe is yet but a Woman.—The old Error ſhall not reign amongst us to leave the living God, and to worſhip things that he has made: For if he will not ſuffer the Angels to be adored, how much leſs the Daughter of</hi> Joachim <hi>and</hi> Anne, <hi>who was born to them as other Mortals are born,</hi> &amp;c. of a Father and a Mother. If the Virgin had then been invocated with Prayers and Hymns, is it to be thought that <hi>Epiphanius,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Haer.</hi> 78. Adv. Antidicom.</note> who in the foregoing diſcourſe raiſed the honour of the Virgin as high as Truth would ſuffer him, would not have ſaid it <hi>there,</hi> or diſtinguiſhed it from Sacrifice here? He ſays indeed, <hi>Let Mary be honoured; but let the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt be adored.</hi> But if it had been then as it is now, <hi>Epiphanius</hi> could not have
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:60697:56"/>avoided ſaying, <hi>Let</hi> Mary <hi>be worſhipped with Religious Invocation indeed, but let God onely be worſhipped with Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice.</hi> But does he intimate any thing of this nature? Nay, he does as plainly exclude all Religious Worſhip of her, as it was poſſible to exclude a thing which had not then obtained in the Church. For ſays he, <hi>God did not commit the Power of Baptizing to</hi> Mary, <hi>or of Bleſſing his Diſciples, or any Authority upon Earth. This onely he vouchſafed to her, to be a Sanctified Creature, and worthy to enter into his Kingdom.</hi> But if ſhe had been then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dored in any ſort, and <hi>Epiphanius</hi> had approved it, he was ſtrangely forgetful of the duty of a good Writer, not to mention it in this place at leaſt, where the plain Rules of Diſcourſe obliged him, and would have led him to it. All which, makes it evident that we are to take <hi>Worſhip</hi> or <hi>Adoration</hi> here in the proper ſence of the word, and not for <hi>viſible Sacrifices</hi> onely. And the whole place is the more unlucky to the Worſhippers of the B. Virgin, becauſe no comfort is to be had from that expreſſion of
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> honouring her, which <hi>Epiphanius</hi> requires we ſhould do. For that by this he did not mean any Religious Worſhip, is I think reaſonably plain, from what he ſays concerning <hi>Eve,</hi> in this very Diſcourſe: <hi>Let our Mother</hi> Eve
<note n="†" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>be honoured, as being formed by God.</hi> I do not know that Prayers are ſaid to <hi>Eve</hi> in the <hi>Roman</hi> Church: But I am confident <hi>Epiphanius</hi> was a ſtranger to any ſuch thing in his time. So that if we examine theſe words of <hi>worſhipping</hi> and <hi>honouring,</hi> as they ſtand in <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanius,</hi> never ſo long, they will confeſs this and no more, that we muſt think and ſpeak very honourably of <hi>Mary,</hi> as being a moſt holy woman, and the Virgin Mother of <hi>Jeſus;</hi> but that we muſt at no hand <hi>adore</hi> her with any ſort of Invocation or Religious Rites what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever. And ſo I ſhall conclude this plain buſineſs with
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:60697:57"/>the words of <hi>Epiphanius: Although</hi> Mary <hi>be excellently good and holy, and to be honoured, ſhe is not yet to be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured ſo as to be worſhipped.</hi> By which we may judge of the modeſty or underſtanding of him, whoever he was, that clap'd the name of St. <hi>Epiphanius</hi> to that fulſome
<note n="†" place="margin">De Laudib. Virg. Mar. Tom. 2. <hi>Epiph.</hi>
                  </note> Oration concerning the B. <hi>Virgin;</hi> where the Angels, <hi>Cherubim</hi> and <hi>Seraphim</hi> are brought in adoring her, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As for what we have concerning the B. Virgin in the Liturgy ſaid to be St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi>'s, and pretended to be tranſlated by <hi>Eraſmus,</hi> it is all manifeſt Interpolation, being directly contrary to St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi>'s Doctrine in his undoubted Writings. Could he that affirms, that if Chriſt were not by
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> in Hebr, <hi>c.</hi> 1. Hom. 2.</note> nature the Son of God, he had been inſeriour to the Angels, affirm alſo that the Bleſſed Virgin (who is <hi>naturally</hi> no Goddeſs) is <hi>incomparably more glorious than the Cherubim and Seraphim?</hi> Or that ſhe was <hi>unſpotted,</hi> whom he plainly notes for
<note n="†" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Joan.</hi> c 2. Hom. 20.</note> Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Deſire of Worldly Glory, and ſuppoſes to be checked by <hi>Jeſus</hi> for it? Concerning the Bleſſed Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, and the priviledge ſhe had by being the Mother of <hi>Jeſus,</hi> they ſpake in thoſe days, as we of the Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion now do. St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> be witneſs for this, in the place laſt cited. <q>When thou heareſt that Woman ſaying, <hi>Bleſſed is the Womb that bare thee, and the Paps that give thee ſuck;</hi> and then himſelf anſwering, <hi>Yea, rather bleſſed are they that hear the Word of God and keep it.</hi> Do not think that theſe words argued con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of his Mother, but that he would ſhew how little it would profit her that ſhe was his Mother, if ſhe were not exceedingly good and faithful. But if it profited <hi>Mary</hi> nothing at all, that <hi>Christ</hi> was born of her, unleſs ſhe had the virtue of the Soul, much leſs good will it do us, to have an excellent <hi>Father, Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> or <hi>Child,</hi> whilſt we have none of their Virtue—
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:60697:57"/>For we are to place our hope of ſalvation in nothing, next to the Grace of God, but onely in our proper good Actions and Qualities. For if that Relation which <hi>Mary</hi> had to <hi>Christ,</hi> were a thing of it ſelf pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable, the Jews had found it ſo in ſome degree. For <hi>Chriſt</hi> was akin to them after the Fleſh; and ſo had the <hi>City</hi> in which he was born, and ſo had his <hi>Brethren.</hi> But whilſt his Brethren did juſt what pleaſed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, the honour they had to be of kin to him, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fited them not at all, but they were condemned with the reſt of the World.</q> A great deal more to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe you may find in this excellent Father, and that in the place by me cited; by which you may ſee what the ſtrain of that Age was, as to the Bleſſed Virgin, and how very unlike to that which was taken up in following times; ſome inſtances of which, we have in <hi>Homilies</hi> falſly attributed to
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>De uno Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſlatore. In Samaritanam,</hi> &amp;c. Tom. 6.</note> St. <hi>Chryſoſtom.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In ſhort, if we ſet aſide ſpurious Writings, ſuch as the Sermon concerning the <hi>Aſſumption</hi> of the Bleſſed <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin,</hi> publiſhed in St. <hi>Hierom</hi>'s Works, and attributed by ſome to <hi>Sophronius,</hi> but was moſt certainly written long after they were both dead; and the two Prayers (at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed to
<note n="*" place="margin">Tom. 4.</note> St. <hi>Ambroſe) Preparatory to Maſs;</hi> in the ſecond of which, God is deſired (according to the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius of after times) to <hi>inſpire the Bleſſed Virgin</hi> firſt, and then the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and then the <hi>Martyrs</hi> and <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors,</hi> with the thought of <hi>praying to God for the Prieſt:</hi> But the beſt learned amongſt the Papiſts have been a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed to produce theſe Prayers as St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi>'s, they are ſo evidently ſuppoſitions. If we ſet aſide alſo the Book of <hi>Meditations</hi> which the <hi>Latin Rhymes</hi> that are in it convince of Novelty; and the Treatiſe of the <hi>Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption,</hi> attributed to St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> and the Sermons un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his name upon the Feaſt of the <hi>Annuntiation,</hi> which
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:60697:58"/>could be none of his, becauſe that Feaſt was not then in being: And in one word, all thoſe Writings which Learned men of the <hi>Roman</hi> Communion have themſelves confeſſed to be at leaſt doubtful, though they had for ſome time gone under the names of <hi>Fathers</hi> of the <hi>Fourth</hi> Age. Setting theſe aſide, I ſay, we find but mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate things ſpoken of the Bleſſed Virgin.</p>
               <p>After all the pains that have been taken to make ſome of her <hi>Feſtivals</hi> Ancient, it is more than probable that as yet ſhe had none; and that the Fathers of the Fourth Age, who are cited for one or two of them, have been, without their conſent, made to ſpeak the ſence of after-Ages, that were loath to be deſtitute of all pretence from Antiquity, for making the honour of the <hi>Bleſſed Virgin</hi> out-ſhine all that was done to others <hi>Martyrs</hi> and <hi>Saints.</hi> For the
<note n="*" place="margin">Conſtit. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſt. l. 8. c. 33.</note> 
                  <hi>Conſtitutions</hi> do not ſo much as men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion one of her <hi>Feſtivals,</hi> where one would think they ſhould have omitted none.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Salutation</hi> of <hi>Ave Maria</hi> has now for ſome time run through the Religion of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> in publick and private Devotions; but in this Age no Example or Recommendation of any ſuch thing is to be met withal.</p>
               <p>No, nor one Prayer to her, do we yet hear of; which plainly ſhews, that (whatever the ſuperſtition of ſome one private Perſon or other might be, of which we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not affirm or deny any thing) her Worſhip was no part of the Religion of the Age. If you would know the firſt bold man, after the <hi>Collyridians,</hi> that brought her into the Church to be invocated; <hi>Nicephorus</hi> will tell you it was
<note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>Niceph.</hi> Hiſt. l. 15. c. 28.</note> one <hi>Peter Fullo,</hi> a <hi>Biſhop</hi> indeed, but an <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tychian,</hi> who found out four very profitable things, if you will believe <hi>Nicephorus;</hi> one whereof, was, that the <hi>holy Name of the Virgin ſhould be called upon in every Prayer.</hi>
                  <pb n="109" facs="tcp:60697:58"/>How the invention of this man was entertain'd, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſay: He lived near the ſixth Age. But neither is thus much Antiquity to be boaſted of, nor was it for the credit of the Innovation, to have an <hi>Heretick</hi> for its Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor.</p>
               <p>The Church was full of the <hi>Memories</hi> of the <hi>Martyrs;</hi> but as yet the <hi>Bleſſed Virgin</hi> had none. What a ſtrange thing was it, that <hi>Theodoret,</hi> who ran the honour of the Martyrs to that height, that it requires ſome Candour <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> bring him down with ſafety and honour; that he, I ſay ſhould make no mention at all of the <hi>Bleſſed Virgin,</hi> and the Solemnities that were due to her: and that in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Diſcourſe where he profeſſedly brings in the <hi>Martyrs,</hi> ſupplanting thoſe <hi>Doemons</hi> which had been ſo long ſerved by the Pagan World. He could name
<note n="*" place="margin">Theod. <hi>de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ndis Graec. affect.</hi> De Martyr ad Fin.</note> 
                  <hi>Peter, Paul, Thomas, Sergius, Marcellus, Leontius, Antoninus,</hi> and <hi>Mauritius.</hi> Do we think the <hi>Bleſſed Virgin</hi> had been left to be underſtood amongſt <hi>the other Saints</hi> that had their <hi>Solemnities</hi> alſo, if ſhe had had even in <hi>Theodoret</hi>'s time any at all? But why ſhould we talk of her <hi>Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,</hi> when as yet her <hi>Reliques</hi> were not ſound, nor in all likelihood ſought for? ſince if they had, 'tis not to be doubted, but thoſe Monks, or others like them, that went up and down with <hi>the Bones of Martyrs, if indeed they were Martyrs Bones,</hi> would have gratified the curio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of devout People, with ſome of thoſe Reliques that Poſterity a long time after was bleſſed with; <hi>viz.</hi> ſome of the <hi>Bleſſed Virgin's Hair,</hi> her <hi>Combs,</hi> her <hi>Hood,</hi> her <hi>Slipper,</hi> her <hi>Eſpouſal Ring,</hi> nay and ſome of her <hi>Milk</hi> too, with ſuch other things, which came not to light, till ſome Ages after the zeal of Reliques began in the Church.</p>
               <p>But when once Devotion began to turn towards her, no time was loſt; and though it was late firſt, yet her Service preſently overtook, and at laſt went beyond the
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:60697:59"/>honour that was done to the other <hi>Saints</hi> and <hi>Martyrs.</hi> The <hi>Thirteenth</hi> Age produced a Relique of the <hi>B. Virgin,</hi> ſo famous for the Miracle that brought it into <hi>Europe,</hi> and for the Miracles that have been done by it ever ſince, that the Reliques of the other Saints are nothing to it: And that is her Houſe once at <hi>Nazareth,</hi> where ſhe was Born, and viſited by the <hi>Angel;</hi> which Houſe was car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried by <hi>Angels</hi> out of <hi>Paleſtine,</hi> into <hi>Dalmatia,</hi> and from thence into <hi>Italy,</hi> where it now ſtands, and is our Lady of <hi>Loretto</hi>'s Chappel. By the <hi>Forthteenth Century</hi> ſhe had gain'd no leſs than ſeven <hi>Feſtivals</hi> in the year, which I mention to ſhew the growing Devotion of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church towards the <hi>B. Virgin;</hi> not that we make this any great matter of complaint; no, though they were twice ſeven, if the Facts upon which they were grounded were true, and the grounds reaſonable, and God onely were worſhipped in the celebration of ſuch <hi>Festi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vals.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The later Doctors have made too much amends for the modeſty of the Ancient Fathers, who ſpake indeed of her very honourably, but within bounds. The World was ſomething altered in the middle of the <hi>Seventh</hi> Age, if Pope <hi>Martin</hi> ſaid what we find in
<note n="†" place="margin">Collectan. <hi>Anast.</hi> p. 73.</note> 
                  <hi>Anaſtaſius: Whoever does not Honour and Adore the</hi> Bleſſed Virgin <hi>the Mother of God, let him be accur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</hi> Of which Curſe,
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>German.</hi> in Biblioth. P. Tom. 12. p. 704.</note> 
                  <hi>Germanus</hi> the Patriarch of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople,</hi> was in no danger, if he addreſſed himſelf in this manner to the Bleſſed Virgin: <hi>No body is repleni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed with the knowledge of God, but by thee, O moſt Holy. No body is ſaved but by thee, O Mother of God. No body is delivered from danger, but by thee, O thou beloved of God.</hi> Again: <hi>Thou having the power of a Mother with God, dost beyond meaſure gain Pardon for them who ſin beyond meaſure. For it cannot be that thou ſhouldſt not be heard,
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:60697:59"/>becauſe to all purpoſes and in all things, and through all things God obeys thee as his true and immaculate Mother.</hi> This was pretty well for the <hi>eighth</hi> Age; as likewiſe was that of <hi>Damaſcene,</hi> who calls the B. Virgin,
<note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>Joh. Damaſc.</hi> lib. 4. c. 15.</note> 
                  <hi>The Lady and Go verneſs of all Creatures.</hi> No wonder therefore that Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal <hi>Peter Damian</hi> coming long after theſe, telleth her that ſhe <hi>comes before the Altar of Reconciliation, not asking on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but commanding; as a Lady, not as a Servant.</hi> I know not whether he was the Author of thoſe glorious Titles which have ſince furniſhed ſome of the <hi>Hymns</hi> that we meet with in the <hi>Offices</hi> of the <hi>Bleſſed Virgin?</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Hom. 46, de Nativ. B <hi>Mar.</hi> 1. Tom. 2 p. 106.</note> 
                  <hi>The Queen of the World, The Window of Heaven, The Gate of Paradiſe, The Tabernacle of God, The Star of the Sea, The Heavenly Ladder, by which the Heavenly King came down to us below, and by which man who grovelled upon the ground, aſcends in exaltation to Heaven.</hi> But <hi>Anſelm</hi> that lived in the ſame Age with him, ſpeaks more fully:
<note n="‖" place="margin">
                     <hi>Anſelm.</hi> Cant. de Excell. Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin. c. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>As God is the Father, and God of all things, by his power creating all things; ſo</hi> Bleſſed Mary <hi>the Mother of God, reſtoring all things by her Merits, is the Mother and Lady of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe.</hi> Which agrees very well with that reaſon he had given before, why her Son went to Heaven before her:
<note n="†" place="margin">Ibid. c. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>Perhaps, O Lord, leſt thy Court in Heaven ſhould ſtand in doubt whom it ſhould rather go out to meet,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">See <hi>Anſwer to Jeſuits Chall.</hi> from p. 478. to p. 495.</note> 
                  <hi>thee their Lord coming to take poſſeſſion of thy Kingdom, or her their Lady aſcending to that Kingdom alſo, which belonged to her by a Mothers right.</hi> To this nothing could be added in ſo little a time beyond <hi>Bonaventure</hi>'s <hi>Pſalter,</hi> who taking the <hi>Pſalms</hi> of <hi>David,</hi> put in <hi>Lady</hi> inſtead of <hi>Lord,</hi> in this manner: <hi>O come let us ſing unto our Lady,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Let every thing that hath breath praiſe our Lady.</hi> But not content with this, he framed the
<note n="*" place="margin">Pſalt. <hi>Bonav.</hi> p. 111, 112, Pariſ.</note> 
                  <hi>Athanaſian</hi> Creed to her Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice too, beginning thus: <hi>Whoſoever will be ſaved, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all things it is neceſſary that he ſhould hold a firm Faith
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:60697:60"/>concerning the Virgin</hi> Mary; <hi>which Faith except a man keep whole and undefiled, without doubt he ſhall periſh ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtingly.</hi> And now whoſoever ſhall conſider the <hi>Lita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies</hi> of the <hi>Bleſſed Virgin,</hi> and her <hi>Roſaries,</hi> and the <hi>Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi> and <hi>Hymns</hi> of her <hi>Saturday</hi>'s Office, and her <hi>Pſalters,</hi> and the vaſt number of Books of Devotion to her, and the Worſhip that is accordingly given to her in preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>Catholick</hi> Countries; whoſoever ſhall conſider what they ſay to her in thoſe <hi>Prayers</hi> and <hi>Hymns,</hi> &amp;c. which the <hi>Speculum Beatoe Virginis,</hi> juſt now publiſhed, has put together, may perhaps find there are Cauſes of <hi>Horror</hi> which Monſieur <hi>de Meaux</hi> is not ſo much concerned at as he ought to be: He may juſtly fear, that if the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation did not give ſome little check, neither would theſe exceſſes ſtop here; though in many places no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing now remains to be done, but without any farther reſervedneſs, to erect Altars proper to the <hi>Bleſſed Virgin</hi> in every Church, as the
<note n="†" place="margin">Trigautii Exp. ad Sinas. lib. 5. c. 15.20.</note> 
                  <hi>Jeſuites</hi> began to do in <hi>Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>O Bleſſed God, look down in thy mercy upon the miſerable eſtate of <hi>Christianity</hi> in ſo many parts of the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> World!</p>
               <p>When the <hi>Bleſſed Virgin</hi> foretold <hi>that all Generations ſhould call her Bleſſed,</hi> did ſhe mean that all Generations would Worſhip her; would Worſhip her Images and Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures; would make her a <hi>Mediatrix</hi> between God and man; would aſcribe to her the power not of prevailing with <hi>Jeſus</hi> only for any thing, but of commanding him too; would offer <hi>Jeſus</hi> himſelf a Sacrifice in her Honour; ſhould burn Incenſe to her, would uſe <hi>Roſaries, Hours,</hi> and <hi>Pſalters</hi> for her eſpecial Invocation and Service; would inſtitute and maintain Fraternities for that Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice;
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:60697:60"/>would build Temples and Chappels to her, and Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars, and by moſt ſolemn Invocation every-where, and by proper Rites of Religious Worſhip, and by letting Devotion run out to her more than to our Lord Jeſus himſelf, to agnize her to be the <hi>Lady of Heaven and Earth,</hi> the <hi>Queen of the World?</hi> No, ſhe did not mean thus, in ſaying that <hi>all Generations ſhould call her Bleſſed:</hi> For thus <hi>all Generations</hi> have not ſerved her. Nothing of all this was done to her for <hi>ſeveral Generations</hi> after <hi>Christ;</hi> nor any thing of it in compariſon till the dregs of Time, till the decay of Learning and Piety, made way for groſs Superſtition.</p>
               <p>The firſt beginnings of theſe Corruptions were more general, but the Improvements of them were chiefly owing to the <hi>See</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> which as it grew in power and greatneſs, ſo it protected thoſe Abuſes more effectually. A Character very ill-beſeeming a Church that pretends to be the <hi>Pillar and Ground of Truth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Wit of Man could not deviſe any thing more ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable to Errour, to make it ſpread in the World; and to fix it, than that a powerful <hi>See</hi> graſping at <hi>Supremacy,</hi> and pretending to <hi>Infallibility,</hi> ſhould take it under her wing.</p>
               <p>This <hi>See</hi> is the Source of all thoſe Oppoſitions, which they have met with that demanded a Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; it is this <hi>See</hi> alone which hath obſtructed a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Reformation, when <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> was otherwiſe well diſpoſed towards it.</p>
               <p>Therefore when Reformation by common conſent was made Impoſſible by the <hi>See</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:60697:61"/>but that the National Churches ſhould reform themſelves?</p>
               <p>Our Reformation was a return to Primitive Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity; and that it may prove a leading example, let us pray without ceaſing, That God <hi>would bring into the way of Truth all ſuch as have erred and are decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Faults to be Corrected.</head>
            <p>PAge 81, ſeventh line from the bottom, for <hi>Conſciences</hi> read <hi>Conceſſions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>P. 82 l. 3. for <hi>Reconciled</hi> r. <hi>Recommended.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>P. 80 l. 6. for <hi>them</hi> read <hi>then.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>P. 88 l. 7. for <hi>ſafely</hi> r. <hi>falſly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>P. 92 l. 3. for <hi>Prayers</hi> r. <hi>Praiſes.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:60697:61"/>
            <head>A Catalogue of ſome Diſcourſes Sold by <hi>T. Baſſet</hi> at the <hi>George</hi> in <hi>Fleetſtreet.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">1. A <hi>Perſwaſive</hi> to an <hi>Ingenuous Tryal</hi> of <hi>Opinons</hi> in <hi>Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The Difference of the Caſe between the Separation of the Proteſtants from the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration of Diſſenters from the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. A Diſcourſe about the Charge of Novelty upon the Reformed Church of <hi>England,</hi> made by the Papiſts ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing us the Queſtion, <hi>Where was our Religion before</hi> Luther?</p>
            <p n="4">4. The Proteſtant Reſolution of Faith, being an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to Three Queſtions. I. How far we muſt depend on the Authority of the Church for the true Sence of Scripture. II. Whether a viſible Succeſſion from Chriſt to this day makes a Church, which has this viſible Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion an Infallible Interpreter of Scripture; and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther no Church which has not this viſible Succeſſion, can teach the true Sence of Scripture. III. Whether the Church of <hi>England</hi> can make out ſuch a viſible Succeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on?</p>
            <p n="5">5. A Diſcourſe concerning a Guide in matters of Faith; with Reſpect eſpecially to the Romiſh pretence of the Neceſſity of ſuch a one as is Infallible.</p>
            <p n="6">6. A Diſcourſe about Tradition; ſhewing what is meant by it, and what Tradition is to be Recieved, and what Tradition is to be Rejected.</p>
            <p n="7">7. A Diſcourſe concerning the Unity of the Catholick Church, maintained in the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">
               <pb facs="tcp:60697:62"/> 8. A Diſcourſe concerning the Neceſſity of Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, with reſpect to the Errours and Corruptions of the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> In two Parts.</p>
            <p n="9">9. A Diſcourſe concerning the Object of Religious Worſhip: or, a Scripture-Proof of the Unlawfulneſs of giving any Religious Worſhip to any other Being beſides the one Supreme God.</p>
            <p n="10">10. A Diſcourſe againſt Tranſubſtantiation.</p>
            <p n="11">11. A Diſcourſe concerning the Adoration of the Hoſt, as it is Taught and Practiſed in the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> Wherein an Anſwer is given to <hi>T. G.</hi> on that Subject, and to Monſieur <hi>Bocleau</hi>'s late Book <hi>de Adora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione Euchariſtioe. Paris,</hi> 1685.</p>
            <p n="12">12. A Diſcourſe concerning Invocation of Saints.</p>
            <p n="13">13. A Diſcourſe concerning the Devotions of the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="14">14. A Diſcourſe concerning the Celebration of Divine Service in an Unknown Tongue.</p>
            <p n="15">15. A Diſcourſe concerning Auricular Confeſſion, as it is Preſcribed by the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> and Practiſed in the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> With a Poſtſcript on occaſion of a Book lately printed in <hi>France,</hi> called, <hi>Hiſtoria Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſionis Auricularis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="16">16. A Diſcourſe concerning the Worſhip of the Bleſſed Virgin and the Saints; with an Account of the Begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings and Riſe of it amongſt Chriſtians: In Anſwer to Monſieur <hi>de Meaux</hi>'s Appeal to the Fourth Age in his Expoſition, and his Paſtoral Letter.</p>
            <p>A <hi>Collection</hi> of <hi>Caſes</hi> and other <hi>Diſcourſes</hi> lately written to recover Diſſenters to the <hi>Communion</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England, by ſome Divines of the City of</hi> London. In two Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumes in Quarto.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
